<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE  TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI.2//EN" "./schanges-tei.dtd">
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Southern Changes.  Volume 22, Number 2, 2000</title>
            <author>Staff</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>staff</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory University. Permission is granted to 
download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to 
the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational
purposes, provided  
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact 
either: Southern Changes Web Project or Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic 
collections and services, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>2003</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Southern Changes Web Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Southern Changes.  Volume 22, Number 2. 2000</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is produced in conjunction with the  
Southern Changes Web Project at Emory University and the Southern Regional Council, 133 Carnegie Way, Suite 900, Atlanta, GA 30303-1024</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="sc22-2.000" n="Southern Changes 22:2" type="Issue">
            <head>Southern Changes.  Volume 22, Number 2, 2000</head>
                <div2 id="sc22-2.marable.000" n="Facing the Demon Head On: Institutional Racism and the Prison Industrial Complex" type="Article">
               <head>Facing the Demon Head On: Institutional Racism and the Prison Industrial Complex</head>
               <docAuthor>By Manning Marable</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>

<p>As long as black people have lived in America, they have experienced some version of institutional or structural racism. During slavery, African Americans were defined as private property or chattel, purchased and sold on auction blocks. In the period following Reconstruction until the early 1960s, African Americans, especially in the South, lived under the oppressive restrictions of Jim Crow segregation. In the northern states, blacks were generally permitted to vote and had access to most public accommodations, but were forced by racial covenants and restrictive laws to live in ghettoes. Under each successive racial formation, African Americans and their white allies formed political and social protest movements, which ultimately transformed the nature of their society. In the antebellum South, there were uprisings and day-to-day resistance by enslaved African Americans, and in the northern states an abolitionist movement developed that contributed to the establishment of the Republican Party. Under Jim Crow, leaders such as Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr., Fannie Lou Hamer, James Farmer, Ella Baker, and a broad coalition of civil rights organizations mounted a series of nonviolent, direct action campaigns that directly led to the desegregation of the South. In the northern states, African Americans employed a variety of strategies, from the labor union organizing of A. Philip Randolph and Bayard Rustin, to the mass political mobilization efforts that elected thousands of public officials, to achieve greater black representation at all levels of society. Progress was frequently slow, but the black freedom movement was generally successful in identifying the specific institutional barriers to African-American equality, and then ultimately finding the appropriate tactics to challenge them.</p>
<p>In the past three decades, the structure and character of American institutional racism has changed dramatically.  We can measure the advances of African Americans in many ways.  The number of black elected officials, barely 100 in 1964, has climbed above 10,000; the black consumer market has grown from $70 billion in 1980 to over $350 billion today.  There is an affluent and substantial black middle class, and the economic expansion of the 1990s greatly improved the quality of life even for millions of working class and low-income households.  The unemployment rate among African Americans has now fallen to about 7 percent which, according to sociologist William Julius Wilson, is "the lowest since the Bureau of Labor Statistics began compiling comparable data by race in 1972."</p>
<p>However, this new prosperity for the black middle class obscures a very real crisis for millions of other African Americans. The unprecedented expansion of what a number of scholars increasingly describe as a "prison industrial complex" has created an oppressively new context for the articulation of racial politics. According to a recently published Justice Department report (August 2000), the total population of the nation's jails and prisons exceeded two million at the end of 1999. The dynamic and seemingly unchecked growth of the U.S. prison population has many profound consequences--politically, economically and socially--for all people of color. </p>
<p>Beginning in the 1960s and 1970s, for a variety of reasons, rates of violent crime, including murder, rape and robbery, increased dramatically, especially in urban areas. By the late 1970s, nearly one half of all Americans were afraid to walk within a mile of their homes at night, and 90 percent responded in surveys that the U.S. criminal justice system was not dealing harshly enough with criminals. Politicians like Richard Nixon, George Wallace, and Ronald Reagan began to campaign successfully on the theme of "Law and Order." The death penalty, which was briefly outlawed by the Supreme Court, was reinstated. Local, state, and federal expenditures for law enforcement rose sharply. Behind much of the anti-crime rhetoric was a not-too-subtle racial dimension, the projection of crude stereotypes about the link between criminality and black people. Rarely did these politicians observe that minority and poor people, not the white middle class, were statistically much more likely to experience violent crimes of all kinds. The argument was made that law enforcement officers should be given much greater latitude in suppressing crime, that sentences should be lengthened and made mandatory, and that prisons should be designed not for the purpose of rehabilitation, but punishment.</p>
<p>	As a result, there was a rapid expansion in the personnel of the criminal justice system, as well as the construction of new prisons. What occurred in New York State, for example, was typical of what happened nationally. From 1817 to 1981, New York had opened thirty-three state prisons.  From 1982 to 1999, another thirty-eight state prisons were constructed. The state's prison population at the time of the Attica prison revolt in September 1971 was about 12,500.  By 1999, there were over 71,000 prisoners in New York State correctional facilities. [Numbers from some southern state should be substituted here, rather than NY.]</p>
<p>	In 1974, the number of Americans incarcerated in all state prisons stood at 187,500. By 1991, the number had reached 711,700. Nearly two-thirds of all state prisoners in 1991 had less than a high school education. One third of all prisoners were unemployed at the time of their arrests.  Incarceration rates by the end of the 1980s had soared to unprecedented rates, especially for black Americans. As of December 1989, the total U.S. prison population, including federal institutions, exceeded one million for the first time in history, an incarceration rate of the general population of one out of every 250 citizens. For African Americans, the rate was over 700 per 100,000, or about seven times more than for whites. About one half of all prisoners were black.  Twenty-three percent of all black males in their twenties were either in jail or prison, on parole, probation, or awaiting trial. The rate of incarceration of black Americans in 1989 had even surpassed that experienced by blacks who still lived under the apartheid regime of South Africa.</p>
<p>	By the early 1990s, rates for all types of violent crime began to plummet. But the laws, which sent offenders to prison, were made even more severe. Children were increasingly viewed as adults in courts, and subjected to harsher penalties. Laws like California's "three strikes and you're out" eliminated the possibility of parole for repeat offenders. The vast majority of these new prisoners were nonviolent offenders, and many of these were convicted of drug offenses that carried long prison terms. Nationwide, African Americans and Latinos comprised 24.3 percent of the population in 1999, but represented 63.6 percent of state and federal prisoners and 78.8 percent of state prisoners convicted of drug offenses. The pattern of racial bias in these statistics is confirmed by the research of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, which found that while African Americans today constitute only 14 percent of all drug users nationally, they are 35 percent of all drug arrests, 55 percent of all drug convictions, and 75 percent of all prison admissions for drug offenses. Currently, the racial proportions of those under some type of correctional supervision, including parole and probation, are one-in-fifteen for young white males, one-in-ten for young Latino males, and one-in-three for young African-American males. Statistically today, more than eight out of every ten African-American males will be arrested at some point in their lifetime. [These numbers should be updated from the new Justice Dept. report.  They are even worse.]</p>
<p>	The latest innovation in American corrections is termed "special housing units" (SHU), but which prisoners also generally refer to as The Box. SHUs are uniquely designed solitary confinement cells, in which prisoners are locked down for twenty-three hours a day for months or even years at a time. SHU cellblocks are electronically monitored, prefabricated structures of concrete and steel, about fourteen feet long and eight feet wide, amounting to 120 square feet of space. The two inmates who are confined in each cell, however, actually have only about sixty square feet of usable space, or thirty square feet per person. All meals are served to prisoners through a thin slot cut into the steel door. The toilet unit, sink, and shower are all located in the cell.  Prisoners are permitted one hour "exercise time" each day in a small concrete balcony, surrounded by heavy security wire, directly connected with their SHU cells.  Educational and rehabilitation programs for SHU prisoners are prohibited. Although Amnesty International and human rights groups in the U.S. have widely condemned SHUs, claiming that such forms of imprisonment constitute the definition of torture under international law, many states are increaseing the number of SHU facilities in their state prisons. As of 1998, California had constructed 2,942 SHU beds, followed by Mississippi (1,756), Arizona (1,728), Virginia (1,267), Texas (1,229), Louisiana (1,048) and Florida (1,000). Solitary confinement, which historically had been defined even by corrections officials as an extreme disciplinary measure, is becoming increasingly the norm.</p>
<p>The introduction of SHUs reflects a general mood in the country that the growing penal population is essentially beyond redemption. If convicted felons cease to be viewed as human beings, why should they be treated with any humanity? This punitive spirit was behind the Republican-controlled Congress and President Clinton's decision in 1995 to eliminate inmate eligibility for federal Pell Grant awards for higher education. As of 1994, 23,000 prisoners throughout the U.S. had received Pell Grants, averaging about $1,500 per award. The total amount of educational support granted prisoners, $35 million, represented only 0.6 percent of all Pell Grant funding nationally. Many studies have found that prisoners who participate in higher education programs and especially those who complete college degrees have significantly lower rates of recidivism. For all prison inmates, for example, recidivism averages between 50 to 70 percent. Federal parolees have a recidivism rate of 40 percent. Prisoners with a college education have recidivism rates of only 5 to 10 percent. Given the high success ratio of prisoners who complete advanced degree work and the relatively low cost of public investment, such educational programs should make sense. But following the federal government's lead, many states have also ended their tuition benefits programs for state prisoners.</p>
<p>	What are the economic costs for American society of the vast expansion of our prison-industrial complex? According to criminal justice researcher David Barlow at the University of Wisconsin at Milwaukee, between 1980 and 2000, the combined expenditures of federal, state, and local governments on police have increased about 400 percent. Corrections expenditures for building new prisons, upgrading existing facilities, hiring more guards, and related costs, increased approximately 1000 percent. Although it currently costs about $70,000 to construct a typical prison cell, and about $25,000 annually to supervise and maintain each prisoner, the U.S. is currently building 1,725 new prison beds per week.</p>
<p>The driving ideological and cultural forces that rationalize and justify mass incarceration are the white American public's stereotypical perception about race and crime. As Andrew Hacker noted in 1995, "Quite clearly, 'black crime' does not make people think about tax evasion or embezzling from brokerage firms. Rather, the offenses generally associated with blacks are those  . . . involving violence." A number of researchers have found that racial stereotypes of African Americans--as "violent," "aggressive," "hostile" and "short-tempered"--greatly influence whites' judgments about crime. Generally, most whites are inclined to give black and Latino defendants more severe judgments of guilt and lengthier prison sentences than whites who commit identical crimes. Racial bias has been well established especially in capital cases, where killers of white victims are much more likely to receive the death penalty than those who murder African Americans.</p>
<p>The greatest victims of these racialized processes of unequal justice, of course, are African-American and Latino young people. In April 2000, utilizing national and state data compiled by the FBI, the Justice Department, and six leading foundations issued a comprehensive study that documented vast racial disparities at every level of the juvenile justice process. African Americans under age 18 comprise 15 percent of their national age group, yet they currently represent 26 percent of all those who are arrested. After entering the criminal justice system, white and black juveniles with the same records are treated in radically different ways. According to the Justice Department's study, among white youth offenders, 66 percent are referred to juvenile courts, while only 31 percent of the African-American youth are taken there. Blacks comprise 44 percent of those detained in juvenile jails, 46 percent of all those tried in adult criminal courts, as well as 58 percent of all juveniles who are warehoused in adult prison.  In practical terms, this means that for young African Americans who are arrested and charged with a crime, that they are more than six times more likely to be assigned to prison that white youth offenders.</p>
<p>For those young people who have never been to prison before, African Americans are nine times more likely than whites to be sentenced to juvenile prisons. For youths charged with drug offenses, blacks are forty-eight times more likely than whites to be sentenced to juvenile prison. White youths charged with violent offenses are incarcerated on average for 193 days after trial; by contrast, African-American youths are held 254 days, and Latino youths are incarcerated 305 days. [is this covered in rick mcdevitt's piece?]</p>
<p>The August 2000 report of the US Justice Department finds that 9.4 percent of black men ages twenty-five to twenty-nine were in state and federal prisons in 1999, almost ten times the rate for white men in their late twenties. Among Hispanic males in this same age group, over 3 percent were incarcerated.</p>
<p>What seems clear is that a new leviathan of racial inequality has been constructed across our country.  It lacks the brutal simplicity of the old Jim Crow system, with its omnipresent "white" and "colored" signs. Yet it is in many respects potentially far more devastating, because it presents itself to the world as a system that is truly color-blind. The black freedom struggle of the 1960s was successful largely because it convinced a majority of white middle class Americans that it was economically inefficient, and that politically it could not be sustained or justified. The movement utilized the power of creative disruption, making it impossible for the old system of white prejudice and power to function in the same old ways it had for decades. For Americans who still believe in racial equality and social justice, we cannot stand silent while millions of our fellow citizens are being destroyed all around us. The racialized prison industrial complex is the great moral and political challenge of our time.</p>
<p>For several years, I have lectured in New York's famous Sing Sing prison, as part of a master's degree program sponsored by the New York Theological Seminary. During my last visit several months ago, I noticed that correctional officials had erected a large yellow sign over the door at the public entrance to the prison. The sign reads: "Through these doors pass some of the finest corrections professionals in the world." I asked Reverend Bill Webber, the director of the prison's educational program, and several prisoners what they thought about the sign. Bill answered bluntly, "demonic." One of the M.A. students, a thirty-five-year-old Latino named Tony, agreed with Bill's assessment, but added, "let us face the demon head on." There are now over two million Americans who are incarcerated. It is time to face the demon head on.</p>
	    </div2>
            <div2 id="sc22-2.bright.001" n="A Smooth Road to the Death House" type="Article">
               <head>A Smooth Road to the Death House</head>
               <docAuthor>By Stephen Bright</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>
<argument><p>    Stephen B. Bright lectures at Yale Law School and is director of the Southern Center for Human Rights in Atlanta. </p></argument>
<p>Regardless of the extent of compassion in his "compassionate conservatism," Gov. George W. Bush of Texas could show some concern for justice by following the example of his presidential campaign chairman in Illinois, Gov. George Ryan, who earlier this year announced a moratorium on executions in his state. </p>
<p>Governor Ryan is concerned that an innocent person might be executed. There are now 161 people on death row in Illinois. Since the death penalty was reinstituted there in 1977, thirteen people who were condemned to die have been exonerated. Twelve have been put to death, and there were serious questions of innocence in the case of one of those twelve. </p>
<p>Three people were freed from death row in Illinois after a journalism class at Northwestern University established their innocence and proved that someone else had committed the crimes. One condemned man came within two days of execution. </p>
<p>Mr. Bush has presided over more than one hundred executions in the state that leads the nation in the number of executions since the death penalty was reinstated and has never expressed a doubt about the assembly-line process by which Texas courts dispatch people to its execution chamber. But because the system to provide lawyers for the poor is so weak in Texas, there is reason to be even more concerned about the risk of wrongful executions there than in Illinois. </p>
<p>And although an investigation by the CBS News program "60 Minutes" contributed to the release of a man under a death sentence in Texas in 1990, and the documentary film "The Thin Blue Line" won the release of another in 1989, there are too many cases--more than 450--moving far too fast for most of them to get the attention of journalists or journalism classes. </p>
<p>In Illinois, many people facing the death penalty are represented by public defenders like those working in Chicago for the highly respected homicide unit of the Cook County Public Defender, which specializes in the defense of capital cases. </p>
<p>Texas has no public defender system.   Instead, the presiding judge in a case assigns a lawyer to represent the accused. Judges have sometimes chosen lawyers with an eye toward getting cases disposed of quickly, and in a survey of judges for the Texas bar association last year, more than half agreed that lawyers' contributions to judges' election campaigns at least sometimes influence the appointments. </p>
<p> The lawyers are compensated at far below what attorneys can make for less demanding work. They are often denied the assistance of investigators and experts necessary to make an independent determination of a defendant's guilt. </p>
<p>The Texas courts do not even require that defense counsels remain awake during trial. The lawyer representing a defendant named George McFarland, who is now on death row, repeatedly fell asleep and snored during his trial in Houston. </p>
<p>Texas' highest criminal court--made up of judges chosen in partisan elections, some of whom ran on platforms supporting the death penalty--upheld the death sentences in Mr. McFarland's trial and two others in which defense attorneys fell asleep. One of those defendants, Carl Johnson, was executed in 1995. </p>
<p>Snoring through trials is only the most visible example of the Texas system's problems. Yet last year Governor Bush vetoed a bill, passed unanimously by both houses of the Texas legislature, that would have taken a few modest steps toward creating public defender offices in Texas counties. </p>
<p>Besides lacking these offices, which pay lawyers a salary to specialize in defending the poor, Texas, unlike Illinois and most other states, also has no office that specializes in representing those sentenced to death in the later stages of appeal, a process called post-conviction review. Texas had such a program, but it was shut down five years ago when Congress eliminated its federal financing. Texas judges have appointed lawyers who have missed deadlines, costing the death row inmates they represent the review of their cases. Other lawyers failed to investigate the cases and filed documents that failed to identify any issues that should be reviewed. </p>
<p>As one Texas judge observed, dissenting in a case in which a condemned man was assigned an inexperienced lawyer with serious health problems, the lawyer's failure to recognize and present any issues "certainly makes it easier on everyone--no need for the attorney, the state, or this court to consider any potential challenges to anything that happened at trial." </p>
<p>Nationwide, more than eighty people have been released from death rows after their innocence was established. There is no reason to think that Texas makes life-or-death mistakes in capital cases less frequently than other states, and good reason to think the risk is higher there. </p>
<p>Whether this risk is acceptable is a separate question from whether one supports the death penalty.  As Governor Ryan recognized, it is a question of fundamental fair.</p>
<p>The president of the United States has no greater responsibility
than to protect the fairness and integrity of our justice
system. Governor Bush, who has expressed his approval of the process
in Texas and refused to intervene or support reform, has failed to
provide leadership in this critical area, raising troubling doubts
about his ability to carry out that responsibility.</p>
	    </div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.nytstaff002" n="Harris County, Texas:
Leading the Way to the Executioner's Table" type="Article">
               <head>Harris County, Texas:
Leading the Way to the Executioner's Table</head>
               <docAuthor>New York Times staff</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>
<argument><p>This article previously ran in the New York Times, on February 7, 2000. </p></argument>
<p>Texas leads the way among the states--to the executioner's table. With 231 people executed since 1982-146 (63 percent) of those under the five years that Governor George W. Bush has been in office--Texas far and away leads the way. The annual number of executions continues to increase with thirty-two people executed to date this year (as of August 31, 2000). Virginia is a distant second, having executed seventy-six people since the reinstatement of the death penalty in 1976.</p>
<p>With Gov. George Bush's presidential campaign well underway, Texas and its penchant for the death penalty have received much press. Little notice, however, has been given to the Texas county that has been so significant in helping Texas earn its dubious reputation.</p>
<p>Harris County, which includes Houston, has prosecuted 143 (31 percent) of the 460 inmates currently on death row.  Dallas County comes in a distant second, having prosecuted forty-two (9.1 percent) of Texas' death row inmates. During twenty-one years of the "leadership" of District Attorney John "Johnny" B. Holmes, Jr., Harris County has executed more people than any other state (sixty-three), excluding Texas and Virginia. In celebration of that "accomplishment," Holmes hangs a sign in his office's death penalty unit that reads, "The Silver Needle Society" and includes a list of all people killed by lethal injection in the county.</p>
<p>A close inspection of the death row inmates from Harris County reveals the racial and economic disparities in the county's capitol punishment system. In a county where African Americans make up 20 percent of the population, seventy-nine of the 146 (54 percent) death row inmates from Harris County are African American. An additional twenty-six inmates (17.8 percent) are Hispanic. More than one-half (seventy-four) did not complete high school or its equivalency. Only four of the 146 were employed in which collar jobs at the time of their arrest. Sixty of the 146 listed "laborer" as their occupation prior to arrest.</p>
<p>There is a possibility for change in Harris County this fall;
District Attorney Holmes will be retiring to be replaced by either
Democrat Jim Dougherty or Republican Chuck Rosenthal. Both support the
death penalty, but Dougherty, a Houston defense lawyer, supports
changing state law to allow life without parole as an alternative and
to prohibit the execution of the mentally ill or disabled. Rosenthal,
a career prosecutor, is a staunch defender of the current system and
has sent fourteen people to death row. Rice University political
scientist and pollster Bob Stein, quoted in the Houston Chronicle,
does not see the death penalty as being a significant factor in the
race though. "This is a Republican county in a death penalty state, "
he said.</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.aclu.003" n="Virginia Death Penalty Statistics" type="Article">
               <head>Virginia Death Penalty Statistics</head>
               <docAuthor>ACLU staff</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>
<argument><p>From "Unequal, Unfair and Irreversible: The Death Penalty in Virginia
Published by the ACLU of Virginia, April 2000 </p></argument>
<p>Virginia is second only to Texas in the number of persons executed since the reinstatement of the death penalty in 1977. In fact, Virginia's execution rate, expressed as a proportion of the state's population, exceeds that of Texas. Disturbed by those stark statistics, the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) of Virginia conducted an indepth study of the circumstances of Virginia's startling death penalty record. The study examined four key aspects of the administration of capital punishment in Virginia--prosecutorial discretion in the charging of capital crimes, quality of legal representation for the accused at trial, appellate review of trials resulting in the death penalty, and race. Some of the startling facts they uncovered are listed below. </p>
<p>Columbia University Law School Professor James Liebman, who conducted an earlier study of post-sentencing judicial outcomes nationwide between 1973 and 1995, summed up Virginia's death penalty record saying, "It's a combination of things. Virginia, in my view, has the broadest death penalty statute in the country. It has a court system in which representation is poorly funded and post-trial review is very limited. It's got a conservative bench, both at the trial level and at Supreme Court level. And then it has the Fourth Circuit. When it comes to getting and keeping death sentences, the planets are just really aligned over Virginia."   </p>
<p> &#x2022;Ninety-seven percent of those sentenced to death in Virginia have been too poor to afford their own lawyers and have been represented by court-appointed lawyers.</p>
<p> &#x2022;The Virginia State Supreme Court has reversed fewer death sentences than any other state supreme court in the country and has never granted an evidentiary hearing or appointed an expert or an investigator to a death penalty case. Between 1973 and1995, Virginia's supreme court found error in 8 percent of capital cases as compared to the national average of 40 percent. Texas, the only state with more executions than Virginia, reverses 28 percent of its cases. </p>
<p> &#x2022;The U.S. Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit, which serves Virginia, grants new hearings to death row inmates in 9 percent of cases in its jurisdiction and only 4 percent of cases in Virginia. This compares to a nationwide average of 39 percent among federal appeals courts.</p>
<p> &#x2022;Since 1978, Virginia has meted out 131 death sentences. Of those sentences, the Supreme Court has reversed exactly eleven, almost all on direct appeal.</p>
<p> &#x2022;In 1998 and 1999, Virginia executed eight prisoners within five years of their sentencing dates. This is the time that is used primarily by higher courts to review death sentences for fairness. The national average time between sentencing and execution in nine years.</p>
<p>&#x2022;Eight of Virginia's 134 jurisdictions have exacted the death penalty for more than 10 percent of total capital murders between 1978 and 1997. Three jurisdictions have exacted the death penalty for more than 30 percent of total capital murders committed in the jurisdiction. They are Prince William County (64 percent), the county that shut down its public schools for 6 years in the 1960s in order to avoid desegregation, Danville City (39 percent), the last capital of the Confederacy, and Bedford County (33 percent), in Southcentral Virginia. </p>
<p>&#x2022;Black offenders who rape and murder white victims in Virginia are more than four times more likely to be sentenced to death than those who rape and murder black victims--70 percent compared to 15 percent.</p>
<p>&#x2022;Trial lawyers who represented the men on Virginia's death row are six times more likely to be the subject of bar disciplinary proceedings than are other lawyers. In one of every ten trials resulting in a death sentence, the defendant was represented by a lawyer who would lose his license. </p>
<p>&#x2022;Virginia has no mechanism through which the state's courts can consider evidence of innocence that surfaces more than 21 days after a defendant's final sentencing in Circuit Court. In recent years, condemned prisoners have gone to their deaths despite inconsistent DNA evidence, witness recantations, and evidence that the crime for which they were condemned was committed by another person entirely.</p>
<p>&#x2022;The Virginia Supreme Court has never upheld an ineffective assistance claim--a claim that the defendant did not receive fair representation--in a death case. Only once has the Fourth Circuit Court upheld an ineffective assistance claim in a Virginia capital case.</p>
<p>&#x2022;Because of the Doctrine of Procedural Default, any violation or error a defendant's lawyer does not identify in the first step of the appeals process is barred from consideration by any court. This undermines the idea that post-conviction review ensured that death sentences are the result of fair trials of appropriate quality.</p>
<p>&#x2022;According to the FBI's Supplemental Homicide Reports,
between 1978 and 1997, 41 percent of victims of apparently capital
crimes were black. Yet of the 131 crimes for which a death sentence
was imposed during the same period, only 20 percent of the victims
were black.</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.torian.004" n="Women in Prison Article" type="Article">
               <head>Women in Prison Article</head>
               <docAuthor>Sarah Torian</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>

<p>In 1994, Kemba Smith became a symbol of a national trend in criminal justice. A twenty-three year old African-American woman from the suburbs of Richmond, Virginia, she was sentenced to 24 1/2 years in prison for her involvement in a four million-dollar crack and powder cocaine drug operation led by her physically and verbally abusive boyfriend and his brother. She had pleaded guilty to conspiracy to drug trafficking, money laundering, and making false statements to federal agents. She had never used nor sold any drugs and had no direct knowledge of any sales. Kemba Smith is representative of a significant part of a national trend, the escalating number of women who are finding themselves behind bars for low-level involvement in drugs and other crimes. </p>
<p>Between 1980 and 1997, the number of women in state and federal prisons increased by 573 percent. Much of this increase is a result of the "war on drugs" and the mandatory minimum sentencing guidelines now imposed for drug offenses. "The impact of sentencing guidelines on women is astronomical," reports Michelle Jacobs, professor at Howard University Law School which hosted a three-day conference sponsored by Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under the Law that examined the increase in the criminalization of women. "A woman may just be married to a man who deals drugs and the woman has only a very basic low-level involvement. She may answer the phone and take messages, receive packages at the door, and yet, with drug laws the way they are now, she gets charged with conspiracy for the total amount of the drugs. Before, judges could take into account prior convictions, families, the potential to rehabilitate. Now they can't." Drug offenses make up one-third of women's convictions, a greater proportion than for men. Between 1990 and 1996, drug felony convictions among women in state courts witnessed a 37 percent increase to 59,027.</p>
<p>Drugs are not the only reason that women now comprise 16 percent of the nation's correction population. According to a Bureau of Justice Statistics special report released in December of 1999, felony convictions of women in state courts increased by more than 20 percent for seven out of nine major crimes. (Only murder and robbery witnessed a drop in convictions.) Fraud was the crime which received the most convictions (33,902) in 1996, an increase of 55 percent from 1990. Larceny, the offense category with the most arrests, saw an increase in convictions of 39 percent, reaching a total of 28,786 in 1996. </p>
<p>Although female juvenile arrest rates have declined each year since 1995, the proportionate number of juvenile arrests is almost double that of adult women (age eighteen or older). In 1998, the number of female juvenile (age ten to seventeen) arrests represented one for every twenty-two female juveniles, compared to one arrest for every forty-two adult women. An estimated 28 percent of violent female offenders are juveniles, but juvenile women are most often arrested for larceny, which includes shoplifting. Larceny arrests, according to the Bureau of Justice Statistics, equaled about one arrest for every 105 minor girls and one arrest for every 337 adult women. </p>
<p>The South leads the nation in the imprisonment of women. In 1998, of state prisoners 44 percent were held by states in the South where the incarceration rate is the highest of any region. There are sixty-five female prisoners per 100,000 residents in the South. Of the southern states, Texas leads the way in locking up women with 10,343 female prisoners and a rate of 102 per 100,000 residents.</p>
<p>One of the most disturbing statistics revealed by the BJS report was the racial breakdowns of female prisoners. White women make up a great majority of the women on probation (62 percent) where African-American women represent 27 percent and Hispanic women 10 percent. Looking at women in jails and prisons, however, the numbers change drastically. White women make up only 36 percent of women in local jails, 33 percent of women in state prisons, and 29 percent of women in federal prisons. African-American women make up 44 percent of women in local jails, 48 percent in state prisons, and 35 percent in federal prisons. Hispanic women represent 15 percent of women in local jails, 15 percent in state prisons, and leap to 32 percent of women in federal prisons. Tracy Snell, who co-wrote the BJS special report on women offenders could not definitively explain these differences. "This is reflective of a number of things," she explained. "It depends on the types of offenses, the criminal history, if the offender was on probation or parole at the time or the offense and so forth. But we did not collect that kind of data for this study, so it is really tough to explain."</p>
<p>The exponential increase in female imprisonment has a broad and devastating impact on the communities that the women leave. More than 233,600 minor children have mothers who are in jails or prisons and 1.3 million minor children have mothers under supervision by the justice system, including parole and probation. These children lose their mothers. "The impact on the community [of the imprisonment of women] is multi-layered," argues Michelle Jacobs. "If a man is arrested, the woman usually continues to care for the family. If the woman is arrested, there is rarely reciprocity. The children are usually shuttled off to foster homes or left with grandmothers who don't have the support they need."</p>
<p>There are a few organizations that provide support to these children, their imprisoned mothers, and their caregivers, but it is not enough. The Center for Children of Incarcerated Mothers reports that children whose mothers are imprisoned are five times more likely to go to prisons themselves. Grassroots organizations like Aid to Children of Imprisoned Mothers, Inc. (AIM) are working to support all three generations impacted by the imprisonment of mothers to turn this trend around. AIM in Atlanta is a member of this national network of community-based organizations that offers support to children, including an after-school program and transportation to visit mothers in nearby prisons; to mothers, including parenting skills and job readiness training; and to grandmothers and caregivers, including support and fellowship groups. "Our focus is intergenerational--across three generations," says Sandra Barnhill, executive director of AIM in Atlanta. "AIM works intensively over a long period with all family members involved to allow for a complete investment in the entire family to begin to turn these trends around."</p>
<p>But the imprisonment of women is indicative of a larger economic injustice.  The women who are being incarcerated are in much more dire financial straits than their male counterparts. Nearly 30 percent of women in state prisons, where African-American and Hispanic women make up 63 percent of the population, reported receiving welfare assistance prior to their arrest, compared to 8 percent of men in state prisons. Thirty-seven percent of women in state prisons had incomes of less than six hundred dollars prior to their arrest, compared to 27 percent of men. "With so much emphasis on men we haven't really been thinking about women and criminal justice," explains Jacobs. "We don't know the conditions of poverty and domestic violence that lead her to an economic crime."</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.mcdevitt.005" n="Juvenile Justice Hurts" type="Article">
               <head>Juvenile Justice "Hurts"</head>
               <docAuthor>By Rick McDevitt</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>
<argument><p>Rick McDevitt is president of the Georgia Alliance for Children.)</p></argument>
<p>In response to [rising rates of?] [what are the rates? Have they risen?] juvenile crime, there has been a lot of discussion about the need to expand the construction of juvenile prisons.  Expansion is not the answer.  In fact, the current system is not reforming children, it is actually hurting them.</p>
<p>Last year in the Georgia Department of Juvenile Justice, there were 4,600 inmate-on-inmate beatings and almost six-hundred staff-on-inmate beatings. [need to expand on this and discuss what kind of assaults, how the information is obtained]  Less than 10 percent of all juvenile crime is violent, yet large numbers [how large?] of nonviolent offenders are in cells with murderers and rapists [need some statistics to support this].  [what is the age range for juveniles?]</p>
<p>According to Georgia crime statistics, white children are arrested twice as often as African Americans, yet almost 70 percent of kids in detention are black.  Crimes committed by African American youth are not more serious; in fact, 750 of the children in the Georgia juvenile justice system are there for nonviolent offenses[ such as?].</p>
<p>Meanwhile the state is building more prisons to provide jobs for local residents, not rehabilitation for youth.  Jailed youth are not being rehabilitated, they are being raped and abused, they are attempting suicide [any examples here? Or sources?], receiving little or no medical attention, suffering mentally [explain], receiving inadequate education [explain] and insufficient rehabilitative services.  It costs approximately $40,000 a year to lock up one child in jail. [source]</p>
<p>In 1997, a U. S. Department of Justice investigation found that the state juvenile justice facilities were "grossly substandard," "egregious," and "unconstitutional."  According to the report, Georgia's juvenile facilities lack enough space to separate younger, more vulnerable youths from older, potentially more predatory youth.  In one incident, a child held for violation of probation was housed with three youths accused of armed robbery and aggravated assault and was beaten and sexually assaulted without intervention from the staff.  [more on this and other incidents, why didn't the staff intervene?]</p>
<p>As a result of low staffing levels, a male staff member was able to sexually assault a fourteen-year old female resident after persuading the only other staff member on the shift to take nap. [how was this discovered?  What happened to the staff member?  The resident?]</p>
<p>Sooner or later, incarcerated juveniles return to their communities much worse for their experience. Almost nothing is spent on community-based programs [what would these be like? Any examples?], the smart alternative to the current juvenile justice system-programs which would get to children's lives sooner, rather than later.  We know that in the medical profession, prevention and early intervention are less expensive and more effective than catastrophic care.  The same reasoning should be applied to juveniles who commit petty property crimes and other less serious offenses.  </p>
<p>Resources must be provided for after-school programs, intensive supervision and mentoring, drug prevention and treatment and mental health counseling for confused or troubled youth.  And parents must be given the tools they need [not clear what this means] to regain control over their confused adolescents.</p>
<p>In June 2000 the Georgia Alliance for Children, backed by
forty organizations [not clear] kicked off a campaign to educate
citizens on the atrocities [word choice?] that are occurring in the
system [the system is the atrocity].  The grassroots movement is
demanding that Governor Roy Barnes and the Georgia State Legislature
redirect money used to operate youth "dungeons"[what does this mean?]
and invest it in community-based intervention, prevention and
aftercare programs that help solve problems before they become
serious.  Every politician should have a position [vague] for
correcting the cruel system we are imposing on our children.  [ending
kind of peters out]</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.torian.006" n="Women in Prison Article" type="Article">
               <head>Women in Prison Article</head>
               <docAuthor>Sarah Torian</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>

<p>	In 1994, Kemba Smith became a symbol of a national trend in criminal justice. A twenty-three year old African-American woman from the suburbs of Richmond, Virginia, she was sentenced to 24 1/2 years in prison for her involvement in a four million-dollar crack and powder cocaine drug operation led by her physically and verbally abusive boyfriend and his brother. She had pleaded guilty to conspiracy to drug trafficking, money laundering, and making false statements to federal agents. She had never used nor sold any drugs and had no direct knowledge of any sales. Kemba Smith is representative of a significant part of a national trend, the escalating number of women who are finding themselves behind bars for low-level involvement in drugs and other crimes. </p>
<p>Between 1980 and 1997, the number of women in state and federal prisons increased by 573 percent. Much of this increase is a result of the "war on drugs" and the mandatory minimum sentencing guidelines now imposed for drug offenses. "The impact of sentencing guidelines on women is astronomical," reports Michelle Jacobs, professor at Howard University Law School which hosted a three-day conference sponsored by Lawyers' Committee for Civil Rights Under the Law that examined the increase in the criminalization of women. "A woman may just be married to a man who deals drugs and the woman has only a very basic low-level involvement. She may answer the phone and take messages, receive packages at the door, and yet, with drug laws the way they are now, she gets charged with conspiracy for the total amount of the drugs. Before, judges could take into account prior convictions, families, the potential to rehabilitate. Now they can't." Drug offenses make up one-third of women's convictions, a greater proportion than for men. Between 1990 and 1996, drug felony convictions among women in state courts witnessed a 37 percent increase to 59,027.</p>
<p>Drugs are not the only reason that women now comprise 16 percent of the nation's correction population. According to a Bureau of Justice Statistics special report released in December of 1999, felony convictions of women in state courts increased by more than 20 percent for seven out of nine major crimes. (Only murder and robbery witnessed a drop in convictions.) Fraud was the crime which received the most convictions (33,902) in 1996, an increase of 55 percent from 1990. Larceny, the offense category with the most arrests, saw an increase in convictions of 39 percent, reaching a total of 28,786 in 1996. </p>
<p>Although female juvenile arrest rates have declined each year since 1995, the proportionate number of juvenile arrests is almost double that of adult women (age eighteen or older). In 1998, the number of female juvenile (age ten to seventeen) arrests represented one for every twenty-two female juveniles, compared to one arrest for every forty-two adult women. An estimated 28 percent of violent female offenders are juveniles, but juvenile women are most often arrested for larceny, which includes shoplifting. Larceny arrests, according to the Bureau of Justice Statistics, equaled about one arrest for every 105 minor girls and one arrest for every 337 adult women. </p>
<p>The South leads the nation in the imprisonment of women. In 1998, of state prisoners 44 percent were held by states in the South where the incarceration rate is the highest of any region. There are sixty-five female prisoners per 100,000 residents in the South. Of the southern states, Texas leads the way in locking up women with 10,343 female prisoners and a rate of 102 per 100,000 residents.</p>
<p> One of the most disturbing statistics revealed by the BJS report was the racial breakdowns of female prisoners. White women make up a great majority of the women on probation (62 percent) where African-American women represent 27 percent and Hispanic women 10 percent. Looking at women in jails and prisons, however, the numbers change drastically. White women make up only 36 percent of women in local jails, 33 percent of women in state prisons, and 29 percent of women in federal prisons. African-American women make up 44 percent of women in local jails, 48 percent in state prisons, and 35 percent in federal prisons. Hispanic women represent 15 percent of women in local jails, 15 percent in state prisons, and leap to 32 percent of women in federal prisons. Tracy Snell, who co-wrote the BJS special report on women offenders could not definitively explain these differences. "This is reflective of a number of things," she explained. "It depends on the types of offenses, the criminal history, if the offender was on probation or parole at the time or the offense and so forth. But we did not collect that kind of data for this study, so it is really tough to explain."</p>
<p>The exponential increase in female imprisonment has a broad and devastating impact on the communities that the women leave. More than 233,600 minor children have mothers who are in jails or prisons and 1.3 million minor children have mothers under supervision by the justice system, including parole and probation. These children lose their mothers. "The impact on the community [of the imprisonment of women] is multi-layered," argues Michelle Jacobs. "If a man is arrested, the woman usually continues to care for the family. If the woman is arrested, there is rarely reciprocity. The children are usually shuttled off to foster homes or left with grandmothers who don't have the support they need."</p>
<p>There are a few organizations that provide support to these children, their imprisoned mothers, and their caregivers, but it is not enough. The Center for Children of Incarcerated Mothers reports that children whose mothers are imprisoned are five times more likely to go to prisons themselves. Grassroots organizations like Aid to Children of Imprisoned Mothers, Inc. (AIM) are working to support all three generations impacted by the imprisonment of mothers to turn this trend around. AIM in Atlanta is a member of this national network of community-based organizations that offers support to children, including an after-school program and transportation to visit mothers in nearby prisons; to mothers, including parenting skills and job readiness training; and to grandmothers and caregivers, including support and fellowship groups. "Our focus is intergenerational - across three generations," says Sandra Barnhill, executive director of AIM in Atlanta. "AIM works intensively over a long period with all family members involved to allow for a complete investment in the entire family to begin to turn these trends around."</p>
<p>But the imprisonment of women is indicative of a larger economic
injustice.  The women who are being incarcerated are in much more dire
financial straits than their male counterparts. Nearly 30 percent of
women in state prisons, where African-American and Hispanic women make
up 63 percent of the population, reported receiving welfare assistance
prior to their arrest, compared to 8 percent of men in state
prisons. Thirty-seven percent of women in state prisons had incomes of
less than six hundred dollars prior to their arrest, compared to 27
percent of men. "With so much emphasis on men we haven't really been
thinking about women and criminal justice," explains Jacobs. "We don't
know the conditions of poverty and domestic violence that lead her to
an economic crime."</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.007" n="DEMOCRACY AND INCARCERATION" type="Article">
               <head>DEMOCRACY AND INCARCERATION</head>
               <docAuthor>by  Si Kahn, Executive Director</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>
<argument><p>Grassroots Leadership
Charlotte, North Carolina
2059 words</p></argument>
<p>Begin your journey through time in Durham, North Carolina, driving north on Interstate 85 towards Richmond, one-time capital of the Confederacy. Just before the Virginia border, turn east onto U.S. 158. Travel through Littleton, where members of the Lumbee-Tuscarora tribe routed the Ku Klux Klan in the 1950s. Pass through Roanoke Rapids, where in 1974 workers at the town's seven J.P. Stevens cotton mills voted to join the Textile Workers Union of America and started a historic six-year national campaign for a contract.  Keep traveling through history until you cross into Hertford County and there, not far from where the Meherrin River flows into the Chowan, you'll come to the old Vann plantation.</p>
<p>These days, it doesn't look like much, just some cotton fields backed by scrub forest. But in 1850, it was a major plantation with more than fifty slaves. In 1860, only 611 plantations in the entire state owned more than fifty slaves, making the Vanns one of the larger slaveholding families in North Carolina.</p>
<p>But, if Corporate America has its way, the old Vann place will soon be back in business with a vengeance. Wackenhut Corrections, a multi-national corporation that builds and runs private prisons for profit, is planning to build a 1,320-bed prison here. They will operate it under a contract from the Federal Bureau of Prisons, which plans to ship the prison 1,200 inmates from the District of Columbia, almost all of them African Americans. So Wackenhut will be importing well over one thousand Black men from the District of Columbia and imprisoning them on the same plantation where African Americans, possibly including some of their own ancestors, were held as slaves 150 years ago. </p>
<p>This is just one example of the ways in which the for-profit prison industry is changing the nature of criminal justice in the United States. The rise of for-profit private prisons raises critical issues for democracy, as well as for the balance of public and private power in an open society.</p>
<p>For-profit private prisons are a relatively recent development. The current wave of privatization generally in the U.S. is less than twenty years old and is still heavily contested. It's paralleled by the recent unprecedented rise in the prison population and in new prison construction. And, of course, for-profit prison privatization is emerging as a major factor in this dynamic, as well as a major growth industry and social phenomenon.  Between 1990 and 1999, the number of prisoners in for-profit private prisons increased over 1,500 percent, from less than 8,000 to over 123,000.</p>
<p>This is partly a response to recent economic and political conditions. States, counties and cities are hard pressed financially and politically by the "need" for increased prison "beds" and have turned to for-profit private corporations to provide them. By contracting with for-profit private prison corporations, elected officials avoid the need to go to the voters with politically risky bond issues for new prison construction. They can also report the costs of these contracts under operating expenses, thus appearing to cut costs and "government jobs."  </p>
<p>To for-profit private prison corporations, the issue is simple: the more prisoners, the more profit.  This partly accounts for their aggressiveness in trying to privatize as much as possible as quickly as they can. In addition, they're obviously trying to grab as much territory as they can before resistance to for-profit private prisons hardens.</p>
<p>But the private prison corporations have another strategic reason for speed. If the present trend towards prison privatization continues, it will quickly reach a "tipping point" where private rather than public prisons are the norm. At this point, any possibility of restoring prisons to public control will be gone. Any idea of restorative justice will have even less hope than it does today. As difficult as it is for inmates and their supporters, including progressive corrections officers, to change conditions when prisons are publicly held and operated, imagine how much harder that will be if the majority of prisons and detention facilities are in private corporate hands. If all prisons turn private, their parent corporations will have no more interest in reducing the shameful number of inmates in this country than Marriott does in holding down its number of hotel guests. Through campaign contributions made possible by increased profits, they'll become an even more significant pressure than they are now towards imprisoning the maximum number of people for as long as possible. Profit rather than the public good becomes the measure of all things.</p>
<p>The development and growth of for-profit private prisons has many negative consequences, including the current interstate commerce in prisoners by for-profit private prison corporations. This is one of the tragedies of prison privatization. Prisoners are incarcerated at great distances from their families, homes and communities, basically to suit the convenience of corporations. Many studies have shown that prisoners in these circumstances are significantly less likely to reintegrate themselves successfully on release and, of course, are therefore far more likely to be returned to prison.     </p>
<p>This "export-import" business has a particular impact on the South. The "exporting" states tend to be those with higher costs per day for prisoners. Exporting prisoners is not just about solving prison over-crowding but about saving money, including the capital costs of building new prisons. The "importing" states tend to be those with lower costs per prisoner per day, often a reflection of their significantly lower labor costs as a result of lack of unionization among corrections officers and other prison employees. Not surprisingly, the importing states tend to be in the South, with its historic low labor costs and lack of unionization.  </p>
<p>It's possible to foresee a scenario where the South, already the site for so many of its own prisoners, becomes the holding area for many of the prisoners from the rest of the nation, the vast majority of whom will be African Americans and other people of color. The South already has a long and shameful history of incarceration and the racialized use of imprisonment as a tool of social control, including chain gangs and convict labor, which tend to make prison privatization more acceptable. According to recent, statistics, almost 70 percent of all prisoners in private facilities are in the eleven states of the old Confederacy and over 95 percent of all private prison facilities and detention centers in the U.S. are owned or operated by Southern prison corporations.</p>
<p>Another negative consequence is the growth of "speculation" or "spec" prisons. The for-profit private prison corporations are using speculation prisons as a way of side-stepping current state legislative restrictions on the construction of private prisons for designated state use. Speculation prisons are particularly insidious, not just because they sidestep the intention of responsible state legislators to restrict and control prison privatization, but because they create pressure for more prisoners. From a management point of view, a prison is like a hotel or motel: you want to fill every bed, every night. If you don't have enough guests, you do whatever you can to get them - including supporting campaigns for mandatory and longer sentences.      </p>
<p>For-profit private prisons have experienced numerous incidents involving deaths, disturbances, physical and sexual abuse of prisoners, to an extent much higher than that in public prisons. To a large extent, such incidents are inherent to the operation of for-profit private prisons, due to their high employee turnover rates and consequent lack of experience among prison personnel. Experience at many prisons which have been established by private corporations in rural areas has shown a turnover rate considerably in excess of that found in public facilities. It is not uncommon for the local workforce to become depleted, with the consequent need to recruit prison personnel from farther and farther away.  The long distances such personnel need to drive to work further increases the likelihood of high turnover rates.</p>
<p>Prison privatization also privatizes decision-making and access. For example, for-profit private prisons can refuse to supply the basic information about their operations that public prisons are required to provide.  Within the prison industry, such conditions ranging from privacy to secrecy are obvious incentives to corruption. It's difficult enough to control corruption in prisons under any circumstances. When you also impose the veil of secrecy and legal protection which is standard operating procedure in most major corporations, you are not only inviting additional corruption, you are also making sure it will be more difficult to root out. </p>
<p>For-profit private prisons are also one of the forces driving the increased incarceration of young people of color. Whole inner-city communities are being robbed of their economic and social potential as young African-American and Latino men and, increasingly, women are arrested and incarcerated, a pattern which is also repeated in other communities of color. The statistics related to the African-American community are both well-known and discouraging.  </p>
<p>&#x2022;Of African-American men between age 20 and twenty-nine, one out of three is either in prison, on probation or on parole.</p>
<p>&#x2022;There are more African-American men in prison than in college.</p>
<p>It is common knowledge how devastating this development has been to communities of color. Prison not only robs young people of their youth, it too often bars them from future employment. Should we then be surprised when communities of color are left behind economically and politically? Or when young people of color say that things today are worse than forty years ago, that the Civil Rights Movement accomplished nothing? </p>
<p>One of the ironies of the growth in incarceration, however, is that it's created economic opportunity for some people of color. Increasing numbers of correctional officers are themselves people of color.  Because public prisons tend to be organized, these employees enjoy reasonable wages and benefits, along with considerable job security. </p>
<p>But all this changes when prisons are privatized. Some for-profit private prisons pay wages that are barely above the minimum wage, with few or no benefits other than those required by law. Turnover for employees in private prisons is astounding, ranging up to 100 percent a year. Working conditions are both difficult and dangerous.  </p>
<p>It is unfortunate that that one of the few economic opportunities open to people of color in so many poor and rural communities is guarding other people of color. But as long as these are the few jobs that are available to them, they need to be good jobs, with decent salaries, good fringe benefits, job security, adequate training and protection.  </p>
<p>To summarize the political situation and to conclude, three parallel developments have been taking place over the past ten years:</p>
<p>&#x2022;Demands by political leaders and, to some extent, by the public, for more prisons, a product of our seeing incarceration as an easy answer to all social problems.</p>
<p>&#x2022;Resistance by voters to increased taxes and/or new bond issues.</p>
<p>&#x2022;The development and growth of the for-profit private prison industry.</p>
<p>These three developments are much more related than any of us have realized. To put it simply:  Politicians are building careers on being "tough on crime" (which translates to many white voters as "tough on people of color"). So they promise to build more and more prisons. But they also can't go to these same voters to approve prison construction bonds, which would involve higher taxes: these days, almost any politician who goes to the voters with a major bond issue is putting her/his career on the line. So they're between a rock and a hard place. They want to build prisons so they can build their careers, but they lack and can't get the capital to do so.</p>
<p>Enter the for-profit private prison corporations, with their ability to capitalize prison construction themselves. No bonds, no referendums, no tax increases, no political risks. No wonder so many elected officials are willing to cut these deals.</p>
<p>But if for-profit private prisons become publicly unacceptable, politically risky, economically unfeasible or even illegal, it will also create a different dynamic for elected officials. Without an easy way to build new prisons, to promote incarceration as the politically acceptable be-all and end-all for social problems, they may need to come to grips with the limits of the current criminal justice system.  In such a situation, rights, reform, rehabilitation, and restorative justice again become imaginable -  but only in a public and publicly accountable system of justice, as is not only appropriate but critical to a democratic society.</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.008" n="Prison Labor - Needs New Title" type="Article">
               <head>Prison Labor - Needs New Title</head>
               <docAuthor>By Murphy Davis</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>
<argument><p></p></argument>
<p>Our friend Thony is locked up for a sentence of 481 years in an infamous Southern plantation-style prison. He spends his days with a swing blade cutting grass on the edge of ditches over the 20,000-acre prison. For his labor he is paid two cents per hour. One penny per hour is banked until his parole consideration (2070); the other penny per hour is his to spend at the prison store.</p>
<p>Mary Louise sews blue stripes down the pants legs of prison uniforms at the garment factory near the women's prison. For her eight hours a day she is paid nothing.  She begs stamps from friends to write to her children.</p>
<p>Charles stands day after day in front of a machine, watching it stamp out license plates. The work is monotonous, and he is paid nothing for it. The prison tells him he is building "work skills." But since license plates are only made in prison industries, he is not being prepared for any work on the outside market.</p>
<p>Frank sits on death row. Day in, day out, he is, for all practical purposes, idle.  Television, exercise, writing letters, and playing checkers pass the time. Frank, though young, strong, and energetic, is not allowed to work. He has spent the past 10 years of his life unable to do anything of use to anyone.</p>
<p>Thony, Mary Louise, Charles, and Frank, like more than two million men, women and children in the United States, cannot control their own labor. They are slaves.</p>
<p>Slavery is, of course, not a fashionable word in the early days of the
twenty-first century. We assume ourselves to be rid of it. But an
often-overlooked fact of U.S. political life and history is that the
Thirteenth Amendment to the Constitution did not abolish slavery in
this country. It simply narrowed the practice. The amendment reads:
"Neither slavery nor involuntary servitude <hi rend="bold">EXCEPT AS A PUNISHMENT FOR CRIME</hi> whereof the party shall have been duly convicted, shall exist within the United States, or any place subject to their jurisdiction (emphasis mine)."</p>
<p>Prisoners are, by mandate of the United States Constitution, slaves. In the 1970's, the terminology of the prison system started to change. We began to have "Correctional Institutions," "Diagnostic and Classification Centers," "Youth Development Centers," etc. Wardens became "Superintendents;" guards became "Correctional Officers;" prisoners became "inmates." Solitary confinement, or the "hole," became the "Adjustment Center." The language of scientific penology attempts to mask harsh reality. </p>
<p>Some of the tough talk of recent years has abandoned the "new" penology and reverted to the chain gang approach.  But whatever words we use for the system or its captives, prisoners are people from whom most rights of citizenship have been taken. They have no right to control where they are, with whom, or how they spend their time - in forced labor or forced idleness.  Whether we say they are given over to the prison system to be "corrected," "rehabilitated," or "incapacitated," the fact remains that they are in the system to accomplish one goal: punishment.</p>
<p>Why? And for whom? Qui bono? Can we be satisfied to live with the commonly held assumption that people are in prison solely because they have done bad things?  If this assumption were true then why would there be such wide variation in incarceration rates around the world and even within the United States? The United States goes back and forth with Russia for the distinction of being the world's #1 jailer. That is to say that the U.S. depends - more than any other government in the world - on caging people as a response to our problems. In recent decades, we have closed mental hospitals, addiction services, and community programs for the retarded and the disabled, not to mention support services for families, children and the elderly. Prisons and jails have become the one-stop solution for all our problems. There are, in many states, more mentally ill people in county jails and state prisons than in hospitals. Most expressions of "deviance" have been criminalized and the criminal control system is supposed to take care of it all, but prisons have not always been such major institutions in the United States.</p>
<p>Georgia's penal history is representative of most Southern states: The first state prison was opened in Milledgeville (then the state capital) in 1817. The prison was based on the "Auburn plan" which assumed that hard work would simultaneously punish and reform. The average number of prisoners remained around 200 - all white. Black people, of course, were slaves and were dealt with inside the system of private ownership. </p>
<p>This development in Georgia roughly coincided with the opening of state prisons in other states. Thomas Jefferson took from Italian philosopher Cesare Beccaria the notion of confined convict slavery and designed a prison for Virginia that opened to receive prisoners in 1800. Centuries earlier governments had learned that the punishment of slavery could be used to the benefit of the state. Galley slavery of ancient Greece and Rome was used again in France and Spain during the 14th and 15th centuries. </p>
<p>In the 19th century, slavery as punishment was tailored to the needs of the American system. The benefits of this form of punishment to general social control were frankly admitted. A prison report in 1820 stressed that convict submission was "demanded not so much for the smooth functioning of the prison but for the sake of the convict himself, who shall learn to submit willingly to the fate of the lower classes."</p>
<p>As the system of American prison slavery was honed, the controversy raged over the practice of chattel slavery.  At the close of the Civil War, the controversy focused on the wording of the Constitutional Amendment to legally abolish slavery. Led by Massachusetts Senator Charles Sumner, those who argued for the complete abolition of slavery in the United States lost their struggle. The 13th Amendment as it was passed, and as it stands, forbids slavery "except as a punishment for crime..." This was a major victory for the Senators of the old Confederacy and their white constituents, bitter over the loss of their captive labor force. Rather than legally abolishing slavery, the amendment changed the system to permit the state, not private citizens, to be slave owners.</p>
<p>After the Civil War, Southern planters thought themselves lost without their slaves. The one legal form of slavery still available to them was imprisonment. Some states passed "Black Codes." Georgia and other states passed vagrancy laws, and similar statutes and ordinances as a way to lock up black people who were seen not to be in their "proper" place. </p>
<p>In 1868 Georgia established by law the convict lease system modeled after the Massachusetts system begun in 1798.Convicts could be leased to counties or county contractors for use on public works. In 1874 the Georgia law was altered to permit leasing convicts to private individuals and companies. By 1877,Georgia had 1,100 prisoners.  994 (90 percent) of them were black.</p>
<p>In 1878, former Confederate Colonel Robert Alston, serving as state representative from DeKalb County, visited convict work camps all over the state. As head of the Committee on the Penitentiary he wrote a scathing report: "The lease system at best is a bad one, and seems to have been forced upon the State by an inability to provide for the great increase in the number of criminals growing out of the changed relations of labor...To turn the prisoners over to private parties, who have no interest in them except that which is prompted by avarice, is to subject them to treatment which is as various as the characters of those in charge and in many cases amounts to nothing less than capital punishment with slow torture added." Alston encouraged leading citizens to withdraw from the companies leasing convicts.  Before long, a man who leased convicts murdered Colonel Alston. </p>
<p>As difficult as it must have been in the harsh days of the post-Reconstruction era, the black community found various ways to protest the lease system. One of their methods was an annual memorial service and "decoration of the grave" for Alston as the first white person to "condemn and denounce the workings of the abominable, blasphemous and vile penitentiary lease system, under which so many of our race are doomed to horror, agony and pollution."</p>
<p>In 1908 the Georgia Prison Commission reported that, in the penitentiary and chain gangs combined, there were 4,290 Negro males, 209 Negro women, 461 white males, and six white women. In that same year a committee report to the legislature on corruption and cruelty in the lease system led the legislature to abolish the lease. From then on, chain gangs worked on public works rather than for private individuals and companies. But abuses and cruelty continued. One infamous warden used to send black trustees out with a pitchfork to make the hogs squeal so that the townsfolk would not hear the human screams as the warden beat a prisoner with hosepipe.  Submission to the "fate of the lower classes" seems to have continued as an agenda in the prison system.</p>
<p>In 1957, forty-one prisoners at the Buford Rock Quarry broke their own legs with their sledgehammers to protest harsh working and living conditions. When the investigations promised by prison officials never took place, a second and then a third group of prisoners broke their own legs. As recently as 1979, a number of prisoners at the Wayne County "Correctional Institution" cut their own Achilles tendons in protest of harsh and demeaning working conditions.</p>
<p>I will never forget my first visit to the Georgia State Prison at Reidsville in the spring of 1978.  We drove onto the prison "reservation" and there, as far as I could see, were groups of men (mostly black) bent over working in the fields.  Over them sat a uniformed white man on horseback with a rifle across his lap.  I was utterly amazed; nothing in my formal education had prepared me to see this contemporary picture of slavery.  Perhaps, indeed, the privilege inherent in my formal education had contributed to my inability to see.</p>
<p>I did not realize then that slavery still existed as a legal institution in the United States.  Most American citizens probably do not.  But as the Committee to Abolish Prison Slavery has said: "In any form, slavery dehumanizes, cripples, and destroys anyone who willingly, or unwillingly, partakes in its practice." Prisons and prison slavery are crucial institutions in this country for controlling labor in the interest of the powerful few and to the benefit of all people of privilege. </p>
<p>It is beyond dispute that imprisonment rates have always gone straight up and down with rates of unemployment among the poor and especially people of color. But this has changed. Today, unemployment is at its lowest rate in recorded history, and crime rates have dropped dramatically, but still the imprisonment rate has continued to grow. What now drives the criminal control system is not crime and punishment but the drive to feed the vast Prison Industrial Complex which has been created to seek growing profits from prison labor. Within this monstrous system, creating even more political and social obfuscation, the phenomenon of privatization of prisons has now made marketable commodities of even prisoners themselves. To feed corporate profits, our legislative bodies have steadily passed harsher laws and longer mandatory sentences while the courts have dutifully imposed the draconian laws and turned a blind eye to selective enforcement and prosecution. And the portrayal of "crime" by the corporate media feeds the process. Because prisons on local, state and federal levels have become multi-million dollar industries, an increasing number of individuals and institutions are dependent on their continued existence.</p>
<p>Prison slavery infects all of us, whether we make ourselves aware of its use or not. Prisons are off the beaten path for most people. Middle and upper class people have very little reason to know anything of prisons or prisoners except when it becomes a local issue. Just a few years ago, communities could be quickly whipped into a frenzy to keep a new prison from being built "in our neighborhood." But with the frequently decimated economic base of small towns and rural areas and the increased "marketing" of prisons as an economic boon to small communities, many of these counties and municipalities now hire  professionals to lobby the legislature and Departments of Corrections, begging them to put the next new prison in their area.</p>
<p>This marriage made in hell of racial polarization and savage discrimination with corporate greed has formed the bottom line of the Prison Industrial Complex and its devastating consequences.</p>
<p>The damage done to the human family by this unchecked pattern is inestimable.</p>
<p> When a breadwinner is taken to prison her/his children often become wards of the state - by foster care or welfare.  More often than not, prisoners are assigned to prisons far from family and community ties, so that relationships are usually at least damaged and sometimes completely broken. Because prisoners earn nothing, or nearly nothing, for their labor, there is no possibility of helping to support their own families or making reparations where appropriate. Millions of men and women and children are being "disappeared" from their communities, losing their families, their access to education and decent employment, and even the right to vote when they are released. The situation becomes more complex by the day as we allow the prison industrial complex to be woven into our social, political and economic fabric.</p>
<p>Pretending to be untouched by systems of degradation and dehumanization can only be a self-defeating game. Perhaps we had to come to this point to begin to face the futility and self-destructiveness of our corporate behavior. Perhaps it took this level of abuse of the system to make us stop and see that our basic document - namely the 13th Amendment to the Constitution - is wrong as long as it allows penal slavery to replace chattel slavery. </p>
<p>It is time for a movement to take up the unfulfilled agenda of the 19th Century Abolitionists. The Southern planters and Senators who fought to maintain penal slavery in the Constitution understood that the criminal control system would be a lynchpin in the political economy of the post-Reconstruction South. It was later a basic underpinning of the Jim Crow system. In our day, the system of police, prisons, and courts are basic to any consideration of racial justice. We will not honestly confront race in our society until we take it on. Prison slavery must and will someday be abolished.  Until then we will not even begin to take an honest look at how we might move toward fair labor practices, a living wage for good work, and the ongoing task of dismantling the vicious racism that infects our common life. It is the least we can do to be about the task of seeking human dignity and liberation for all of God's children.</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.008" n="Prison Labor: Crime Still Doesn't Pay" type="Article">
               <head>Prison Labor: Crime Still Doesn't Pay</head>
               <docAuthor>By Brian Boldt</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>
<argument><p></p></argument>
<p>The phrase "prison labor" usually invokes images of chain gangs supervised by armed men on horseback or license plate factories. Yet few customers of Starbucks, Eddie Bauer, or Microsoft are likely to realize the products they purchase are supporting the participation of convict labor in private industry. With growing incarceration rates in this country, joint ventures between prisons and the private sector are becoming an increasingly common, though underreported, phenomenon. While inmate labor in private industry initially seems to offer benefits to both the general and prison population, close examination of these claims and of the context of prison growth reveal substantial weaknesses.</p>
<p>Although proponents of prison labor often tout the economic
benefits to the general public, that taxes paid from prisoner wages offset incarceration costs, these claims inevitably leave out substantial costs that are covered by the state. In many cases of prison labor, subsidies are provided to businesses entering into such ventures. In the Texas' Lockhart prison, the prison bore the cost of constructing a factory and charges Lockhart Technologies, Inc. (LTI) one dollar in annual rent. LTI also receives tax breaks from the city of Lockhart. A 56,000 square foot industrial building next to the Washington State Reformatory brings in more money - one dollar per month. The organizational structures of these ventures vary, but there are always administrative costs and these are carried by the prison. <hi rend="bold">[Need to address the constraints that private companies, working through the legislatures and courts historically, have exerted not to allow prisoners to engage in industries which might genuinely threaten very profitable and influential capitalist enterprises.  Thus the fallback on license plates and low-paying skills even when the chance of learning skills is offered.  Mention of this here will help set up the material in the paragraphs below</hi>.</p>
<p>Supporters of inmate labor for private industry claim that the work offers rehabilitative effects. A 1991 study by the U.S. Bureau of Prisons found that only 6.6 percent of federal inmates who had been employed in prison industries violated their parole or were re-arrested within a year of their release versus 20 percent for non-employed prisoners. Proponents frequently cite these figures as support for prison labor programs while others suggest that gainful employment be used as the benchmark for success rather than simply recidivism rates. </p>
<p>The "marketable skills" learned by inmates on the job are of
questionable value. Nearly all jobs in prison industries are labor
intensive, low skill work. Advice from garment manufacturer Third Generation highlights this: "Keep it simple, put the least complex sewing jobs you have inside the prison."<hi rend="bold">[give source for this quote]</hi> Escod Industries, which manufactures electronic cables inside South Carolina's Evans Correctional Facility, offers similar recommendations, "Now we concentrate in the prison our simpler, labor-intensive products." <hi rend="bold">[source?]</hi> </p>
<p>Other companies claim to bring jobs to the U.S. through prison
labor. In search of lower wages, Data Processing Accounting Services moved U.S. jobs to Mexico, but increased competition sent DPAS back to the U.S. in 1992 to San Quentin State Prison. "Some of the work went to China and some of the work we sent to San Quentin," DPAS owner Bob Tessler says. "Our objective is to find low-cost labor. We have a captive labor force, a group of men who are dedicated. And the whole thing is very profitable."<hi rend="bold">[cite source for quote]</hi> </p>
<p>Some opponents of prison labor are concerned that the prison industries' ability to undercut prevailing wages could be used as a union-busting tool and, in fact, Trans-Continental World Airlines has used inmate labor to break strikes. During a flight-attendant strike in 1986, TWA turned its reservation clerks into flight attendants and put inmates to work taking reservations. TWA still pays five dollars an hour to its inmate clerks at a juvenile facility in Ventura, California. That same work, when unionized, pays eighteen dollars an hour. </p>
<p>Despite language in federal regulations designed to mandate consultations with local unions on the possibility of prison labor, companies can exploit loopholes to keep their prison labor force a secret. The United Auto Workers union was surprised to find prisoners from Ohio prisons assembling Honda parts at Weastec Corporation, with prisoners being paid only $2.05 per hour (net wage is actually only 35 cents per hour). "No smaller employer could compete for that contract with Honda," says UAW director Warren Davis. </p>
<p> There is also a potential conflict of interest between employers
who want a steady workforce and fair prison policies. Escod Industries' efforts to address high prisoner turnover rates led them to negotiate for a second plant at a minimum-security facility. Correctional officials even placed some offices directly inside Escod's buildings, so that they may better "serve the needs of the company." <hi rend="bold">[source for quote.]</hi> This exemplifies a fundamental concern over prison labor - the diffusion of the "prison lobby" throughout the economy. As companies become dependent on prison labor pools, prison industries will have a vested interest in criminal legislation and could attempt to influence policy decisions. </p>
<p>The huge costs associated with Americans' choice to deal with
social problems by mass imprisonment are a fundamental part of the
drift toward privatization of prisons and prison industries. It seems
to matter less that prisons stop crime than that they give the
appearance of doing so - or of doing something. In this respect, the
growing popularity of prison labor is understandable. In a society
unable or unwilling to address the fundamental social and economic
causes of criminality, symbolic action substitutes for substantive
reform. </p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.009" n="THE  REEF " type="Article">
               <head>THE  REEF </head>
               <docAuthor></docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>
<argument><p>
     Ray's address:  Raymond Luc Levasseur, 10376/016, Atlanta, GA, 30315 

     A large collection of Rays essays and letters can be found at: 

     http://home.earthlink.net/~neoludd/</p></argument>
<p>(editors note: from 1989 to 1997, Ray's essays &#x0026; letters were a regular feature on WORT-FM Community Radio in Madison, WI. After an absence of many years, I had an opportunity to do a piece on WORT, and asked Ray if he had any thoughts for his audience in Madison. He sent me the following.....) </p>
         
<p>AS SOME OF YOU KNOW I've been in prison for political offenses since 1984. I was tried and acquitted of sedition. As the government stated in its indictment - our "revolutionary anti-imperialist organization" sought to challenge its authority to kill with impunity in Central America. I was convicted of bombing military facilities in an effort to expose U.S. war crimes against the people of El Salvador, Nicaragua and Guatemala. I was convicted of actions taken against American corporations whose power and products strengthened the racist apartheid system in South Africa.  </p>
<p>FOR THIS I'm supposed to suffer and die in prison. The trial judge recommended that I never be paroled - that I remain in prison until "expiration" of my 45 year sentence, if I don't expire of something else doing that kind of time.  </p>

<p>         TO PUNCTUATE THEIR HATRED of what they perceive to be my political beliefs and associations, the government sent me to their worst prison - the infamous Marion - in 1986. When the government built an ever higher tech, mind numbing penitentiary called Administrative Maximum (ADX), at Florence Colorado, I was sent there in 1995. As some of you know, I've written extensively about human rights violations, and the counterproductive, spirit-crushing nature of such prisons. </p>
<p>ON AUGUST 20, 1999,  after many long years of isolation and close confinement, where walls were never more than a few steps away, I was transferred from ADX to the maximum security penitentiary at Atlanta, Georgia. Built in 1905, Atlanta has held other political prisoners including Eugene Debs (a socialist), Alexander Berkman (an anarchist), and Pedro Albizu Campos (Puerto Rican Nationalist). Federal prisons have always served as way stations for revolutionaries and dissidents - from "Wobblies" (Industrial Workers of the World) to draft resisters. </p>
<p>IMMEDIATELY UPON MY ARRIVAL here I was placed in segregation - the hole. I was told by a representative of the administration that because of my extensive history of radical activism, and the many years I spent in their worst prisons, I would  remain in the hole for months before serious consideration would be given to releasing me into the prison general population. </p>
<p> SEGREGATION CONDITIONS at Atlanta are among the worst I've experienced. Every U.S. Supreme Court judge should be required to sleep on a cell floor as I did, smell shit backed up in the toilet, leave the cell to walk in an outside kennel cage three hours a week (if the guards are up to giving you that much). Maybe then we'd see some humanity from the robed ones.  </p>
<p>I HAD TO CHALLENGE what was becoming an increasingly volatile situation. There is nothing prison administrators fear more than solidarity among prisoners and a penetrating look at their operations from people outside the walls. Aware of this, friends and supporters initiated a campaign to get me out of the hole. This campaign was successful and I was released from segregation in December 1999, albeit under restrictive conditions. I can see the Moon now, something I've gone years without being able to do. I'd still be in the hole were it not for the efforts of so many caring and committed people whose collective voice was feet from the U.S. penitentiary at Atlanta to the Bureau of Prisons in Washington, D.C.. It was a voice to behold. Lest we succumb to that ubiquitous skepticism or the slippery slope of cynicism that too often mines the field of political activism - the notion that writing a letter of protest or support, or performing some other seemingly mundane task is wasted effort - we just proved otherwise. Struggle brings results, and all struggles begin with a first step and advance through commitment, work and sacrifice. And it's in this spirit that we can save our brother Mumia Abu Jamal from the state's executioner and ultimately free all political prisoners. </p>
<p>A SINGLE CORAL is infinitesimally small, but a coral reef is able to alter the ocean's current. Our little campaign to get me out of the hole built a big enough reef to alter the prison administration's designs on me. I am grateful to all who made this possible and thank those of you in Madison who pitched in - including you who at various times over the years sent me cards and letters, books and periodicals, kind words and encouragement. Some of you have remained active on various fronts and I take heart when I see you do not stand idly by when the system attempts to crush life with police power and dollar signs. I also want to thank the folks at WORT radio - past and present - who've allowed issues like that of political prisoners to be aired, issues which would not have otherwise seen the light of day. </p>
<p>SOMEONE WROTE TO ME recently asking me whether I thought the militancy of the anarchists/youth at the anti-WTO demonstrations in Seattle was counterproductive. My response to that is a resounding NO. And it's not even a matter of whether I personally agree or disagree with the tactic of smashing windows that reflect corporate profits over human needs. Destroying corporate property to make a political point has a long history among the oppressed. And it most certainly is not the major contradiction. The major contradiction is corporate power raping the earth, bankrolled by the sweat of underpaid and abused workers. It's not militancy that threatens to pull the plug on the American Left, but rather the lack of militancy and sustained activism. As the saying goes - think globally and act locally. Too often we fail to act on issues confronting us in our own communities - whether it be police brutality, jail and prison conditions, homelessness and affordable housing, labor activism and jobs, taking back the night, environmentalism, etc. Amidst the current weakness of the Left, the rule of thumb should not so much be ideology and party line as time, place and conditions.  The duty of the activist is to be active.  I'd rather see someone cross a police line than wallow in apathy.  </p>
<p>         THE LAST TIME I was in the city of Atlanta was in 1969. It was April - the first anniversary of Martin Luther King Jr.'s assassination. I was here with a contingent of the  Southern Student Organizing Committee. We gathered at the Ebenezer Baptist Church and marched to the state capital buildings, which were ringed by Georgia State Police. We were in Atlanta to honor Dr. King and press on for civil rights and opposition to the Viet Nam war. Between the church and state capital we stopped outside the county jail for a solidarity demonstration with prisoners inside. Thirty years ago there was a different consciousness about the role of prisoners in the pursuit of basic civil and human rights. They were seen as a potential part of the solution - not as part of the problem that deserved to be ostracized and forgotten. Now there are 2 million prisoners in America -25% of the world's entire prison population. The wages they receive for their forced labor is on par with and often less than what NIKE pays its Asian shoe and clothing workers. How do we continue to ignore exploitation on such a scale? </p>
<p>THIRTY YEARS AGO our battles were about human rights, and they're about human rights today. It's about daring to struggle for these rights if we want to win. It's about acting on principle and sound strategies, rather than generating antagonistic divisions through over-inflated rhetoric.  It's about Attica being all of us and Mumia being our brother. It's about a future for children that embraces peace, justice and freedom. </p>

           <p> Raymond Luc Levasseur </p>
            <p> Atlanta Federal Prison </p>

<p>                        Love,  </p>

<p>                        Ray</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.010" n="Restorative Justice" type="Article">
               <head>Restorative Justice</head>
               <docAuthor>By Harmon Wray</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>
<argument><p>Harmon Wray is...</p></argument>
<p>	In recent years many faith-based and secular criminal justice activists and scholars have developed a practical and theoretical perspective which offers both a critique of the prevailing criminal justice system and a paradigm of what an alternative system might look like. Usually called "restorative justice", this model has perhaps been most fully articulated by Howard Zehr in his seminal book Changing Lenses (Herald Press, 1995). Presently a number of religious organizations and some state corrections departments are tweaking and experimenting with restorative justice principles and methodologies. This is a promising development but at the same time it runs the risk of co-opting or watering down the radical vision 0f true restorative justice.</p>
<p>The distinctiveness of the restorative justice approach can best be understood by contrast with the criminal justice system in the USA. Our current system, based on the concept of retribution, or revenge, defines crime as primarily an offense against the laws of the state. The state, in turn, assumes the power to pick out a likely offender and to process this person through an adversarial drama in which the major actors are lawyers. Through either a plea-bargaining process or a trial in open court, played according to rules established by the state and enforced by the judge, the opposing attorneys fight it out in a sort of war game. Eventually the accused is declared either guilty or not guilty. If the person is found, or pleads, guilty, a sentence is imposed, which may amount to a symbolic slap on the wrist, a highly punitive prison term, ritual killing by the state, or something in between.</p>
<p>The focus is on offender and his/her past behavior. The real victim of the crime, if there is one, is treated as marginal, as is the community - except insofar as they can be manipulated into lobbying for vengeance-and the offender is treated as passive. The process is geared toward fixing blame, not solving problems. The relationship between the.victim and the offender is ignored. Both repentance and forgiveness are discouraged. Accountability is defined strictly as the offender taking his/her punishment, which-to call it by its real name-is the intentional infliction of pain of a human being by other human beings.</p>
<p>	The whole process encourages Competitive and individualistic values, assumes a win-lose outcome, ignores the social, economic, political, cultural, and moral context of the crime and of the appropriate response to it. It is based on a commitment to retribution by the state against the offender, not on the principle of restitution of the victim by the offender. Opportunities for abuse of discretion and for corruption, racism, sexism, and class discrimination-personal and institutional-abound.</p>
<p>Rooted in older, indigenous, tribal traditions of community justice and in biblical traditions of shalom (peace with justice), Jubilee economics, and the Sermon on the Mount, restorative Justice refocuses our gaze and reshapes the questions and assumptions underlying the retributive criminal justice system. It seeks de-institutionalize abstract system of jurisprudence and replace them with action by concrete, grassroots.</p>
<p>Rather than continuing and escalating the cycle of violence and coercion by both individuals and institutions restorative justice tries to stop it in its tracks. Rather than separating legal or criminal justice from the larger picture of distributive justice-that is, how wealth, power, and status are apportioned out in the society - restorative justice looks at the whole social, historical, and political context to determine how the law ought to be most fairly applied. At its best, restorative justice methodology is alert for patterns and systemic issues affecting the community-which often function as root causes of crime-that might emerge in the course of doing restorative justice in particular cases.</p>
<p>	Restorative justice reverses the retributive justice system at almost every point. Crime is understood primarily as the violation of one person by another, or-by extension-as the violation of one person or group by an institution or a system. The real victim, the offender, and the local community are all seen as the principal stakeholders and therefore. are principally involved in deciding what it will take to "make it right". Their relationships and feelings are closely attended to. A future, problem-solving, healing orientation is predominant. Accountability is understood as taking responsibility for what one has done by repenting of it, trying to make it right (typically through restitution by the offender to the victim), and not doing it again. Dialogue, not an adversarial battle, is normative.</p>
<p>The community takes responsibility for helping the offender and the victim "work it out" and holds the offender responsible for following through with whatever that entails. As the community seeks to support the victim, it also seeks to help the offender get what he/she needs and to integrate the offender further into the community, not cast him/her out of it.</p>
<p>	A restorative justice process considers the total context of the situation, not just the "crime" as an isolated event. Just as it seeks to empower victims, it also seeks to empower offenders by fostering in them remorse over having violated others, rather than regret at having been caught, and internal self-discipline, instead of the passive bearing up under externally imposed punishment. It teaches victim, offender, and community new ways of dealing with conflict.</p>
<p>	A restorative approach to justice encourages values of mutuality and cooperation and makes possible win-win outcomes. Instead of the unrealistic "forgive and forget" model, or the vengeful "remember and punish" model, restorative justice offers a healing vision of "remember, restore, and reconcile" for all the principal, parties: victim, offender, and community.</p>
<p>	A justice system based on restoration would look very different from our system. Such a system would not be "warm and fuzzy", characterized by an "I'm okay, you're okay" attitude. Nor would it be "soft on crime". But it would be more just in responding to crime, more preventive in its long-term outcomes, and more effective in educating and empowering all parties to analyze and transform the forces acting upon them.</p>
<p>There would be a lot more of offenders and victims struggling face-to-face with each other in the presence of community mediators, over what one has done to the other, and why, and what they now need to do about it, with the support of the community. And a lot less under-the-table deal making, courtroom theatrics, and gamesmanship by lawyers and judges, and "quick-fix" law-and-order rhetoric by politicians looking for easy votes.</p>
<p>We would have fewer courtrooms, and more neighborhood-based dispute mediation centers. Fewer cops, and more local volunteer mediators. Fewer guns and bullets, more talk. Drug education and treatment programs instead of a war on some of the people (i.e. young, poor, urban, Mrican American ) who use drugs. No private, for-profit prisons, and better publicly operated prisons. No more prison building boom, but more community-based alternative programs. No death penalty, more victim restitution. Less crime, more dialogue. More victims' rights, but not the right to revenge, and not at the expense of defendants' rights. No more sentence enhancement hate crime legislation, but less hate.</p>
<p>To be sure, not every criminal case lends itself to resolution by mediation, and the legal system needs to remain in place as back-up when mediation fails and to handle cases which it is not appropriate (for example, domestic violence cases and most rape and sexual abuse cases). The legal structure also must continue to play the critical role of monitoring the more informal, restorative efforts to do justice to insure the protection of the constitutional rights of all parties and guard against the specter of vigilante justice. But the focus of any justice system needs to be on the primary stakeholders themselves, not the professionals acting as their proxies.</p>
<p>	Piecemeal efforts at criminal justice reform have usually backfired and been easily co -opted. This could happen to restorative justice, too, but it is clear that only a theory and practice as bold and visionary as that offered by restorative justice has the potential to turn around the vicious, costly, unjust, and ineffective criminal justice system presently in place.</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.011" n="Treatment Oriented Courts:
A Viable Alternative to Incarceration for the Drug Offender" type="Article">
               <head>Treatment Oriented Courts:
A Viable Alternative to Incarceration for the Drug Offender</head>
               <docAuthor>By Donnarae Baity</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>
<argument><p>Donnarae Baity is Director of Georgia Community Resources Exchange, Inc.</p></argument>
<p>	The average person views drugs and crime as the two most urgent issues facing this country today. It's not paranoia. It's real! The relationship between drugs and criminal behavior is a major problem in this country. It's not difficult to identify either. One simple glance at criminal justice statistics makes it clear.</p>
<p>	In state prisons, the number of women drug offenders jumped more than 400 percent between 1986 and 1991 [get more recent dates.]. Incarceration increased even more dramatically for black women drug offenders, jumping 828 percent during the same period. More than two-thirds of the women in Federal prisons have been incarcerated for drug offenses. Three-fourths of men charged with domestic battery in a 1992 study reported by the National Research Council tested positive for alcohol, while half tested positive for illegal drugs. In 1994, drug testing of adult male arrestees reveals drug positives ranging from 48 percent in Houston to 82 percent in Manhattan. Among juveniles, two out of five arrested in 1994 tested positive for drugs, more than twice the rate in 1991.</p>
<p>	One-third of state prison inmates say that they were under the influence of drugs when they committed the crime for which they are in prison. In a 1993 survey of state prison inmates, one in four women and one in six men committed their first offense for money to buy drugs. Over 80 percent of state prison inmates had used illegal drugs and nearly half of those in prison for violent crime were current users when arrested.</p>
<p>	Americans are frustrated with being bombarded with the problem and seeing so little being done to prevent or even decrease it. The problem is clear but the solution is not. How do we reverse today's alarming impact of drugs and drug-related crime on our country? Is it possible to eliminate the revolving-door syndrome of substance abuse cycling in and out of the criminal justice system?</p>
<p>	We've been trying for years. In our efforts to reduce the severity of the issue we continue to arrest and incarcerated people at an alarming rate but drugs and crime continue to prevail. We legislate "get tough on crime" laws and wage a "war against drugs," yet the problem persists. We spend millions of dollars on building new jails and prisons, but the beat goes on. Among some three hundred police chiefs recently surveyed, 60 percent feel that law</p>
<p>[missing a page]</p>
<p>taskmaster, cheerleader, and mentor, in turn exhorting, threatening, encouraging, and congratulating the participant for his or her progress or lack thereof.</p>
<p>	Of course, positive reinforcement is better than negative sanctions, but to shape behavior both most be used. I recently attended a graduation of Atlanta's Fulton County Diversionary Drug Court and listened as the Judge and treatment team introduced the defendants individually and told the audience of how this particular individual was able to progress to recovery. For many of the offenders, a Drug Court graduation is the only graduation they have ever attended.</p>
<p>	On the other hand, it is just as important for the offender to be sanctioned for program failures. However sanctions require a sense of balance. Offenders are admonished for their failures and at the same time encouraged in their ultimate ability to succeed. Most Drug Court judges handle program failures, as well as remands into custody, early on in their calendars so that all offenders present have the opportunity to see the consequences of failure. It's amazing what effect even a single day's incarceration can have on both the offender and the audience.</p>
<p>	It is self-evident that offender accountability is the cornerstone of successful drug treatment. It is also the reason why Drug Courts hold such strong appeal. The general public is tired of hearing stories about criminal defendants "beating the system" or manipulating it to their advantage (and usually the public's disadvantage). Overall, it quickly becomes obvious that the treatment program requirements are more demanding than the applicable sanctions received through traditional adjudication. It is common to hear both successful and unsuccessful participants comment that "if I had known how tough this was going to be, I would have just taken the jail time!"</p>
<p>	Drug Courts <hi rend="italic">are</hi> providing a substantive
and cost-effective alternative to standard incarceration, and are
reducing recidivism rates, according to a recent study by <hi rend="itaqlic">Drug Strategies</hi>. Using the coercive power of the court to force abstinence from drugs and alter behavior or substance abusing offenders has significantly changed the way the courts system works. According to the study, re-arrest rates among drug court graduates are lower than for drug abusing offenders who have been released from prison or are on probation. Recidivism ranges from 5 percent to 28 percent for those who were at some point in their case involved in the program, and it is only 4 percent for graduates of the drug court program. A 1996 Drug Court Clearinghouse and Technical Assistance Project study found that in the Miami drug courts, 3 percent of drug court participants were re-arrested within one year, as compared to 30 percent of those in the comparison group who were not in the drug court program. In Austin, Texas, the recidivism rate for drug court participants was 25 percent; the rate for the comparison group was 59 percent. "We are seeing dramatic reductions in recidivism. They aren't committing crimes anymore. They are getting jobs, supporting their families, helping their kids," said Margaret Beaudry, research director at <hi rend="italic">Drug Strategies</hi>. In short, they are working!</p>
<p>	Debate about the ever-increasing cost of incarceration at the local and state level provides an opportunity to further develop new and innovative programs that can treat drug-using offenders in their own communities with minimal incarceration, criminal recidivism, and cost. The challenge continues to be to prove that Drug Courts and court-ordered rehabilitation programs can work to the benefit of the individual participant as well as to the benefit of society as a whole.</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc22-2.012" n="Katya Lezin. Finding Life on Death Row. Boston: Northeastern University Press, ?." type="Review">
               <head>Katya Lezin. Finding Life on Death Row. Boston: Northeastern University Press, ?.</head>
               <docAuthor>Reviewed by Nibs Stroupe</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 2, 2000</docDate>
<argument><p></p></argument>
<p> I am opposed to the death penalty, but I understand the primal desire for vengeance. If one of my loved ones were murdered, I would want a shot at revenge. My impulse is nothing new in human history - it is as old as blood feuds or Hammurabi's Code or Jesus' words in the Sermon on the Mount. Katya Lezin's compelling book speaks directly to this impulse and testifies strongly to the need for opposition to the death penalty. The number of governments using the death penalty is shrinking. As Steve Bright notes in the Foreword, four nations now account for 80 percent of the documented executions in the world:  China, Iran, Saudi Arabia, and the United States.</p>
<p>     My opposition to the death penalty comes from moral, political, legal, and religious reasons. The moral ground comes from the dehumanization of those convicted - we must strip them of their humanity in order to allow ourselves to kill them. In this process, we as part of the state become the killers, and in so doing, become the very thing that we seek to eliminate in using the death penalty. The political ground, as demonstrated so ably in this book, is that the overwhelming majority of those sentenced to die are poor. The death penalty is not a response to murder in this country. It is a response to murder committed by poor people. The legal reason is connected to the political, pointed out bluntly in Lezin's book: the appalling lack of adequate legal representation of those who are poor and are accused of murder. This reason also connects us to the consciousness that is the most frightening - far more people than we wish to admit who are convicted and sentenced to death are innocent. The religious ground for me as a minister is simple but fundamental: God is the author of life, and the use of the death penalty violates the Sixth Commandment.  </p>
<p>     Katya Lezin touches on all of these in this enlightening portrait of six people sentenced to die. It reminds us that they really are people, and it reminds us how callous our process of convicting and sentencing them really is. In doing this, the book does not sentimentalize them or their crimes. The author does not choose those who may be innocent, though it is unclear about one person. Innocence is not the question here - the nature of state-imposed death is the issue.</p>
<p>     Lezin puts the death penalty in its terrible context in our nation's history.  The book is well written, but it is difficult reading because it is about the power of death: people who are murdered and people who are executed by the state. The death machine constructed by the state is even more heinous than the original murders themselves. Yet, this book is also deeply inspirational reading in its portraits of people who bring humanity in a destructive and dehumanizing world: the convicted people who turn out to be people after all; the attorneys who oppose the death penalty and who work ceaselessly to save the lives of their clients against overwhelming odds; volunteers and ministers who bring humanity and the possibility of life in the midst of death; family members who remain loyal and loving even when their beloved is convicted of murder; prison guards and wardens who try to steer a course between the death machine and retaining and sharing their humanity.</p>
<p>     Katya Lezin reminds us that in our use of the death penalty, we are killing real people. In such a situation, one would think that there would be a meticulous legal process that bends over backward to guard the rights of the accused. What we see in this book in an appalling death machine that tramples on rights and that would be comical if it weren't so serious and deadly: a defense attorney who is drunk at the trial and held in contempt but who remains on the case and indeed, the next day both attorney and client come from jail to the trial; a defense attorney who calls no witnesses;  a prosecuting attorney who has a long record of racial discrimination in jury selection but is never reprimanded. Five of the six defendants in the book had court appointed attorneys who were either callous or incompetent.  Four are saved because of the work of committed and competent attorneys, paralegals, and volunteers, all of whom are connected to the Southern Center for Human Rights in Atlanta.</p>
<p>       The recent Columbia University study demonstrated that 67 percent of death cases are overturned nationally, largely related to the issues raised here.  The Chicago Tribune study in June of the 131 executions during George W. Bush's tenure as governor of Texas revealed a cynical disregard for justice, and Finding Life on Death Row testifies to that same process in South Carolina, Alabama and Georgia.  This book combines the theoretical struggles over the death penalty with portraits of the humanity of those convicted under it.  It is compelling reading. It reminds us of our humanity and the humanity of others, and it reminds us of the forces of death that seek to crush that humanity.  It is realistic, difficult, and hopeful, and it asks us to take our stands and to be witnesses for life.</p>
</div2>
	 </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>