<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Southern Changes.  Volume 20, Number 2, 1998</title>
            <author>Staff</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>staff</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory University. Permission is granted to 
download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to 
the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided  
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact 
either: Southern Changes Web Project or Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic 
collections and services, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>2003</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Southern Changes Web Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Southern Changes.  Volume 20, Number 2. 1998</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is produced in conjunction with the  
Southern Changes Web Project at Emory University and the Southern Regional Council, 133 Carnegie Way, Suite 900, Atlanta, GA 30303-1024</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="v20-2.001" n="Southern Changes 20:2" type="Volume">
            <head>Southern Changes.  Volume 20, Number 2, 1998</head>
            <p> 
               <title>Southern Changes.</title>  Volume 20, Number 2, 1998</p>
            <div2 id="v20-2.002" n="Covering Race: A Deep White Sleep" type="Article">
               <head>Grand Opening: The Mississippi Sovereignty Commission</head>
               <docAuthor>By BILL MINOR</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 20, No. 2, 1998</docDate>

<p>Mississippi recently had a Grand Opening. The grand opening of what? The old state Sovereignty Commission files, of course.</p>
<p>Many in the news profession have been itching to get their hands on the whole sorry mass of tomfoolery the old state segregation watchdog agency was up to during its seventeen years of existence from 1956 to 1973.</p>
<p>I used to refer to it as the "KGB of the cotton patches" because of the way its agents went around spying on a lot of poor Black folks, many not long from the farm, if they bucked the system of white mastery. Of course, they also spied on some white folks as well, and doted on tracking anybody who came down from Yankee-land to "sow discord" among our happy Black folks.</p>
<p>The Mississippi Sovereignty Commission was largely a Keystone Kops operation, a bunch of bumbling would-be sleuths trying to prop up a dying system of white supremacy.</p>
<p>What Commission agents mostly did, sinister though much of it was, was to compile a gumbo of innuendo, hearsay, and utterly false information about individuals who somehow came within the Commission's scope.</p>
<p>My view is that what will be found in the files will offer very few nuggets of news or revelations not already revealed in print. What has been seen earlier, however, amounts to only part of the Sovereignty Commission files. The Grand Opening opens the whole works.</p>
<p>Looking at some of the Commission's files brings back memories of how, as the Mississippi correspondent for the <title>New Orleans Times-Picayune</title> in the 1950s and 6Os, I constantly kept an eye on the Sovereignty agency, which had its office just down the ball from the press room at the state Capitol.</p>
<p>Opening of the entire Commission files results from a court order by U.S. District Judge William Barbour, who several years ago struck down an act of the Mississippi Legislature which had sealed the files for fifty years. His order turned the details of opening the files over to the state's Department of Archives and History, which systematically cataloged the files and classified names appearing therein as "actors" and "victims." An actor is anyone the Commission considered to have done some thing beneficial to the Commission and a victim was anyone under the Commission's scrutiny.</p>
<p>According to the glossary which Archives and History prepared, I show up twice as an actor and twenty-three times as a victim. But I have not bothered to checkout each instance I show up in the files.</p>
<p>Over the years I have seen some copies of some of the reports that went in to the Commission files concerning me and they related to the journalistic work I was doing. For instance, the late Erle Johnston, the ex-Forest Mississippi weekly editor who served as the agency's executive director for six years, had reported to the Commission that he had "straightend Minor out" after I had broken stories that didn't make his outfit look very good. My old friend Erie did assure me back some years ago that he had seen to it that my personal file had been shredded before he left the Commission in the Late 1960s. As for "straightening me out," I always kidded him as a miserable failure.</p>
<p>Governor J.P. Coleman, a moderate for his time, is credited or blamed for creation of the Sovereignty Commission in 1956. However difficult it may be for some to understand today, Coleman was under siege, at the time, by forces of the powerful segregationist white Citizens' Council which controlled a large part of the Legislature.</p>
<p>Although, in conscience, Coleman opposed the idea of creating a segregation strategy agency in state government, he theorized that it was a way to keep the extremists off his back and that he could control what the agency did. Indicative of his restraint was an incident in May, 1959 when a Sovereignty Commission investigator intercepted a bizarre plan hatched by Citizens' Council braintrusters to have NAACP national director Roy Wilkins arrested when he spoke in Jackson.</p>
<p>At the last minute, the Commission investigator stopped a Hinds County deputy from arresting Wilkins on an affidavit sworn out by a segregationist who later admitted to being put up to it by Citizens' Council mogul William J. Simmons. The affidavit charged Wilkins with advocating overthrow of a 1956 state segregation law. Had Wilkins been arrested on such a charge in Mississippi, it would have given the state another huge black eye.</p>
<p>Citizens' Council leaders seized control of the spy agency, ending the relative moderation of the Sovereignty Commission, when Coleman left office in 1960 and Ross Barnett moved in. Aside from getting the Sovereignty Commission to funnel some $100,000 in state funds to support Citizens' Council programs, the Council also got the agency to do much of its footwork.</p>
<p>Of all the mean things done by the old state Sovereignty Commission, one of the most despicable was aimed in 1962 at weekly editor Hazel Brannon Smith of Lexington, Mississippi. At the lime, Smith was struggling against an economic boycott of her <title>Lexington Advertiser</title> launched by the white Citizens' Council in Holmes County.</p>
<p>The Lexington woman editor, who was white, had become friendly with some of the young civil rights workers based in Jackson who wanted to start a little newspaper called the <title>Free Press</title>. Because they were unable to get it printed in Jackson they asked Smith to print it for them in her l plant. Needing the little additional revenue, she agreed to.</p>
<p>If she was not already under scrutiny by the Sovereignty Commission, Smith now became a prime target of Sovereignty agents. They tracked her every move. One day when she and her husband, Walter, delivered bundles of the <title>Free Press</title> to the office of the little paper, Sovereignty agents armed with cameras photographed the whole thing, showing Smith with several of the civil rights workers known to the Commission.</p>
<p>That was when another dark, deep charade was perpetrated by the Sovereignty Commission. It turned over copies of the photographs to an arch-segregationist state senator from Smith's Holmes County. Next day, he took the floor of the state legislature and, waving the damning photographs, denounced Smith as some kind of traitor to the state of Mississippi.</p>
<p>Of course, this entire sorry episode was calculated for one thing: to deliver the final economic blow to the already vulnerable <title>Lexington Advertiser</title> and drive Hazel Smith out of town, perhaps the state. But Hazel Brannon Smith was a tough customer. Somehow she kept the paper going, though barely. She was, however, so financially wounded that she would never recover.</p>
<p>Her editorial courage the following year in 1964 moved the Pulitzer Prize Committee to award Hazel its prize for editorial writing, which it said demonstrated "steadfast adherence to her editorial duty in the face of great pressure and opposition."</p>
<p>In the early 1980s her husband Walter died. Then, after struggling more than a decade for survival, her news paper succumbed amid a sea of debt in 1985. Not long after, she was diagnosed with Alzheimer's disease, and in the spring of 1994, completely broke, Hazel died in a nursing home in Cleveland, Tennessee.</p>
<p>Back in the halcyon days of the <title>Lexington Advertiser</title> in the 1940s and early 1950s, when she was a dazzling brunette bachelor lady, Hazel was the belle of the Mississippi Press Association. When she coated through the lobby of Biloxi's grand old Buena Vista Hotel at MPA conventions, the lustful eyes of a dozen or more country editors followed her every move. Her Cinderella world changed radically, however, after the 1954 Brown, Board of Education desegregation ruling, which inspired the birth of the white Citizens' Council in Mississippi. Holmes County became a hotbed of Council support.</p>
<p>Then, in 1955, when Hazel blasted the local sheriff for shooting a Black man in the back for no cause, the segregationist Council initiated its systematic boycott to destroy her newspaper. The sheriff sued her for liable, winning a judgment in the county circuit court. The judgment was overturned later by the state Supreme Court, but the expense of defending herself sent her into financial straits. In 1993 a somewhat fictionalized movie of Hazel's lonely battle against racial bigotry as a courageous editor was produced by the ABC network. It fell far short of telling the n story of her struggle against Mississippi's Citizens' Council and Sovereignty Commission and the paper's demise.</p>
<p>The Sovereignty Commission was finally put out of business in 1973 when Gay. Bill Wailer vetoed its appropriation, ending another sordid chapter of Mississippi history.</p>

<p><argument><hi rend="italic">Averaging three stories a day as a stringer for national media like the Associated Press, <title>Newsweek</title>, and <title>The New York Times</title>, and for many years at the <title>New Orleans Times-Picayune</title>, Mississippi journalist Bill Minor helped bring the nation's attention to the civil rights movement, Southern injustices, and corruption. Bricks and bullets shattered the windows and a cross was bunted at the Capitol Reporter office, the weekly paper he owned in Jackson, after he published articles detailing the Klan's resurgence and influence in state government (For more about Minor, see "Eyes on Mississippi" in the August/September 1992 Southern Changes.)</hi></argument></p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
