<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Southern Changes.  Volume 22, Number 3, 2001</title>
            <author>Staff</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>staff</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory University. Permission is granted to 
download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to 
the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided  
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact 
either: Southern Changes Web Project or Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic 
collections and services, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>2003</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Southern Changes Web Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Southern Changes.  Volume 21, Number 3. 1999</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is produced in conjunction with the  
Southern Changes Web Project at Emory University and the Southern Regional Council, 133 Carnegie Way, Suite 900, Atlanta, GA 30303-1024</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="v22-3.001" n="Southern Changes 22:3" type="Volume">
            <head>Southern Changes.  Volume 22, Number 3, 2001</head>
            <p> 
               <title>Southern Changes.</title>  Volume 22, Number 3, 2001</p>
            <div2 id="v22-3.002" n="Cells for Sale" type="Article">
               <head>Cells for Sale</head>
               <docAuthor>By SI KAHN</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 3, 2001</docDate>

<p>Begin your journey through time in Durham, North Carolina, driving north on Interstate 85 towards Richmond, one-time capital of the Confederacy. Just before the Virginia border, turn east onto U.S. 158. Travel through Littleton, where members of the Lumbee-Tuscarora tribe routed the Ku Klux Klan in the 1950S. Pass through Roanoke Rapids, where in 1974 workers at the town's seven J.P. Stevens cotton mills voted to join the Textile Workers Union of America and started a historic six-year national campaign for a contract. Keep traveling through history until you cross into Hertford County and there, not far from where the Meherrin River flows into the Chowan, you'll come to the old Vann plantation.</p>
<p>These days, it doesn't look like much, just some cotton fields backed by scrub forest. But in 1850, it was a major plantation with more than fifty slaves. In 1860, only 611 plantations in the entire state owned more than fifty slaves, making the Vanns one of the larger slaveholding families in North Carolina.</p>
<p>But, if Corporate America has its way, the old Vann place will soon be back in business with a vengeance. Wackenhut Corrections, a multi-national corporation that builds and runs private prisons for profit, is planning to build a 1,320-bed prison here. They will operate it under a contract from the Federal Bureau of Prisons, which plans to ship the prison 1,200 inmates from the District of Columbia, almost all of them African Americans. So Wackenhut will be importing well over one thousand Black men from the District of Columbia and imprisoning them on the same plantation where African Americans, possibly including some of their own ancestors, were held as slaves 150 years ago.</p>
<p>This is just one example of the ways in which the for- profit prison industry is changing the nature of criminal justice in the United States. The rise of for-profit private prisons raises critical issues for democracy, as well as for the balance of public and private power in an open society.</p>
<p>For-profit private prisons are a relatively recent development.  The current wave of privatization generally in the U.S. is less than twenty years old and is still heavily contested.  It's paralleled by the recent unprecedented rise in the prison population and in new prison construction.  And, of course, for-profit prison privatization is emerging as a major factor in this dynamic, as well as a major growth industry and social phenomenon. Between 1990 and 1999, the number of prisoners in for-profit private prisons in creased over 1500 percent, from less than 8,000 to over 123,000.</p>
<p>This is partly a response to recent economic and political conditions. States, counties, and cities are hard pressed financially and politically by the "need" for increased prison "beds" and have turned to for-profit private corporations to provide them. By contracting with for-profit private prison corporations, elected officials avoid the need to go to the voters with politically risky bond issues for new prison construction. They can also report the costs of these con tracts under operating expenses, thus appearing to cut costs and "government jobs."</p>
<p>To for-profit private prison corporations, the issue is simple: the more prisoners, the more profit.  This partly accounts for their aggressiveness in trying to privatize as much as possible as quickly as they can.  In addition, they're obviously trying to grab as much territory as they can before resistance to for-profits prisons hardens.</p>
<p>But the private prison corporations have another strategic reason for speed. If the present trend towards prison privatization continues, it will quickly reach a "tipping point" where private rather than public prisons are the norm. At this point, any possibility of restoring prisons to public confront even less hope than it does today. As difficult as it is for inmates and theft supporters, including progressive corrections officers, to change conditions when prisons are publicly held and operated, imagine how much harder that will be if the majority of prisons and detention facilities are in private corporate hands. If all prisons turn private, their parent corporations will have no more interest in reducing the shameful number of inmates in this country than Marriott does in holding down its number of hotel guests. Through campaign contributions made possible by in creased profits, they'll become an even more significant pressure than they are now towards imprisoning the maxi mum number of people for as long as possible. Profit rather than the public good becomes the measure of all things.</p>
<p>The development and growth of for-profit private prisons has many negative consequences, including the current interstate commerce in prisoners by for-profit private prison corporations. This is one of the tragedies of prison privatization. Prisoners are incarcerated at great distances from their families, homes and communities, basically to suit the convenience of corporations. Many studies have shown that prisoners in these circumstances are significantly less likely to reintegrate themselves successfully on release and, of course, are therefore far more likely to be returned to prison.</p>
<p>This "export-import" business has a particular impact on the South. The "exporting" states tend to be those with higher costs per day for prisoners. Exporting prisoners is not just about solving prison over-crowding but about saving money, including the capital costs of building new prisons. The "Importing" states tend to be those with lower costs per prisoner per day, often a reflection of their significantly lower labor costs as a result of lack of unionization among corrections officers and other prison employees. Not surprisingly, the importing states tend to be in the South, with its historic low labor costs and lack of unionization.</p>
<p>It's possible to foresee a scenario where the South, already the site for so many of its own prisoners, becomes the holding area for many of the prisoners from the rest of the nation, the vast majority of whom will be African Americans and other people of color. The South already has a long and shameful history of incarceration and the racialized use of imprisonment as a tool of social control, including chain gangs and convict labor, which tend to make prison privatization more acceptable. According to recent statistics, almost 70 percent of all prisoners in private facilities are in the eleven states of the old Confederacy and over 95 percent of all private prison facilities and detention centers in the U.S. are owned or operated by Southern prison corporations.</p>
<p>Another negative consequence is the growth of "speculation" or "spec" prisons. The for-profit private prison corporations are using speculation prisons as a way of side stepping current state legislative restrictions on the construction of private prisons for designated state use. Speculation prisons are particularly insidious, not just because they side step the intention of responsible state legislators to restrict and control prison privatization, but because they create pressure for more prisoners. From a management point of view, a prison is like a hotel or motel: you want to fill every bed, every night.  If you don't have enough guests, you do whatever you can to get them -- including supporting campaigns for mandatory and longer sentences. </p>
<p>For-profit private prisons have experienced incidents involving deaths, disturbances, physical, and sexual abuse of prisoners, than extent much higher than that in public prisons. To a large extent, such incidents are inherent to the operation of for-profit private prisons, due to their high employee turnover rates and consequent lack of experience among prison personnel. Experience at many prisons which have been established by private corporations in rural areas has shown a turnover rate considerably in excess of that found in public facilities. It is not uncommon for the local workforce to become depleted, with the consequent need to recruit prison personnel from farther and farther away. The long distances such personnel need to drive to work further increases the likelihood of high turn over rates.</p>
<p>Prison privatization also privatizes decision making and access. For example, for-profit private prisons can refuse to supply the basic information about their operations that public prisons are required to provide. Within the prison industry, such conditions, ranging from privacy to secrecy, are obvious incentives to corruption. It's difficult enough to control corruption in prisons under any circumstances. When you also impose the veil of secrecy and legal protection which is standard operating procedure in most major corporations, you are not only inviting additional corruption, you are also making sure it will be more difficult to root out.</p>
<p>For-profit private prisons are also one of the forces driving the increased incarceration of young people of color. Whole inner-city communities are being robbed of their economic and social potential as young African- American and Latino men and, increasingly, women are arrested and incarcerated, a pattern which is also repeated in other communities of color. The statistics related to the African- American community are both well-known and discouraging:</p>

<p>• Of African-American men between age 20 and twenty-nine, one out of three is either in prison, on probation or on parole.</p>
<p>• There are more African-American men in prison than in college.</p>
<p>It is common knowledge how devastating this development has been to communities of color. Prison not only robs young people of their youth, it too often bars them from future employment.  Should we then be surprised when communities of color are left behind economically and politically? Or when young people of color say that things today are worse than forty years ago, that the Civil Rights Movement accomplished nothing?</p>
<p>One of the ironies of the growth in incarceration, however, is that it's created economic opportunity for some people of color. Increasing numbers of correctional officers are themselves people of color. Because public prisons tend to be organized, these employees enjoy reasonable wages and benefits, along with considerable job security.</p>
<p>But all this changes when prisons are privatized. Some for-profit private prisons pay wages that are barely above the minimum wage, with few or no benefits other than those required bylaw. Turnover for employees in private prisons is astounding, ranging up to 100 percent a year. Working conditions are both difficult and dangerous.</p>
<p>It is unfortunate that one of the few economic opportunities open to people of color in so many poor and rural communities is guarding other people of color. But as long as these are the few jobs that are available to them, they need to be good jobs, with decent salaries, good fringe benefits, job security, adequate training, and protection.</p>
<p>To summarize the political situation and to cow dude, three parallel developments have been taking place over the past ten years:</p>
<p>• Demands by political leaders and, to some extent by the public, for more prisons, a product of our seeing incarceration as an easy answer to all social problems;</p>
<p>• Resistance by voters to increased taxes and/or new bond issues; and,</p>
<p>•The development and growth of the for-profit private prison industry.
These three developments are much more related than any of us have realized. To put it simply: Politicians are building careers on being "tough on crime" (which translates to many white voters as "tough on people of color"). So they promise to build more and more prisons. But they also can't go to these same voters to approve prison construction bonds, which would involve higher taxes: these days, almost any politician who goes to the voters with a major bond issue is putting her/his career on the line. So they're between a rock and a hard place. They want to build prisons so they can build their careers, but they lack and can't get the capital to do so.</p>
<p>Enter the for-profit private prison corporations, with their ability to capitalize prison construction themselves. No bonds, no referendums, no tax increases, no political risks. No wonder so many elected officials are willing to cut these deals.</p>
<p>But if for-profit private prisons become publicly unacceptable, politically risky, economically unfeasible, or even illegal, it will also create a different dynamic for elected officials. Without an easy way to build new prisons, to promote incarceration as the politically acceptable be-all and end-all for social problems, they may need to come to grips with the limits of the current criminal justice system. In such a situation, rights, reform, rehabilitation, and restorative justice again be come imaginable-but only in a public and publicly- accountable system of justice, as is not only appropriate but critical to a democratic society.</p>

<argument><p><hi rend="italic">
Si Kahn is executive director of Grassroots Leadership and is campaign director for the Public Justice and Safety Campaign based in Charlotte, North Carolina.</hi></p></argument>
</div2>

<div2 id="v22-3.003" n="Facing the Demon Head On: Institutional Racism and the Prison Industrial Complex" type="Article">
               <head>Facing the Demon Head On: Institutional Racism and the Prison Industrial Complex</head>
               <docAuthor>By MANNING MARABLE</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 22, No. 3, 2001</docDate>

<p>As long as black people have lived in America, they have experienced some version of institutional or structural racism. During slavery, African Americans were defined as private property or chattel, purchased and sold on auction blocks. In the period following Reconstruction until the early 1960s, African Americans, especially in the South, lived under the oppressive restrictions of Jim Crow segregation. In the northern states, blacks were generally permitted to vote and had access to most public accommodations, but were forced by racial covenants and restrictive laws to live in ghettoes.</p>
<p>Under each successive racial formation, African Americans and their white allies formed political and social pro test movements, which ultimately transformed the nature of their society. In the antebellum South, there were uprisings and day-to-day resistance by enslaved African Americans, and in the northern states an abolitionist movement developed that contributed to the establishment of the Republican Party. Under Jim Crow, leaders such as Dr. Marlin Luther King, Jr., Fannie Lou Hamer, James Farmer, Ella Baker, and a broad coalition of civil rights organizations mounted a series of nonviolent, direct action campaigns that directly led to the desegregation of the South. In the northern states, African Americans employed a variety of strategies, from the labor union organizing of A. Philip Randolph and Bayard Rustin, to the mass political mobilization efforts that elected thousands of public officials, to achieve greater black representation at all levels of society. Progress was frequently slow, but the black freedom movement was generally successful in identifying the specific institutional barriers to American-American equality, and then ultimately finding the appropriate tactics to challenge then.</p>
<p>In the past three decades, the structure and character of American institutional racism has changed dramatically. We can measure the advances of African Americans in many ways. The number of black elected officials, barely 100 in 1964, has climbed above 10,000; the black consumer market has grown from $70 billion in 1980 to over $350 billion today. There is an affluent and substantial black middle class, and the economic expansion of the l99Os greatly improved the quality of life even for millions of working-class and low-income households. The unemployment rate of African Americans has now fallen to about 7 percent which, according to sociologist William Julius Wilson, is <q direct="unspecified">"the lowest since the Bureau of Labor Statistics began compiling comparable data by race in 1972."</q></p>
<p>However, this new prosperity for the black middle class obscures a very real crisis for millions of other African Americans. The unprecedented expansion of what a number of scholars increasingly describe as a "prison industrial complex" has created an oppressively new context for the articulation of racial politics. According to an August 2000 Justice Department report, the total population of the nation's jails and prisons exceeded two million at the end of 1999. The dynamic and seemingly unchecked growth of the U.S. prison population has many profound consequences-politically, economically and socially-for all people of color.</p>
<p>Beginning in the 1960s and 1970s, for a variety of reasons, rates of violent crime, including murder, rape and robbery, increased dramatically, especially in urban areas. By the late 1970s, nearly one half of all Americans were afraid to walk within a mile of their homes at night, and 90 percent responded in surveys that the U.S. criminal justice system was not dealing harshly enough with criminals. Politicians like Richard Nixon, George Wallace, and Ronald Reagan began to campaign successfully on the theme of "Law and Order." The death penalty, which was briefly outlawed by the Supreme Court, was reinstated. Local, state, and federal expenditures for law enforcement rose sharply. Behind much of the anti-crime rhetoric was a not- too-subtle racial dimension, the projection of crude stereo types about the link between criminality and black people. Rarely did these politicians observe that minority and poor people, not the white middle class, were statistically much more likely to experience violent crimes of all kinds. The argument was made that law enforcement officers should be given much greater latitude in suppressing crime, that sentences should be lengthened and made mandatory, and that prisons should be designed not for the purpose of rehabilitation, but punishment.</p>
<p>As a result there was a rapid expansion in the personnel of the criminal justice system, as well as the construction of new prisons. What occurred in New York State, for example, was typical of what happened nationally. From 1817 to 1981, New York had opened thirty-three state prisons. From 1982 to 1999, another thirty-eight state prisons were constructed. The state's prison population at the time of the Attica prison revolt in September1971 was about 12,500. By 1999, there were over 71,000 prisoners in New York State correctional facilities.</p>
<p>In 1974, the number of Americans incarcerated in all state prisons stood at 187,500. By 1991, the number had reached 711,700. Nearly two-thirds of all state prisoners in 1991 had less than a high school education. One third of all prisoners were unemployed at the time of their nests. Incarceration rates by the end of the 1980s had soared to unprecedented rates, especially for black Americans.  As of December 1989 the total U.S. prison population, including federal institutions, exceeded one million for the first time in history, an incarceration rate of the general population of one out of every 250 citizens. For African Americans, the rate was over 700 per 100,000, or about seven times more than for whites. About one half of all prisoners were black. Twenty-three percent of all black males in their twenties were either in jail or prison, on parole, probation, or awaiting trial. The rate of incarceration of black Americans in 1989 had even surpassed that experienced by blacks who still lived under the apartheid regime of South Africa.</p>
<p>By the early 1990s, rates for all types of violent crime began to plummet. But the laws, which sent offenders to prison, were made even more severe. Children were increasingly viewed as adults in courts, and subjected to harsher penalties. Laws like California's "three strikes and you're out" eliminated the possibility of parole for repeat offenders. The vast majority of these new prisoners were nonviolent offenders, and many were convicted of drug offenses that carried long prison terms. Nationwide, African Americans and Latinos comprised 24.3 percent of the population in 1999, but represented 63.6 percent of state and federal prisoners and 78.8 percent of state prisoners convicted of drug offenses. The pattern of racial bias in these statistics is confirmed by the research of the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, which found that while African Americans today constitute only 14 percent of all drug users nationally, they are 35 percent of all drug nests, 55 percent of all drug convictions, and 75 percent of all prison admissions for drug offenses. Currently, the racial proportions of those under some type of correctional supervision, including parole and probation, are one-in-fifteen for young white males, one-in-ten for young Latino males, and one-in- three for young African-American males. Statistically to day, more than eight out of every ten African-American males will be arrested at some point in their lifetime.</p>
<p>The latest innovation in American corrections system is "special housing units" (SHU), but which prisoners also generally refer to as "The Box." SHUs are uniquely designed solitary confinement cells, in which prisoners are locked down for twenty-three hours a day for months or even years at a time. SHU cellblocks are electronically monitored, prefabricated structures of concrete and steel, about fourteen feet long and eight feet wide, amounting to 120 square feet of space. The two inmates who are confined in each cell, however, actually have only about sixty square feet of usable space, or thirty square feet per person. All meals are served to prisoners through a thin slot cut into the steel door. The toilet unit, sink, and shower are all located in the cell. Prisoners are permitted one hour "exercise time" each day in a small concrete balcony, stir-rounded by heavy security wire, directly connected with their SHU cells. Educational and rehabilitation programs for SHU prisoners are prohibited. Although Amnesty International and human rights groups condemned SHUs, claiming that such forms of imprisonment constitute the definition of torture under international law, many states are increasing the number of SHU facilities in their state prisons. As of 1998, California had constructed 2,942 SHU beds, followed by Mississippi (1,756), Arizona (1,728), Virginia (1,267), Texas (1,229), Louisiana (1,048) and Florida (1,000). Solitary confinement which historically had been defined even by corrections officials as an extreme disciplinary measure, is becoming increasingly the norm.</p>
<p>The introduction of SHUs reflects a general mood in the country that the growing penal population is essentially beyond redemption. If convicted felons cease to be viewed as human beings, why should they be treated with any humanity? This punitive spirit was behind the Republican- controlled Congress and President Clinton's decision in 1995 to eliminate inmate eligibility for federal Pell Grant awards for higher education. As of 1994, 23,000 prisoners throughout the U.S., had received Pell Grants, averaging about $1,500 per award. The total amount of educational support granted prisoners, $35 million, represented only 0.6 percent of all Fell Grant funding nationally. Many studies have found that prisoners who participate in higher education programs and especially those who complete college degrees have significantly lower rates of recidivism. For all prison inmates, for example, recidivism aver ages between 50 to 70 percent Federal parolees have a recidivism rate of 40 percent Prisoners with a college education have recidivism rates of only 5 to 10 percent. Given the high success ratio of prisoners who complete advanced degree work and the relatively low cost of public investment, such educational programs should make sense. But following the federal governments lead, many states have also ended their tuition benefits programs for state prisoners.</p>
<p>What are the economic costs for American society of the vast expansion of our prison-industrial complex? According to criminal justice researcher David Barlow at the University of Wisconsin at Milwaukee, between 1980 and 2000, the combined expenditures of federal, state, and local governments on police have increased about 400 percent. Corrections expenditures for building new prisons, upgrading existing facilities, hiring more guards, and related costs, increased approximately 1000 percent. Although it currently costs about $70,000 to construct a typical prison cell, and about $25,000 annually, to supervise and maintain each prisoner, the U.S. is currently building 1,725 new prison beds per week.</p>
<p>The driving ideological and cultural forces that rationalize and justify mass incarceration are the white American public's stereotypical perception about race and crime. As Andrew Hacker noted in 1995, <q direct="unspecified">"Quiteclearly,'blackcrime' does not make people think about tax evasion or embezzling from brokerage firms. Rather, the offenses generally associated with blacks are those . . involving violence."</q> A number of researchers have found that racial stereotypes of African Americans - as "violent," "aggressive," 'hostile," and "short-tempered" - greatly influence whites' judgments about crime. Generally, most whites are inclined to give black and Latino defendants more severe judgments of guilt and lengthier prison sentences than whites who commit identical crimes. Racial bias has been well established especially in capital cases, where killers of white victims are much more likely to receive the death penalty than those who murder African Americans.</p>
<p>The greatest victims of these racialized processes of unequal justice, of course, are African-American and Latino young people. In April 2000, utilizing national and state data compiled by the FBI, the justice Department and six leading foundations issued a comprehensive study that documented vast racial disparities at every level of the juvenile justice process. African Americans under age eighteen comprise 15 percent of their national age group, yet they currently represent 26 percent of all those who are arrested. After entering the criminal justice system, white and black juveniles with the same records are treated in radically different ways. According to the Justice Department's study, among white youth offenders, 66 percent are referred to juvenile courts, while only 31 per cent of the African-American youth are taken there. Blacks comprise 44 percent of those detained in juvenile jails, 46 percent of all those tried in adult criminal courts, as well as 58 percent of all juveniles who are warehoused in adult prison. In practical terms, this means that young African Americans who are arrested and charged with a crime, are more than six times more likely to be assigned to prison than white youth offenders.</p>
<p>For those young people who have never been to prison before, African Americans are nine times more likely than whites to be sentenced to juvenile prisons. For youths charged with drug offenses, blacks are forty-eight times more likely than whites to be sentenced to juvenile prison. White youths charged with violent offenses are incarcerated on average for 193 days after trial; by contrast, A American youths are held 254 days, and Latino youths are incarcerated 305 days.</p>
<p>The August 2000 report of the US Justice Department finds that 9.4 percent of black men ages twenty-five to twenty were in state and federal prisons in 1999, al most ten times the rate for white men in their late twenties. Among Hispanic males hi this same age group, over 3 percent were incarcerated.</p>
<p>What seems clear is that a new leviathan of racial inequality has been constructed across our country. It lacks the brutal simplicity of the old Jim Crow system, with its omnipresent "white" and "colored" signs. Yet it is in many respects potentially far more devastating, because it presents itself to the world as a system that is truly color blind. The black freedom struggle of the 1960s was successful largely because it convinced a majority of white middle class Americans that the Jim Crow system was economically inefficient, and that politically it could not be sustained or justified. The movement utilized the power of creative disruption, making it impossible for the old system of white prejudice and power to function in the same old ways it had for decades. For Americans who still believe in racial equality and social justice, we cannot stand silent while millions of our fellow citizens are being destroyed all around us. The racialized prison industrial complex is the great moral and political challenge of our time.</p>
<p>For several years, I have lectured in New York's famous Sing Sing prison, as part of a master's degree program sponsored by the New York Theological Seminary. During my last visit several months ago, I noticed that correctional officials had erected a large yellow sign over the door at the public entrance to the prison. The sign reads: <q direct="unspecified">"walking through these doors pass some of the finest corrections professionals in the world."</q> I asked Reverend Bill Webber, the director of the prisons educational program, and several prisoners what they thought about the sign. Bill answered bluntly, "demonic." One of the Master's students, a thirty-five-year-old Latino named Tony, agreed with Bill's assessment, but added, "let us face the demon head on." There are now over two million Americans who are incarcerated. It is time to face the demon head on. </p>
</div2>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
