<div1 id="v1-5.001" n="Southern Changes 1:5" type="Volume">
<head>Southern Changes. Volume 1, Number 5, 1979</head>
<p>
<title>Southern Changes</title>. Volume 1, Number 5, 1979</p>

<div2 id="v1-5lincoln.003" n="When Shall We Overcome?" type="Article">
<head>When Shall We Overcome?</head>
<docAuthor>By C. Eric Lincoln</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 1, No. 5, 1979, pp. 4-5</docDate>

<argument>C. Eric Lincoln is Professor of Religion at Duke University
in Durham, North Carolina.</argument>

<p>A man died. That was eleven years ago. </p>
<p>A man died who ought not to have died: not because he was a Black man, but because he was a good man;

<q><p>not because he had a dream, but because the dream he had was so critical for a people who had forgotten how to dream; for a nation whose dreams had lost their meaning;</p>

<p>not because he was a Christian, but because in being truly Christian his love for his fellow man transcended all religions and all diviions of men;</p>

<p>not because his death was a personal loss for those who knew him and loved him, but because his dying was a national tragedy for those who believe in the promise of America; and because his death was a temporary triumph for those who would deny that promise. For the promise of America is the American Dream, but for too many Americans it is a Dream that was never meant to be. There are those who would be Killers of the Dream, and for them the routine expression of the American Way of Life is the consignment of the poor and the undefended to the American Way of Death through poverty, disease, deception and discrimination.</p></q></p>

<p>Our greater tragedy is that the people we seem to kill most readily
are the people whose dreams we find most troubling: dreams that refuse
to articulate with the prevailing way of doing things here in
America. And so with the poor and the defenseless, we kill the Abraham
Lincolns, the John Kennedys, the Malcolm Xs, the Martin Luther Kings
and whomever else dares to dream against the grain of the waythings are. We kill the dreamers to get at the dream in the childish belief that dreams die with the man.</p>

<p>Not so. Dreams die hard, if ever they die at all.</p>

<p>For no matter the name of the dreamer, once a dream is spoken, it belongs to the people. It lives in the people, and it can only die if the people reject it, or if the people themselves are exterminated. So let it be known that whomever would kill a dream must be prepared to first kill all the people who believe in it; or else to so narcotize them with circuses, or dazzle them with counterfeits that they forget the dream and the dreamer, and succumb to illusion and deceit. The nations who have traveled that road have inevitably paid the price, for when the people lose their dreams, they lose their confidence. When they lose their confidence, they lose their self-respect. And when they lose their self-respect, their freedom can be taken away from them.</p>

<p>Today our cities are floundering in crisis and decay. Our jails are filled to overflowing. Our public schools have been turned into holding pens and battlegrounds; men and women who want to work, and who need to work to survive with dignity, walk the streets and haunt the taverns for want of jobs.</p>

<p>Those who challenge the way things are find themselves harassed and intimidated, or silenced with unjust incarceration. They are the political prisoners Andrew Young had the temerity to bring to the world's attention. Those of doubtful and sober minds turn to introspection; and those who believe in the righteousness of God wonder at the limits of His patience and tremble in the anticipation of His justice. Though we search and re-search the accumulated records of our national comportment, we find in them no compelling reasons for solace or satisfaction. It seems clear that somewhere America has gone wrong! It is not so much the empty pews where God and man used to meet that mark the people's disaffection and dereliction, as it is the empty faces, the empty hearts, the empty lives.</p>

<p>The divorce rate is astronomical; the suicide rate is unbelievable. The murder rate far exceeds that for any other "civilized" nation in the world. This is America. The showplace of democracy; the citadel of freedom. A nation under God. The place where dreams come true. What happened? What happened to America? What has happened to us, for we make America what it is?</p>

<p>Our tragedy is that the American Dream has been compromised by
false visions and spurious promises of those who would demean that
dream. Our hope, unsubstantiated by performance, is too often made the
hope of children, or the hope of fools - uninformed, Uninquiring, and
unassessed. The characteristic political art of our times is delusion
by confusion - the diffraction and scattering of half-truths and
un-truths to the end that reality is obscured under an avalanche of
words which do not mean anything, and are not intended to mean
anything. Their function is merely to confuse the real issues and thus
to silence opposition and paralyze response.</p>
<pb n="5"/>
<p>More than that, we have developed a frightening affinity for self-delusion, which is the art of putting an acceptable face on what is patently unacceptable through the manipulation of words and the meaning of words. We have become masters at persuading people to believe what they know isn't so through the employment of a kind of lingual cosmetology. When spending what you haven't got is dismissed as "a negative cash flow," and when shacking up is explained as "experimental living," or when the murder of innocent individuals becomes quasirespectable because it is defined as a "contract," or "extreme social alienation," we have gone a far piece down the road toward legitimizing the illegitimate, and blurring the lines by which civilizations have traditionally sought to order human existence and give it direction.</p>

<p>The ultimate objective of such casuistry is, of course, the avoidance of human responsibility. If up and down are indistinguishable, and if all corners are round, then morality has no meaning, and one act is as good as another, barring some temporary inconvenience. No one can be held accountable if the conditions of accountability are sufficiently confused, or if there is no way to determine the place where the good and the not-good, the true and the not-true, the beautiful and the ugly separate and depart from each other.</p>

<p>The immediate, practical benefit of a philosophy of moral indistinction is release from the necessity of making choices. If no ethical principles can be clearly identified, then the implications for restraint and circumspection in such traditional areas of high moral concern as religion, politics, sexual behavior, human and family relationships soon vanish, individual accountability becomes obsolete, and human relations are reduced to a state of nature in which life becomes increasingly nasty, mean, solitary, brutish and short.</p>

<p>In a swiftly paced society such as our own, there is increasingly less opportunity for reflection and introspection.</p>

<p>Decisions are ad hoc: choices involving the most serious consequences are made on the flip of a coin. Millions of Americans, who are otherwise rational and intelligent, have come near to giving up making choices altogether. They have accepted instead a pre-determined print-out of their behavior based on the doubtful projections of astrology, bypassing reason, science and experience in a childlike pursuit of fantasy and easy answers. Yet, our eagerness to consign to the stars the burden of rational choice is perhaps one more evidence of the increasing onerousness of human responsibility, the release from which we struggle so vainly to accomplish.</p>

<p>Our destiny is not in the stars. Neither is the truth we need to
make accountability reasonable and responsibility endurable. Nor is
responsibility the exclusive province of any particular race, or sex,
or age group, or political party, or church or denomination. It is of
critical importance now to realize that our destiny is where it always
was, that our national greatness can never transcend our national
behavior, and that our national responsibility begins with the earnest
concern for the welfare of all the people. What is the people's
welfare? It was spelled out for all time in the founding documents of
the commonwealth: It is life - which includes the means of earning a
decent living at a decent wage. It is liberty, which means freedom of
conscience and freedom from unjust restraint or incarceration. It is
the pursuit of happiness, which means the right of equal participation
in all of the common values of this society regardless of your race,
your sex, or your religion. Too many Americans are penalized, not
because they have done wrong, but because they have the wrong name, or
the wrong address, or the wrong color, or the wrong sex, or the wrong
attitude, or the vrong political opinion, or the wrong friends, or the wrong amount of money.</p>

<p> A man died eleven years ago.</p>

<p>A great man died with a dream that we would overcome the great
wrong that makes it so wrong to be poor, or to be Black or to be
without the privileges of status and power. It is time now to get on
with the resuscitation of a dream that never was, but could have been,
rather than to continue to live perpetually in the shadow of that
dream, or in our weakness and despair consign in to destruction. It is
time for the high principles which once distinguished our efforts and
encouraged our success to be brought out of hiding. It is time to
shake off the shackles of accommodation to chauvinism; time to lift a
torch of conviction; time to get on with the process of humanizing our
deteriorating social order. It is time to ask ourselves, "What
happened to the promise that was America?" It is time to give
substance to the Dream of the gentle Dreamer who eleven years ago
surrendered his life on the altar of America's racial
intransigence.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="v1-5lewis.004" n="Declining Donkeydom in Presleyland" type="Article">
<head>Declining Donkeydom in Presleyland</head>
<docAuthor>By Boyd Lewis</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 1, No. 5, 1979, pp. 6</docDate>
<argument>Boyd Lewis is an Atlanta free-lance writer.</argument>

<p>It was 100 years ago that cartoonist Thomas Nast decided to portray the Democratic Party as a flop-eared jackass and the Republican Party as an elephant of clearly low-wattage intelligence. Amazingly, neither party felt insulted by the nasty Mr. Nast and over the years the animal icons came to symbolize party identity and outlook.</p>

<p>Some years the impish little Demo donkey romps merrily around the ponderous GOP elephant and in others the elephant stomps the Bejesus out of the donkey in the manner of a wonderful underground cartoon called "Bambi Meets Godzilla".</p>

<p>Politics has meant Party and Party has meant Politics for as long
as anyone now alive can remember in this country. But in Memphis this
December, amid a Wagnerian weather scheme that featured tornado warnings, howling rainstorms and an ice incrustation, the mainstream part of the USA showed that it is now held together by spit and bailing wire. The donkey is fast going the way of the dinosaur.</p>

<p>The Democrats were lured to Memphis for its first mid-term conference under the impression that the city would be warmer than conventionseeking Denver and drier than Seattle, another contender. As it turned out, it was colder, wetter and more miserable than almost any place in the country for the entire run of the miniconvention.</p>

<p>And the Democratic National Committee thought Memphis would
represent a massed hymn to the policies of Jimmy Carter, a highly
publicized show of unity, joy and Prussian organization. But as with the weather, Memphis was a ferocious disappointment. The party's 2,700 delegates and alternates, the insiders in the 1976 campaign and footsoldiers for 1980, were split seven ways from Sunday on the most basic issues of party policy how well or poorly Carter has been doing, how the Democrats should deal with health care, defense, urban development and employment in the next election.</p>

<p>What was excruciatingly clear in Memphis was that the grand old coalitions which have kept the Democrats in power or close to it since the days of Franklin Roosevelt are no more. Gone is the linkage of organized labor, liberals, the cities, Blacks and the poor which interwove the special interests of each into bloc votes for the Democrats.</p>

<p>The George Meany/Alan Barkan/COPE/Teamsters variety of labor political operatives boycotted the Memphis gathering. Unions that did show up - NEA (National Education Association), AFSCME (Association of Federal, State, County and Municipal Employees), auto workers, machinists and the like - were all hotly opposed to the president's domestic spending slashes and they provided the core of disenchantment on the conference floor which put lump after lump in the smooth, controlled flow of resolutions from the delegates.</p>

<p>White liberals, the veterans, the antiwar movement supporters, the environmentalists, Clean Gene, HHH and McGovern supporters, either closed ranks with the party hierarchy or pecked away at the edges in flaccid coalitions like the Democratic Agenda.</p>

<p>New coalitions rose and the most stunning was the woman's caucus. The women and the women alone held together through the conference, got most of their resolutions passed and got ringing endorsements of the ERA from Jimmy on down the line. Indeed, the only thing Carter said at his keynote address which got the delegates to their feet was his reendorsement of ERA.</p>

<p>But beyond the internal events of the mini-convention, the Democrats and the Republicans are in big trouble. More voters failed to vote in the 1976 election (71 million) than there are registered Democrats, the party which runs most states, Congress and the White House. Few people vote straight party tickets any more. Single issue voting (tax relief, support of Israel, outlawing abortion, etc.) undercuts the entire rationale of a political party, which strives to provide a little of many things to the most people.</p>

<p>In Memphis, the donkeys of December met to show unity but revealed down-to-the-heart fractures; to support Carter but only by 2/3 of their votes; to discuss issues but only in a rigid format that choked off debate and angered the little democrats: to reinforce coalitions but saw them fall and new ones arise.</p>

<p>But most important of all, the Democratic Party failed to deal with a threat to its reason for being - the party of government helping, not government obsessed by the bottom line. President Carter's $l5-$l8 billion cuts from health, job, city, education and minority assistance programs while boosting the Pentagon's budget II percent for the next fiscal year is seen by party liberals as sheer neoNixonism, a Republican ploy if ever there was one.</p>

<p>Carter's junking of the party's basic philosophy was given little serious debate by the Memphis miniconvention. Those probing for cancer in the party's body politick need look no further than that.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="v1-5reese.002" n="National Advisory Committee for Women and
      the 'Friday Afternoon Massacre'" type="Article">
<head>National Advisory Committee for Women and the 'Friday Afternoon
Massacre'</head>
<docAuthor>By Lenora Reese</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 1, No. 5, 1979, pp. 18-20</docDate>
<argument>
Lenora Reese is on the staff at the Alabama Journal in Montgomery.
</argument>

<p>A month ago, a random poll of the American people would probably have indicated few, if any, had ever heard of the National Advisory Committee for Women.</p>

<p>The 40-member committee had not publicly trumpeted its existence since a presidential executive order signed it into being last April. Informal sessions had been held and issues batted back and forth. A staff was set up in Washington, D.C., and duties assigned.</p>

<p>But it wasn't until January 12, the day some are calling the "Friday afternoon massacre," that the once obscure group got the recognition it deserved. And it came at the expense of its outspoken co-chair, Bella Abzug, who was fired by President Carter after White House officials learned of a press release critical of Carter's economic and social policies.</p>

<p>Enraged over the dismissal, more than half the committee resigned. As this issue went to press, the count stood at 24 resigned, 16 remaining.</p>

<p>Of the eight members from the Southern states, the majority, six, including honorary chairperson Judy Carter, chose to stay on the panel, while two left. Of the three Southern Black members, two remained, and one left. Of the two men on the committee, one stayed and other resigned. (A third original male member, Lane Kirkland of the AFL-CIO, had resigned earlier over an unrelated matter.)</p>

<p>There was apparently no evident cohesiveness among the "Southern coalition" on the committee, and after the split, there seemed to be even less consensus of opinion on the reasons for the firing, the committee's original purpose and its uncertain future.</p>

<p>Still smarting over Abzug's dismissal in late January was Brownie Ledbetter, founding member of the Arkansas Women's Political Caucus and state legislative chairman, a member of the Executive Committee of the Southern Regional Council, Business and Professional Women's Clubs and Church Women United. She and Jefflyn Johnson, of Falls Church, Va., were the only two Southerners to step down.</p>

<p>Ledbetter, like many other feminists, believes Carter used Abzug merely as a scapegoat for the rest of the committee which he felt had gone beyond the call of duty in criticizing his position on the economy, including proposed cuts for the federal budget. Issues such as social security cutbacks and postponement of national health insurance were of vital concern to women, committee members felt, and needed to be brought to the president's attention.</p>

<p>According to the committee's guidelines, set up after the 1977 Houston International Women's Year conference, the panel was to gather and disseminate information concerning women's issues and advise the president on how the government would implement the National Plan of Action adopted in Houston.</p>

<p>The press release, which summarized a lengthy report compiled by the committee and its staff for Carter, warned the president that his "anti-inflation program will impose additional burdens upon women in increased unemployment, cutbacks in social programs, postponement of comprehensive national health insurance and deferred action on programs and addressing poverty and assistance to cities where the majority of women live."</p>

<p>The release also criticized an administration proposal to increase the Defense budget by 10 percent and called on Carter to appoint a committee to investigate "military extravagance."</p>

<p>Press reports have indicated that White House staffers, upon learning the release's contents, abruptly decided Abzug should be canned. Staffers were said to be already miffed that the committee had cancelled its December meeting with Carter. According to members, a majority of the committee voted to cancel the session, although Abzug opposed such a move, because they felt the 15 minutes allotted was clearly not enough time for a meaningful dialogue.</p>

<p>Ledbetter, however, believes neither the press release nor the cancelled meeting were the real reasons for the dismissal. Rather, they were an excuse for the Carter administration to dispose of someone who wouldn't toe the party line. The firing, she said, was indicative of the administration's view of women.</p>

<p>"We were never taken seriously to begin with," she said. "We were just shunted aside."</p>

<p>The committee had been given a $300,000 budget and a staff to work with, but Ledbetter said Abzug and co-chair Carmen Delgado Votaw "did all the work." Little cooperation was received from White House staffers, she said, and "it has been a constant hassle."</p>

<p>"I think it's essentially the president's fault. I don't think he's without compassion for women, but it's compassion for us as wives and mothers. He didn't treat us as equals. He wouldn't have treated a committee of men that way."</p>

<p>Carter, meanwhile, defended his firing of Abzug at a press
conference five days after the episode. The group's criticism of him was "not part of it at all," he said. His ap-<pb n="19"/>pointment of Abzug just "didn't work out well. The committee has never been well organized; their functions have never been clearly expressed to me. There's not been good cooperation between the committee and the Cabinet members or my advisors, or me."</p>

<p>Carter said he understood the group's function was "to work with me, hopefully in harmony, to achieve mutual goals - goals of enhanced opportunities for women, for the elimination of any discrimination against women, to assure that every decision made by the government, and the executive branch or Congress, has at least one factor to be considered: how we can best meet the needs of women and to overcome the suffering that they have experienced because of past legal and other discriminatory actions."</p>

<p>Carter, feminists say, obviously would have preferred the panel stick to strict "women's" issues such as abortion rights or the passage of the Equal Rights Amendment. "But we did something really far out," said Ledbetter, with a trace of sarcasm. "We were talking about fiscal policy."</p>

<p>Ledbetter said those who resigned did not see themselves as taking a critical direction, as Carter had implied in his meeting with the committee before Abzug was given her pink slip.</p>

<p>"We saw it as our right to tell our various constituencies what the administration was doing in areas that affect women," she said. "I don't feel Bella lead us down a leftist, liberal path."</p>

<p>Ledbetter was backed in her resignation by the Southern Coalition for Educational Equity, a group of Southern feminists formed recently to focus on issues of sexism and racism in secondary and elementary education.</p>

<p>While she believes Abzug's firing and the resulting resignations were unfortunate, Ledbetter says publicity generated by the entire episode may have actually helped the cause.</p>

<p>"It was unfair to Bella, but in a sense it was good because somebody heard us say, 'the economy is a women's issue.' That's clearly what we wanted to do in the first place."</p>

<p>What happens now, however, will probably be up to the remaining members and whomever Carter appoints to replace those who do not return. Whatever the outcome, Ledbetter and other feminists believe Carter has been hurt by the incident and will feel the repercussions come 1980. "He misjudged us," she said. "And her strength."</p>

<p>Among the stalwarts who stayed are six Southerners, including Memphis attorney Richard Rossie, the only remaining man; Owanah Anderson of Texas, member of the Health, Education and Welfare Committee on Rights and Responsibility of Women; Dr. Elizabeth Koontz, assistant state superintendent of education for North Carolina; Judy Carter, the president's daughter-in-law; Brenda Parker, national president, Future Homemakers of America, another Texan; and Ann Richards, Travis County, Texas commissioner, and president of the Texas Association of Elected Women.</p>

<p>Rossie, founding member of the Women's Resources Center of Memphis,
blames Abzug and co-chair Votaw for the "totally negative" press release and the "foul-up," and feels it was not the committee's function to question the president's economic policy.<pb n="20"/></p>


<p>"The president's policy has been that excessive government spending leads to inflation, and we were implicitly rejecting that statement," Rossie said.</p>

<p>And while Abzug was not personally involved in the preparation of the press release, Rossie says the staff who did prepare it "were her people. She chose them. I'm going to hold her responsible."</p>

<p>The first version of the committee report, he charged, "clearly reflected her thinking and style," which he termed "confrontational," and he felt the committee staff had "gone wild" with it. Even after it had been redone to soften some of the more critical points, Rossie said "it reads Bella all over."</p>

<p>Rossie, the only Southern member contacted to applaud Abzug's firing, accused the former co-chair of "lecturing" Carter on the committee's role during the group's session with him. "Bella had the opportunity to say the press release was done without her approval and say thanks," Rossie said, "but she didn't." Instead, she lectured the president on the role of the committee and how the committee viewed its role."</p>

<p>Carter reportedly informed panel members of a few things he'd had on his mind about their function, namely that they weren't being supportive enough of him.</p>

<p>Although feminists have said Carter's firing of Abzug was a politically naive move, Rossie says Abzug's treatment of the president made it the other way around. "I was horrified."</p>

<p>Rossie, chairman of the Shelby County, Tenn., Democratic Committee, remains on the committee but is ambiguous about its future. Taking a more optimistic outlook were Koontz and Richards.</p>

<p>Koontz, former president of the National Education Association and director of the Women's Bureau for the U.S.</p>

<p>Department of Labor, said she agreed to be on the committee because she believed in its purpose: 'To further the goals of the Houston women's agenda and have an impact at national, state and local levels. That has not been achieved," she said.</p>

<p>"The war has not been won. I don't want to give up. I hope we can be a stronger force for what has happened. There must be someone there to negotiate."</p>

<p>Koontz said she had been contacted by another committee member who had resigned and asked why she had not done so as well. "I wouldn't regard it as pressure," she said, "but I basically operate on the premise that we set out to do a job ... and I think it's still possible to do that job."</p>

<p>The chairman of the National Committee on Working Women, Koontz predicted some members may come back if they could do so "without turning their backs on Bella." If they do not, however, Carter will more than likely have to appoint replacements from the same organizations whose representatives resigned.</p>

<p>For Ann Richards, whose political commitments in Texas keep her
busy year-round, resigning from the committee would have meant turning
her back on a decision she made last year to join the group in spite of other commitments.</p>

<p>Though she said she would not pass judgment on those who resigned in protest, Richards said, "Women need to progress to the point where we're stateswomen, not merely reacting to changes because we don't agree."</p>

<p>"From my own conversations with Sarah Weddington (Carter's special
assistant for women's affairs), my impression is that the White House
wants it to continue. There was never any concrete definition of what
we were going or where we were going. I hope out of this will come a
better understanding of the whole thing. Time will tell."</p>
</div2>
