<div1 id="v1-6.001" n="Southern Changes 1:6" type="Volume">
<head>Southern Changes. Volume 1, Number 6, 1979</head>
<p>
<title>Southern Changes</title>. Volume 1, Number 6, 1979</p>

<div2 id="v1-6staff.003" n="Tribute to Gwendolyn Cherry" type="Article">
<head>Tribute to Gwendolyn Cherry</head>
<docAuthor>By Staff</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 1, No. 6, 1979, pp.2-3</docDate>


<p> On February 7, Gwen Cherry, the Vice-President of the Southern
Regional Council, died in an automobile accident in Tallahassee,
Florida.Her deal leaves the Council without one of its valued
officers and a dear close friend.</p>

<p>As a state leader in Florida, Gwen Cherry set new standards and
precidents for the discussion of issues in government relating to
Blacks, other minorities, women and poor of her state. As a national
leader, Gwen inspired many withher singular devotion and joyful
energy. She raised issues, took positions, and conducted the business
of justice without fear of personall loss or concern for monetary
reward.</p>

<p>As an officer and member of the Council, Gwen led the organization
from a time of increasing despair and disbelief to a beginning period
of hard work, faith in human nature
<pb n="3"/>
and potential, and no-nonsense judgment tempered by humor and
tolerance.</p>

<p>While often overworked, underreqarded and too often unseen, Gwen
Cherry was an example of accomplishment and belief in principled
equality which many Blacks and women immediatly emulated and
admired. Yet for everyone of any race or sex -- Black or White, male
or female-- she represented the virtue of patience untouched by hate,
the belief in freedom unbridled by cinicism, and a very unique insight
into the tragic-humor of people who resist the call for action.</p>

<p>As a lawyer, Gwen Cherry represented the interest of clients and
causes in court. Still, she spent as much time developing the
potential of cooperation as exercising the art of an advisary.</p>

<p>As the first Black woman in the Florida Legislature, she was the
spokeswoman at home and elsewhere for feminism and equal
rights. Yet,she was much more to many more. Gwen CHerry stood alone to
say "nay" when the lynching mob of the Florida Legislature pushed
through the death penalty. She stood alone in saying "nay" when boards
and compmissions were filled without Blacks and women. She stood alone
and said "nay" when the state rushed helter skelter to push Black and
poor students out of the schools in the name of competency. Gwen
Cherry stood alone when she proposed numerous pieces of legislation to
aid the afflicted, the aged, the poor, and the uninfluential.</p>

<p> Like most of us, Gwen Cherry lost too many of the battles which
she fought as a state leader, an officer of the Council, a lawyer, and
a national figure. Her victories were too few. So long as she took
breath, however, she continued her struggle believing that people of
good will would someday, somehow act.</p>

<p>The most fitting and lovely tribute that we as her friends and
companions can pay to Gwen Cherry will be to endure beyond the
conditions against which she fought and to take her life and
friendship as a special gift which enables us tobe more wise, loving,
and devoted to the just and humane world of which she gave us a clear
vision.
</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="v1-6sun.004" n="A RETURN TO THE SUN" type="Article">
<head>A RETURN TO THE SUN</head>
<docAuthor>BY SUN & REP</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 1, No. 6, 1979, pp.4,12</docDate>
<argument>SUN/REP is a new, non-profit, public interest organization
committed to the advocacy and commercialization of appropriate
technology in the Southeast United States. Direct your inquiries to:
SUN/REP, Suite 412, 3110 Maple Dr., Atlanta, Georgia 30305. Phone:
(404) 261-1764.</argument>

<p>Five thousand years ago men worshipped the sun. After a 50 century hiatus, man is turning his attention and hope - toward that same sun. Today, we are caught in the middle of the most sophisticated technological web ever spun on this earth. The spider is energy - fossil fuels like coal, oil and natural gas, and nuclear power. There is one possible avenue of escape - the sun, and its energy in the form of wind power, water power, biomass, geothermal energy and others.</p>

<p>The energy dialogue poses three critical questions about our resources: (1) Are they limitless? (2) Are they safe? and (3) Who controls them? With regard to the first question, there is no infinite amount of any extractible natural resource: none are renewable. There is only so much oil, for example, and even though new reserves are periodically discovered, the cost of bringing oil to the surface is substantial and increasing daily. Also, the demand for energy is likewise increasing at an alarming rate.</p>

<p>The second point, safety, produces damning evidence against all fuels, especially nuclear power. Burning fossil fuels produces a staggering amount of air and water pollution; and nuclear fuels are hazardous to extract, transport, use, store and dispose of. Finally, because the raw material of fossil fuels is site specific, requiring elaborate extraction, transport, refining and distribution equipment and systems, no individual acting alone or collectively has the ability to control the fuel he uses for heat and cooling. The capital investment needed in bringing such fuels to homes, businesses and industries has been great, encouraging large and powerful corporations to dominate and control our energy.</p>

<p>Solar energy and its offspring, on the other hand, are limitless,
ubiquitous and can be captured by anyone at a fraction of the cost of conventional energy. We simply must learn how to do it.</p>

<p>The price of coal and oil has been kept at artificially low levels for many years, encouraging overdependence on energy resources which are environmentally hazardous and in some instances, dangerously depleted. Experts, however, now believe the sun can power 32 percent of America by the year 2000, if the government and private sector will direct their considerable expertise to the research and development of solar energy.</p>

<p>There is some basis for hope. From a budget of $1 million in 1970, Washington's current solar technologies budget for fiscal year 1979 has exceeded $500 million, and along with hundreds of small manufacturers, the giants of American industry General Motors, RCA, General Electric, Grumman, to name a few are beginning to invest seriously in solar development.</p>

<p>Perhaps because of the energy crisis, a new philosophy has emerged about man's relationship to technology and his environment. Recent events have shown that despite our presumed mastery of technology, technology is actually controlling us. We are learning that we cannot create our own environment and mutilate the one which nature has created and shaped over millions of years. We have learned that in an attempt to control and simplify our lives, we have instead complicated them and placed them in the hands of powerful and centralized interests far removed from the expression of public needs and desires. The movement for appropriate or small-scale technology is designed to enable all human beings to regain control over their lives. It is a recognition that we must understand. We must accept our limitations, as well as respect the world in which live.</p>

<p>Appropriate technology (AT) includes the various solar technologies, holistic and preventive health measures, solid waste recycling, acupuncture, natural foods production, organic gardening and cooperative arrangements of all types. In other words, AT encourages people to control the tools they need to enable them to live in harmony with their environment. AT recognizes that ecological balance must be maintained if disasters, crises, shortages, suffering and poverty are to be minimized; that greed must yield to need in maintaining the progress that we have attained in many fields.</p>

<p>Adopting the concept of AT might lead to some of the following: a group of Alabama tenant farmers receiving technical and volunteer assistance to grow and eat their own fish and use the inedible portions for fertilizing crops in an alternating cycle; a rural community in South Carolina building and heating their passive solar-heated homes for practically nothing, after a modest initial investment; a Nashville resource recovery waste system where thousands of tons of glass, paper and metals are collected, separated, sold and recycled, with proceeds to participating communities in a system where people can learn management skills.</p>

<p>Or it might lead to community gardens in Charlotte, North Carolina
operated and maintained by groups of residents who supply, plant,
harvest and eat organically grown vegetables at a fraction of their
retail cost; Southern Georgia rural communities powered by
wood-burning stoves, supplied with forest wastes for heating, cooking
and washing; a community health clinic in Jackson, Mississippi, where
doctors and trained volunteers teach and practice preventive medicine
to residents
<pb n="12"/>
and are supported by the Jackson community; farmers in the citrus belt of Florida taking their products by truck to St. Augustine, setting up market stalls and selling directly to consumers, eliminating middlemen and 66 cents on the dollar they lose when processors, transporters, packagers and retailers take their cuts.</p>

<p>These are some of the ways AT can - and is already beginning to
operate in the Southeast United States. The potential is here. The
Southeast receives more sunlight than most sections of the U.S.; there
are few organized co-ops, many isolated farmers and rural
communities. The Southeast is politically, economically and socially poor, but more and more voices are being heard; complaining, questioning and demanding action. People want power to control their own lives and their environment. They want to return, not to a harder, poorer life, but to one that is safe, healthy and satisfying. People want to see, feel, hear and smell nature, not destroy it. They want a community which reflects and blends with nature, not one that overpowers it.</p>

<p>AT can help lead us to that time and place, but it cannot happen
without changes in many of our assumptions and values. And AT has
something for everyone - the rich, the poor, the powerful, the needy,
White, Black, urban dweller, rural farmer, businessman, tradesman -
all of us. It is the belief that each of us is a human being with the
right and power to control the basic needs of our own lives, free from
outside manipulation, and with the dignity that only comes with
economic well-being and the pride of self-sufficiency.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="v1-6sun.004" n="Black Farmers: A Vanishing Breed" type="Article">
<head>Black Farmers: A Vanishing Breed</head>
<docAuthor>by Robert M. Press</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 1, No. 6, 1979, pp.5-7</docDate>

<argument><p>Robert Press is a staff correspondent of <hi rend="italic">The Christian Science Monitor</hi>.</p>

<p>Reprinted by permission from <hi rend="italic">The Christian
Science Monitor</hi>. c 1978: The Christian Science Publishing
Society. All rights reserved.</p>
</argument>

<p><hi rend="bold">Bolivar County, Mississippi</hi>-Mary Coleman
hunches over, shucking corn on the wooden porch of the small crossroads grocery store she runs here. Weedcroppers from the cotton fields will stop in around noon to buy cold bottles of sodapop, crackers, and Vienna sausage.</p>

<p>Houston Coleman, her son, has come by to talk to this reporter about the problems he and other Black farmers are having. He is a big man, dressed in gray slacks, a longsleeved shirt, and mudspattered black street shoes. He wears a straw cowboy hat and talks in a booming voice.</p>

<p>"At one time we had too much rain; next it was dry," he says, recalling the past several years.</p>

<p>"That puts you in the hole. You keep borrowing and borrowing. Then you have a bad crop and next year you have to go back and borrow again."</p>

<p>In 1976 the Coleman family could not get a bank loan or a federal farm loan, even though they had been consistently paying off their old debts. They were told their "payback ability" was not good enough, says Mary Coleman. "But it was all because we were Black," she contends.</p>

<p>Just when things began to look desperate, the Atlantabased Emergency Land Fund (ELF) loaned them $12,000 which the Colemans have since paid back.</p>

<p>The aim of ELF is to help Blacks keep their farmland a challenge that is becoming increasingly urgent.</p>

<p>During bad times, a lot of Black farmers in the area have quit or rented out, says Coleman, who now owns about 300 acres, which he farms in cotton and soybeans.</p>

<p>He swings into his pickup and we drive down a gravel road, then turn onto a dirt track bordering his cotton field.</p>

<p>Several adults and a few children - including his nephew - are hoeing weeds among the long lines of green cotton plants. Coleman lifts a big jug of ice water from the pickup and sets it down for the workers - all of them Black.</p>

<p>It is in the upper 90s. No clouds.</p>

<p>Houston Coleman picks up a hoe and starts chopping at some weeds
among the cotton. "A lot of Black folks have sold their land," he
says. "Now they're up North and they want to come home and they ain't got no home to come to."</p>

<p>Black farmers are a vanishing breed in the U.S.</p>

<p>A new federal analysis shows the number of Black farm operators declining by 90 percent since 1950, compared to a 54 percent drop among White farmers.</p>

<p>In the same period, the amount of Black-owned farmland has fallen by some 70 percent to less than onehalf of 1 percent of total U.S. farmland. The amount of agricultural land owned by Whites has increased slightly since 1950, according to the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) analysis based on 1974 Census Bureau figures.</p>

<p>The number of Black farm operators, according to the analysis, dropped from about 550,000 in 1950 to 53,000 in 1974. The number of tenant farmers also has been falling.</p>

<p>In 1950, Blacks owned some 12.5 million acres of farmland, almost
all of it in the South, compared to 3.8 million in 1974. Whites, in
the same period, increased their
<pb n="6"/>
farm holdings from 825 million to 887 million.</p>

<p>The federal figures reveal an even greater loss of Blackowned farmland than ELF has been citing.</p>

<p>ELF steps in when other loan sources, such as banks or the federal government, refuse to take the risk of lending to Black farmers. It also offers legal aid to help Black families keep ownership of land.</p>

<p>In Mississippi, the state with the most Black farmers, Blacks got FmHA operating loans (for seeds, fertilizer, and equipment) of $2,746,000, while Whites got $21,029,000, in fiscal year 1975, according to USDA figures cited by ELF.</p>

<p>The total FmHA loans for the same period for purchase of land and for development were: Whites $9,852,000; Blacks $662,000.</p>

<p>Department of Commerce statistics for 1974 show that in Mississippi there were 32,061 White-owned farms and 6,387 Black-owned farms.</p>

<p>Edward Pennick, ELF director, says the Carter administration's "rhetoric" on helping Black farmers has been good, but tangible action is missing. He wants more Black lending agents in the FmHA, but the FmHA's Pickinpaugh says there are few positions available.</p>

<p>And the problem is not limited to loans.</p>

<p>Some Black farmers in South Carolina suspected prejudice when graders at a White-run packing shed kept giving them less than the top grade (and hence less money) for their tomatoes. When they formed their own packing cooperative, other certified graders gave their tomatoes top rating, says Edgar Jordan, of the Southern Cooperative Development Fund in Lafayette, Louisana.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Poor farm management.</hi> Many Blacks fail to look
at farming as a business, says Jordan. They have "poor record keeping, poor farm management," he says.</p>

<p>Many of the South's Black farmers have not learned new technology," he adds. This is also true of poor White farmers in the regions, he says.</p>

<p>One thing that would help, he suggests, is formation of more cooperatives for sharing equipment and marketing.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Sale of land by inheritors.</hi> Farmland in most
Southern states is inherited under a legal arrangement that gives each heir an interest in the entire farm rather than a piece of land for himself. But any one heir can sell his interest or petition a court to order sale of the land so that proceeds may be divided up equally among heirs. It is one way to turn an asset into cash.</p>

<p>The problem arises when not all the heirs agree to the sale - or are even aware of it. This situation occurs most commonly among Blacks.</p>

<p>Often heirs have the false impression nothing can be done to their land unless all the heirs agree. But that is not the case, says ELF director Pennick.</p>

<p>Attorneys' fees in Alabama for handling such sales can be as much as 10 percent of the value of the sale.</p>

<p>Inheritances often are further complicated by lack of a detailed will, says Joe Adams, of the ELF branch in Mississippi.</p>

<p>A case now before the Alabama Supreme Court challenges the constitutionality of such proceedings. In that case, one of more than 75 heirs to the English family farm of some 300 acres, much of it in timber, asked the court to sell the land and divide the proceeds. The other heirs objected to the sale. (A White attorney bought the interest of the selling heir before the sale but asked that the sale proceed.)</p>

<p>Behind the Black exodus from the farm lie the voluntary decisions of many rural Black families to search for a better life in the city. But it is argued that many Black farmers would have stayed on their land if they had been able to improve their income.</p>

<p>Median income among White farmers (in constant 1975 dollars) increased from $9,730 in 1970 to $11,237 in 1975, but Black median farm income rose only from $4,278 to $4,857, according to USDA figures.</p>

<p>Blacks, much more than Whites, tend to have smaller farms and fewer outside sources of income. They are more vulnerable during periods of sharp increase in farm operating expenses and during periods of bad crops.</p>

<p>"The problem is the bad years," explains James Carmicle, a Black Mississippi delta farmer. "Just when you've met the high production costs," he continues, prices for crops drop "and you can't make it."</p>

<p>Carmicle owns 53 acres and rents another 70. One 40acre plot he works carries three deeds his own and those of his two sisters. "I work hard all year, then at the end of the year I can't meet obligations," he laments.</p>

<p>ELF and others point to these problems contributing to the Black departure from the farm:</p>

<p>1. Prejudice in making loans to Black farmers.</p>
<p>2. Poor management of Black farms.</p>
<p>3. Sale of Black farmland by one of the heirs without consent, or sometimes even knowledge, of the other heirs.</p>
<p>4. Sale of Black-owned farmland for unpaid taxes.</p>

<p>What is needed, they say, are fairer lending practices, including appointment of more Black lending supervisors in the Farmers Home Administration (FmHA), more technical aid to Black farmers, and a change in state laws to make sales of farmland fairer to all involved.</p>

<p>Some help for small farmers is pending.</p>

<p>Congress is in the final stages of approving a bill to allow the FmHA to make loans to small farmers at 5 percent instead of the current interest rate of about 8 percent.</p>

<p>And the USDA is sponsoring several conferences over the next few
months at which top department officials will meet small farmers and
become better acquainted with 
<pb n="7"/>
their needs.</p>

<p>But on the main problems outlined by ELF, progress is slow:</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Prejudice.</hi> Although its contention is difficult to prove, ELF asserts that Black farmers with small landholdings have a harder time getting loans than White farmers of similar circumstances.</p>

<p>"In some cases we've found this to be true," says Lynn Pickinpaugh, new director of the FmHA's production loan division. Complaints are investigated, but no largescale discrimination against Blacks has been found, he asserts.</p>

<p>"Many times they say it is discrimination and it is other reasons," says Pickinpaugh.</p>

<p>Speaking of what he has seen in the Mississippi delta, cotton farmer Houston Coleman says: "Most of the White folks are in the office - and they know what's going on. Even if you qualify, a White man can run in there and grap a stipulation and twist it the way he wants to."</p>

<p>Sale has been blocked until the appeal is heard.</p>

<p>Attorney Michael Figures, of Mobile, Alabama, representing the other heirs, contends such sales should not be allowed until any heir who wants to retain the land has been given first chance to do so. The same person should be given the right to buy out the others, he adds.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Tax sales.</hi> If a Black family living in Chicago, for example, inherits farmland in the South, the Southern county tax office might have lost track of them. An heir still living on the land may falsely assume he does not have to pay the entire bill until he is notified of long overdue taxes and forced to sell.</p>

<p>Notice for tax sales in some states is made only in the local newspapers, so distant heirs may never hear of the sale.</p>

<p>Once sold, owners often "redeem" the land. This means they can repurchase the land during a redemption period under conditions that vary from state to state. In Mississippi, for instance, the conditions include paying back the taxes, the cost of the sale, and interest on the unpaid taxes.</p>

<p>The redemption process is not always easy and takes time and added expense. One improvement, says Figures, would be to assure that any inheritor living on the land be given immediate right to repurchase it by himself, to the exclusion of the other heirs.</p>

<p>ELF has been operating a tax watch to alert heirs of pending sales. In Mississippi, says Adams, fewer Blacks are losing their farmland today as a result of tax-sales.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="v1-6suitts.005" n="Solar Greenhouses: The Greening of the South" type="Interview">
<head>Solar Greenhouses: The Greening of the South</head>
<docAuthor>by Steve Suitts and Bill Dow</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 1, No. 6, 1979, pp.8-10</docDate>

<p><hi rend="bold">Publisher's Note:</hi><hi rend="italic"> I was in no mood to he convinced when Bill Dow began to explain his idea last year. As he sat with his legs draped around one of my office chairs, I wondered what kind of bedside manner I was about to experience from this physician who prefers T-shirts and tennis shoes as work garments.</hi></p>

<hi rend="italic"><p>There was a twinkle in his eyes, shielded only in
part by the horned-rimmed glasses which kept poking back towards his forehead. Apparently, as a part of his ceremony, he scratched his head and asked, as if both of us might figure out the answer, "What could cut your heating bill 25-45 percent, produce some vegetables and fruit year-round, and only cost about $400?"</p>

<p>"I thought we were going to talk about issues of health care or
jobs..."  Bill didn't wait for the completion of the sentence. Just as well. He asked another question more direct: "Why not attach a greenhouse to your home, grow some vegetables in it, and use the warm air to heat your house in the winter?"</p>

<p>A greenhouse onto my house. Fine, Bill, but what does this have to do with heating bills and food? "It's all the same thing," he said, with an arch in his voice and a shift in his chair. I knew then that he was going to enjoy this conversation:</p></hi>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> Okay, let's see if you're serious. Give me the basics.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> While everybody else is talking about elaborate technology and fancy solar energy equipment, there's something simple that a lot of folks can do that involves greenhouses. You know even in the winter a greenhouse overheats in the daytime and is generally ventilated to keep the temperature down in the low 80s. With a solar greenhouse, instead of ventilating the hot air to the outside, just allow the air into the house when it's needed.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> That's why you said solar greenhouse.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> Yes. Not only would it act as a solar
collector for heating the house during the day, but it also would
contain heat storage devices so that the excess heat can in part he stored and then released at night. Then you have a heat source that can be used to maintain temperature.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> I think it's going to be complicated.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> Not at all. Let's take it in steps. First, a greenhouse is to be attached to the south side of the dwelling. Obviously, you place the greenhouse at that location so that it can receive the full benefit of the sun from the east in the morning, from the south at midday, and the west in the evening. At the same time, the dwelling serves as an insulation and a barrier to the north which would be the side through which ordinarily the heat would escape during the winter days.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> Simple enough.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> Yes, and there's more. The second reason you place it on the south side is because the sun is lower on the southern horizon in the winter than in the summer. The fact is that much more heat passes through a surface when it strikes the surface on the perpendicular. Thus, in the winter, the greenhouse would give maximum heating potential because on the south side it would be perpendicular to the sun's rays. Even at the coldest points in winter, the attached greenhouse on the south side could generate 900 heat with the winter sun.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> Okay. There's heat in the greenhouse. Won't it escape?</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> The storage of the heat can be
accomplished in several ways. The two major types of storage are in
the floor and in water. The floor of the greenhouse can be, for
example, concrete slabs or gravel, each of which can heat up during
the day either from direct sunlight or contact with the air. Then
after sundown, the floor will gradually give up its heat to the
greenhouse helping maintain the temperature. The storage of heat can
also take place by placing water in various containers in the
greenhouse. This is often done in 55-gallon milk containers. In either
case, the principle is the same, the water heats up during the day and
gives off heat at night. Thereby, you can store heat to
<pb n="9"/>
warm the temperature in the night.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> Still, don't you have to do anything else to prevent the heat from escaping?</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> Well, all the walls not covered with transparent material should be heavily insulated. The transparent "skin" or covering should be a double layer. The two layers, with air between, provide some insulation. The outside layer is usually a fiberglass acrylic material and the inside covering a polyethelene sheet. There are different types of covering on the market and the materials can vary.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> Tell me, what do we do with the hot air that we've got in the greenhouse? Carry me one step further.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> Rather than venting the hot air which you have stored in the greenhouse to the outside, on the cold days of fall, winter, or spring, the warm air can be allowed to move into the adjacent house or building. Hot air moves to cold, you know, and by opening a window or a door from the greenhouse into the house, the warm air from the greenhouse will naturally move into the house. With an opening such as a door, the cold air off the floor will move into the greenhouse as the warmer air higher up in the greenhouse moves to the upper part of the door and into your house. If the opening is only a window, then the air can enter the greenhouse from a duct off the house floor to the greenhouse or from crawling space under the house and upon heating enter through the window.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> That sounds more like a doctor's explanation of the respiratory tract. Are you sure about that?</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> A friend of mine in Durham, N.C., John Hatch, has a 8 X 16 greenhouse attached to his first floor with a sliding glass door. The living quarters are on the second floor. Throughout the winter, Hatch is able to turn off his heat at 9:00 a.m. and turn it on again a half-hour after sundown. Some people have used a fan to help move the warm air into the house. Same is true for heating the greenhouse at night. Some people use the passive heat of the storage facilities and others actively heat their greenhouses at night. An 8 X 16 solar greenhouse in Pittsboro, N.C., with seven 55-gallon drums of water storage, never got below 530 during this past winter. And that was without any additional heating and some very cold weather.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> What if the sun doesn't shine for three or four days or a week?</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> If one is growing vegetables or plants sensitive to the cold and cannot be moved into the house, then there will be a need for a back-up heating system. This in all likelihood will simply mean leaving the opening to the house open so that heat from the house will hold the temperature up. The alternative which many people use is to simply put a heating unit in the greenhouse usually an electric heater or a wood stove. Another alternative some are using is to compost in an area adjacent to the greenhouse and utilize the heat given off by the compost.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> What about summer?</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> Indeed, the greenhouses do get hot in the
summertime. However, adequate venting of the inside temperature will
make it approximate the outside temperature. If this develops into a
significant problem, a turbine vent can be put on the roof of the
greenhouse. The turbine vents move a great deal of air and should hold
the inside temperature about equal to the outside temperature.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> Bill, I gather this is where the business of growing the vegetables comes in.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> Right. The food producing potential really is limited only by space and the grower. Many vegetables, such as tomatoes, broccoli, lettuce, turnips, spinach, onions, and others can be grown. Fruits, too. The greenhouse may serve to prolong the fall and help the spring start earlier. This also means that one can start seedlings which can be transplanted to an outside garden later. Houseplants, obviously, can also be grown in the greenhouse.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> Oh yes, and then there's fish.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> If you are going to tell me some story about how to multiply fish and loaves, I'm ready to declare it a miracle.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> Seriously, there are several places in the country where people are experimenting with using water for storing heat and growing fish. And these are edible fish, not the aquarium sort.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> It sounds impressive, exciting; however, I go back to the beginning. Am I going to give up an arm and a leg to get a greenhouse built? For myself, I've never built a greenhouse and really wouldn't know where to begin.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> Actually, it's very simple and if you just know the basics about carpentry and do a little reasoning and reading, the task is hardly insurmountable. There are several good reference books I'd suggest you might want to look at - studying some details in each of them. (References listed at the end). In total, the parts and materials will be around $400-$500.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> It's such a simple idea and really very exciting. I suppose it has a great deal of potential.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> These greenhouses can be very important to folks with a little money and a lot of time. Where the government is spending millions of dollars to help poor and lowincome families cut down on their heating costs, perhaps they ought to think about this idea as a means for "weatherization."</p>

<p>I don't want to take us too far. But, there is a possibility of some jobs being generated here. This kind of building can be done by the hard-core, unemployed young whose skills are not yet developed. In rural areas in the South, young folks could build greenhouses in jobs programs for the elderly and the disabled and get some valuable skills which could be used in later life. Actually, the ideal people for this task would be the small and subsistence farmers who need supplemental income. This type work would allow the time needed for agricultural pursuits. The actual building can be done in three to four days.</p>

<p>Farmers have the basic construction and horticultural skill
already. With some basic theory and design, background and information
they should be able to get into this developing trade. Perhaps, with
time this could be expanded to include other forms of solars and
appropriate technology installation and maintenance. At the very
least, the added income could help maintain these farmers on their
farms rather than have them join so many already severed from their
land.</p>
<pb n="10"/>
<p>There are still some questions to be answered before the scale of this kind of project gets massive. True, the technology is simple and the undertaking is relatively inexpensive as a means of partially heating a house and producing food. Still, we don't know precisely how much heat savings or food can be generated. We don't know exactly what the cost efficiency comes to be. There's a need for more data and more experience. I don't mean that the question at this point is will it work. Rather, the question is how well will it work given certain conditions, such as the type of weather or the floor space to be heated in the house. Also, how well does it work in urban areas compared to rural; in the South, West, or even the North.</p>

<p>When you think about it, however, the possibilities may extend a long way. For instance, could the increase in humidity in the house coming from the greenhouse alleviate many of the upper respiratory tract problems which are bothering people in the wintertime because of dry house heat? Also, what about reducing stress? When people become more vulnerable to social and economic pressures, they become more susceptible to disease. So, it might he possible that a solar greenhouse which reduces heat arid produces food, could help somebody feel more self-sufficient, self-reliant, and make them less susceptible to disease. Maybe...</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Suitts:</hi> Wait a minute. Let's not put too much of the potential before the fact now. Come back to the ground floor. Where do we go from here?</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Dow:</hi> For folks with money and the inclination to try it, they can begin to follow up on the idea for themselves. For those with no money - and these are really the people who might be helped the most - lending institutions, governments, churches, and foundations are going to need to make some money available for some exploration and demonstrations of how it all works. No matter how you look at it, it can't be a bad return on the dollar: heat, tood, possibly jobs, and perhaps improved health - all for a little time and a little more floor space in your house.</p>

<p>For information or inquiries, write Bill Dow, SRC, 75 Marietta Street, Atlanta, Georgia 30303.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">REFERENCES:</hi></p>

<p>The Food and Heat Producing Solar Greenhouse. Fisher & Yanda;
Building & Using Our SunHeated Greenhouse, Helen Scott Nearing; The
Solar Greenhouse Book, James C. McCullogh; "Organic Gardening &
Farming" magazine. December 1977.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="v1-6swift.002" n="A New Day in Wilcox County: 1978" type="Article">
<head>A New Day in Wilcox County: 1978</head>
<docAuthor>By Harriet Swift</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 1, No. 6, 1979, pp. 15,16,28</docDate>
<argument>
Harriet Swift is a copy editor at the Birmingham Post-Herald.
</argument>

<p>"Bad Wilcox," the civil rights workers used to call it.</p>

<p>"In Alabama they say that there are 66 counties and then there's Wilcox," sighs a federal official.</p>

<p>Wilcox County, resting squarely in the center of Alabama's Black Belt, presents a storybook picture of the rural Deep South. Its sparse population has steadily declined since 1900, leaving only 16,000 people (about 68 percent of them Black) to populate the tiny towns and large plantations. A pleasing vista of fertile fields, rolling hills and proud Southern forests intertwined with the Alabama River, Wilcox is dotted with white-columned mansions and pathetic wood and tin shacks. The insular, provincial social life has bred a steady line of stock Southern characters from the imperious Miss Ann in the Big House to the wise and folksy Dilsey living out back.</p>

<p>The county's abundance of traits identifying it as the archetypal
Black Belt county have not gone unnoticed. In 1950 sociologist Morton
Rubin published his well-known social anthropology study of the
Southern plantation culture, "Plantation County," which was entirely
drawn from his field research in Wilcox County. Photographer Bob
Adelman expanded his 1965 cover story on the county for the old Look
magazine into a book in 1972, the poignant and moving "Down Home." <hi rend="italic">National Geographic</hi>, <hi rend="italic">The New Yorker</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Wall Street Journal</hi>have all used the county as a Southern metaphor, while its motherlode of social patterns and inculcated race and caste obsessions have been steadily mined by graduate students and historians.</p>

<p>The characteristics of Wilcox County that have made it such an
attraction for writers and journalists are the same features that have
kept it a segregated, repressive society that has driven away the best
and brightest of both races. In 1970 the median family income was
$3,920 a year, compared with $7,200 for the state of Alabama. A recent
study based on conservative data indicates that 1.1 percent of the
county's population owns at least 70 percent of the land. The infant
mortality rate is an outrageous 32.6 per thousand births. Until 1965
no Black person had voted in the county since Reconstruction. Under
the eyes of federal<pb n="16"/> marshals dispatched by the Voting Rights Act of 1965 Black voters were added to the poll lists. But Wilcox County remained in the tight grip of White office-holders until 1978, despite repeated attempts by Blacks to win seats on the county commission, school board and positions in the courthouse.</p>

<p>A combination of factors worked against the Black community, including splits within its own ranks. But none of these divisions and frustrations were visible on a rainy, bleak January night when men, women and children from all parts of Wilcox County and the Black Belt gathered to pay homage to the two men that they had finally catapulted into the antebellum red brick courthouse in Camden.</p>

<p>Billed as an inaugural ball and program, the evening had all the trappings of a formal event and was held in the cavernous National Guard Armory on Whiskey Run Road in Camden.</p>

<p>"Something has happened to the heat," the Rev. Thomas Threadgill apologized to visitors who kept on overcoats and wraps over their tuxedos and evening gowns. No one mentioned that the armory is in the middle of a White residential section and almost adjoining the White segregation academy. At this moment of triumph there was enough warmth and generosity to ignore the chill and overlook the suspected pettiness.</p>

<p>The program was long and carefully structured. They had waited a long time and everyone was going to get a chance to share the glory. Ferdinand Ervin, a retired school principal, was the master of ceremonies and welcomed everyone to this "new day in Wilcox County." It was the official theme of the program and every speaker used it at least once, some like Ervin rolled it out in a sonorous bass and savored each syllable.</p>

<p>Threadgill, a tall imposing man who has weathered untold crises in the county with courage and dignity took the podium early in the program. The unofficial leader of the Black community in the county, the "Rev.'s" influence goes far beyond the perimeters of his New Trinity Presbyterian Church.</p>

<p>"We come to make a collective pronouncement," he said evenly. "We'd like to have some elbow room. To those crowding us in we say, get back and let us move about. Let us grow, mature and render contributions like other folk."</p>

<p>"If there are those bent on preventing that, we say, 'Get back. Here we come'."</p>

<p>The "those" warned by Threadgill were not in attendance. Out of several hundred people gathered, only five were White: two out-of-county visitors and two old civil rights hands and their seven-year-old daughter.</p>

<p>Choirs from two county high schools were included on the program and their role was oddly reminiscent of a Greek chorus. One group was resplendent in blue robes, the other in pastel gowns and conservative suits. Their songs underlined the optimism and pride that filled the room like an aroma. "I want to be ready," they sang earnestly, "to walk to Jerusalem." Without a smidgen of irony, they poured most of their fervor into "God Bless America." "Mine eyes have seen the glory of the coming of the Lord," sang voices that know what it is to attend a segregated school system that has little money and fewer resources - voices that know the hard physical labor of picking cotton and hauling water because there is not running water at home. Strong, clear voices that have rough edges and waver with emotion and energy said as much about the new day in Wilcox County as the men and women who held the podium.</p>

<p>The two new office-holders present an interesting contrast between the old and the new in the county. The newly elected sheriff is college-educated, young (26) and well versed in the unfussy rhetoric of the '70s. He is a "home boy" who headed for California and found urban America unsympathetic and unlivable.</p>

<p>His colleague, the tax collector, is a white-haired veteran of many civil rights campaigns. He has lived in the county all of his life, making his way with various jobs at various times.</p>

<p>Prince Arnold, the sheriff, was introduced first. A former special education teacher, he radiated confidence and pride. A handsome, compact man in a well-tailored three-piece suit, Arnold stepped up to the podium and waited for the standing ovation to subside.</p>

<p>"We are facing crucial decisions in the year ahead," he told the jammed auditorium. "We must win the war against racism by a landslide!"</p>

<p>He talked earnestly of brotherhood and unity, and like Threadgill, spoke to the people who were not there. "I will be sheriff of ALL the people of Wilcox County," he vowed to warm applause.</p>

<p>Arnold then addressed himself to specific issues which had much to do with his election. "I'm greatly disturbed by the number of murders in Wilcox County," he said as a murmur of approval circled the auditorium. "Today, here tonight, I am declaring a war on murder in Wilcox County!" This declaration was greeted with the most sustained applause of the night. The indifference of White law enforcement officials to crime within the Black community is a sore point in the county. Killings and other violent crimes are desultorily investigated and trials are casual. Light sentences are the rule and early parole is frequent. As one "Plantation County" resident explained to Morton Rubin in the 1940s: "When a White man kills a colored man, it's self-defense. When a colored man kills a White man it's murder. But when colored kills colored, it's just one less nigger."</p>

<p>Not any more.</p>

<p>The declaration of war was also extended to drug dealers,
"overseers of those who would like to enslave us; Judases who would betray us for a few pieces of silver while calling us 'brother.'"<pb n="28"/></p>

<p>Arnold summed up his approach to law enforcement simply. "Freedom must be deeply rooted in responsibility," he said. "We will work within the constitutional framework of the law."</p>

<p>When the affable Jesse Brooks took over the speaker's place he didn't talk about his office (a non-controversial job) or campaign promises.</p>

<p>"I stand here before you as your tax collector," he told his friends and neighbors. "But I also stand here tonight for someone else. I stand here as the grandson of a little Black slave boy who was brought down river from Charleston, South Carolina, to Lower Peachtree, Alabama, and sold for a thousand dollars. Thanks be to God there's not going to be any more bidding off of human beings!"</p>

<p>It was a wildly emotional moment and Brooks stood in the center of it ramrod straight, letting the cheers and clamorous applause roll around him. It was a golden moment when the years of struggle, pain and despair were faced squarely and dismissed. The sufferings of that "little Black slave boy" had been vindicated. Against ridiculous odds something very fine and strong had survived in Wilcox County and was now going to take its place in the sun.</p>

<p>Brooks did not fail to mention that what is ahead is more struggle, but "we plan to push forward until justice runs down like mighty waters."</p>

<p>He vowed to walk into the courthouse "just like John walked into Jerusalem" and begin working hard to build what he predicted will become "one of the best counties in God's country."</p>

<p>Bobby Joe Johnson, a Vietnam veteran who lost a hand and a leg in
the war, stepped forward to close out the program. He is the president
of the Wilcox County Democratic Conference, the Black arm of the
Democratic Party in the county. He also has a seat on the more
powerful Democratic Executive Committee, but it was the conference
that sponsored the inaugural celebration. Johnson began introducing
the evening's "Special guests," an exercise which turned into a sort
of who's who in the Black Belt. One by one he asked them to stand and
be applauded, elected officials and activists from Perry, Dallas,
Monroe, Bullock, Marengo, Lowndes, Greene, Macon and Montgomery
counties. Men and women who had fought the same long, harrowing battles and knew the price that had to be paid to elect Blacks in Bad Wilcox.</p>

<p>Like those before him, Johnson reiterated the need to look to the future. He also took the occasion to announce his candidacy for the Wilcox County Commission in 1980. "We can't stop now!"</p>

<p><hi rend="Bold">Epilogue</hi></p>

<p>"Things in the county are going real well," says Bobby Joe Johnson a month after the inaugural ball. "Prince is doing a good job. Now there's some that thought just because he was Black and they were Black, well, he'd just look the other way. But he arrested them and put them in jail. 'If you break the law I'm going to arrest you,' he told them."</p>

<p>But there have been problems. The new tax collector isn't scheduled to take over until this year's taxes are all closed out in the fall. Until that time the current tax collector is not allowing his successor in the office. A small vexation, says Johnson. A plan has been worked out for Brooks to work in the tax collector's office of a neighboring county until October.</p>

<p>Despite the great success of the inaugural ball, all did not end pleasantly. Several persons left the armory to find their tires slashed. Eye witnesses named the outgoing sheriff one of his former deputies and two other men as the culprits. All four have been arrested and charged. Although they have attempted to end the incident by apologizing and paying for the damage, they'll be tried in circuit court.</p>

<p>But nobody expected Bad Wilcox to crumple in a day. "We're making
it," says Johnson confidently. "We're doing real well."</p>
</div2>
