<div1 id="v2-7.001" n="Southern Changes 2:7" type="Issue">
<head>Southern Changes. Volume 2, Number 7, 1980</head>
<p>
<title>Southern Changes</title>. Volume 2, Number 7, 1980</p>

<div2 id="sc02-7suitts.002" n="A Tribute to Bell Wiley"
      type="Article">
<head>A Tribute to Bell Wiley</head>
<docAuthor>By Steve Suitts</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 2, No. 7, 1980, pp. 2</docDate>

<p>When I was at the University of Alabama I once had a theory that most professors and administrators showed up at meetings late because it was the custom of the university at that time to begin classes 10 minutes after the hour or half hour. With that impression of most college professors I was, of course, a bit surprised in a small way when Bell Wiley came to our meetings at the SRC offices usually ahead of time.</p>

<p>I should have known better. Bell was no stranger to me in style even at our first meeting. I had read many of his books on the Civil War and had come to know him as a very particular scholar. In the course of almost three years, I also came to appreciate the rare personal qualities of this Southerner who was in the best sense a scholar and a gentleman.</p>

<p>In fact, Bell was a far more gentle and quiet man than I had realized. While a Southern gentleman in manners, he seemed to favor sly folk humor and used it more than once. He also was obviously fond of bright red galluses.</p>

<p>Bell measured people and events carefully and often in silence a
way that reminded me of the sage of the backwoods country store who always seemed to be sitting next to the potbellied stove in a pushed-back cane chair, saying little, and knowing a great deal more.</p>

<p>These personal attributes were reflected in Bell's writing where the facts and lore about the common Southerner during the Civil War was often the stuff of which he wrote. Bell's appreciation for Southern ways obviously did not diminish his capacity to be offended by Southern racism. He often scolded White Southerners and especially Southern leaders for their facile and disingenuous arguments attempting to keep up segregation.</p>

<p>I suppose it is a statement of the obvious that Bell Wiley made important contributions to the people and ideas of his own time. He was precise and prudent in his personal habits, generous in his love for the South, and stern in his demand that hatred and neglect be rooted out of Southern life. His books and the memory of his own life will keep those simple yet unreached ideals in the hearts and minds of many who were his students, readers, colleagues, and friends - all his admirers.</p>
</div2>

<div2 id="v2-7suitts.003" n="In this Issue"
      type="Article">
<head>In this Issue</head>
<docAuthor>By Steve Suitts</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 2, No. 7, 1980, pp. 2-3</docDate>

<p>About this time of year in 1948 a simple, yet remarkable occurance
took place in Richmond, Virginia. A Black man named Oliver Hill was
elected to the City Council. In the next few ywears other political
breakthorughs occured. In Nashville in 1951 a Black attorney,
Alexander Looby, was elected to the city's governing board and in late
1953 the prominent Black decuator Rufus Clement began to serve on the
Atlanta school board.</p>

<p>Of course, it was not until afer 1965 with the passage of the
Voting Rights Act that more than 20 percent of the South's population
began to have more than a symbolic opportunity to exercise and
franchise and to help put Blacks into office</p>

<p>In this issue and others to come this year, we will be looking
closely at the status of Southern politics and especially the
achievements, disappointments, and obstacles that Black voters
and Black officeholders face. Like some other rural and urban places
in the South, Richmond now has several Blacks onthe city council and a
Black mayor. Yet the problems and limitations with which these
andother officials must function are considerable as they attempt to
translate political gains into real and specific social and economic
progress; moreover, in many Southern communities even basic political
gains have not yet been realized.</p>

<p>To set the stage for this on-going theme, this month's <hi
rend="italic"> Southern Changes</hi> tells of both the immediate and
historic problems with which the poor of any color in the South must
live today. Veteran writer Wayne Greenhaw gives us a glimpse of the
lives of the poor, rural Blacks and Indians in south Alabama where the
myths about welfare recipients are tragically disproven. Probably
supported more by their own fierce sense of heritage and independence,
these Southerns are fighting for nothing more than survival. </p>

<p>Our managing editor, Janis Powell, also filed a report on the
Protest for Survival, a ten day series of events last month when
groups across the South attempted to object loudly to the fact that
the poor were the major victims of the congressional efforts to
balance the budget. Also, we have a
<pb n="3"/>
soapbox piece which suggests that even when the federal government is
not cutting back its programs touching the lives of the poor, its
methods of measuring poverty to determine who will receive assistance
is a distortion of need and reality.</p>

<p>Our two pieces on the political status of the South are case
studies of two communities not greatly different in social and
economic life. Both are located in the Black Belt of the South with
large Black populations, an agricultural past,and little present
industry. They differ perhaps most remarkably in their stage of
political develpment.</p>

<p>From Dawson, Georgia, senior editor, Betty Chaney tells the story
of recent Black achievements to break the racial barriers of elected
office. We find here a sense of very real achievement and optimism on
the part of Blacks who are the first to hold elected office. Even in
"Terrible Terrell," one of the life-long dreams of many in the Black
community has finally come true.</p>

<p>As our cover story illustrates, the political journey in Lowndnes
County, Alabama may be a sobering reminder of the difficulties that
communities continue to face even after the political system has begun
to change. A decade after Blacks began holding public office, Lowndes
County's Black and White officials find enormous economic and societal
barriers that continue to stymie rapid change. With a caring view for
detail and mood, Tom Gordon's writing demonstrates that the burden of
the past remains often the real limit for the future. Perhaps just as
disturbing, the alternatives available to Lowndnes County in moving
itself out of the poverty and racial conflict are clearly limited.</p>

<p>Finally, Patrice Gaines-Carter reviews for us the controversy in
Florid over the McDuffie case where politics and the courts are being
tested as means of dealing with the issue of police/community
relations.</p>

<p>When finished with this issue, you may have a sense of frustration,
puzzlement and perhaps even anger. At least these were some of my
first reactions. At the same time I gather from these reports and
perspectives some confirmation that the South retains a reservoir of
energy, gaith and devotion offering  a possibility that this region
may yetfind and hold on to a better sense of community then has ever
been known or practiced on this soil.</p>

<div2 id="v2-7powell.004" n="Survival Week Protests Budget Cuts"
      type="Article">
<head>Survival Week Protests Budget Cuts</head>
<docAuthor>Janis Sharp Powell</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 2, No. 7, 1980, p. 4</docDate>


<p>"No cuts in poor people's programs" was the message being sent to Congress and the nation by the poor people and labor, civil rights, tenants and religious organizations involved in planning Survival Week.</p>

<p>Over 150 organizations in nine Southern states organized and endorsed Survival Week, a series of activities that took place May 1-11 to protest Carter's efforts to "balance the budget" and "fight inflation" at the expense of poor people's needs for jobs, housing, medical care, food and education.</p>

<p>The cuts threaten to close Black colleges, cripple health care for the young and elderly, and hundreds of thousands of families will face hunger, malnutrition, and starvation when the cuts eliminate the food stamp program. Organizers of Survival Week state that "Carter wants to spend $4 billion less on poor people so he can spend $4 billion more on guns and bullets." They feel that the federal government is trying to trade the need for medical care and a decent income for two submarines and a bomber.</p>

<p>A spirited rally by the Atlanta Welfare Rights Organization on May
9 set the stage for a series of weekend demonstrations centered in
Georgia. As a crowd of 300 rallied at the Richard B. Russell federal building to chants that "hungry people will steal, hungry people will kill" plans were being made for people all over to go to a rally in Americus, Georgia and march to Plains Jimmy Carter's home town. Two hundred marchers carried "Say No to Carter's Budget Cuts" banners and other placards while chanting "Don't want no Carter, no Carter; don't want no Klan, no Klan; just want some justice, jobs and land" through the south Georgia countryside.</p>

<p>Mother's Day marked the final demonstration for Survival Week. One
thousand protestors, representing the South's poor and hungry, marched
in Atlanta on Sunday, in what the Committee for Survival called a "March for Bread and Justice." The march followed the route of Martin Luther King's funeral procession by Morehouse College where Rosalyn Carter was giving a commencement address to a freedom rally in University Park at the Atlanta University Center. The loudest chant of "Jimmy Carter has got to go" was heard as demonstrators passed by Morehouse.</p>

<p>Students staged a separate demonstration to protest the First Lady's presence at the Black men's college. They claimed her presence was a ploy to obtain the votes of Black and poor people by displaying her "concern for their welfare and respect for their educational institutions." Four persons were arrested for criminal trespass and failure to disperse as they protested in front of the Martin Luther King, Jr. Chapel on the campus.</p>

<p>Congress meanwhile was moving toward averting the cutoff but many
fear it will not move fast enough. Protestors also stress that simply
reinstating the current allotment will not be sufficient. With the
current rate of inflation, without an increase, the poor will have a
25 percent "budget cut" based on what they are receiving now.</p>
</div2>
<div2 id="sc02-7eisenberg.006" n="The Measure of Poverty" type="article">
<head>The Measure of Poverty</head>
<docAuthor>Pablo Eisenberg</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 2, No. 7, 1980, pp. 5-6</docDate>


<p>When Lyndon Johnson proclaimed his unconditional War on Poverty in 1964, no one knew precisely the number or even the definition of "poor." As a result, the Council of Economic Advisors quickly sought to designate the poverty population and concluded among other things that in 1961 a family of two or more making under $3,000 a year had been in official poverty.</p>

<p>An estimated food budget was the basis for determining the poverty index for different families. Based on 1955 surveys by the U.S. Department of Agriculture, the Council found that food expenditures accounted for one-third of a low-income family's total budget. With that evidence, the cost of the 1961 "economy food plan" was multiplied by three, yielding a total amount needed by that family to meet all costs. This figure became the official poverty line.</p>

<p>Questions about the adequacy of the food plan were raised
early. Even the author of the formula wrote in 1965 "with this plan,
adequate nutrition is obtainable, but in practice, nearly half the
families spending so little fell far short of adequacy. Of families spending at this rate in 1965, more than 40 percent have diet providing less than two-thirds of their requirements."</p>

<p>In 1969 the model took on further administrative status when the Bureau of the Budget designated the index as the official government measure of poverty. From that point on all federal programs were required to use this official measuring system in determining eligibility and funding in many key legislative efforts to combat poverty.</p>

Under the official measure, the current poverty index figures for families of various sizes are divided between farm and nonfarm.

In order to place the figures in context, one can look at the $6,700 a year allowed for an urban family of four. Officially speaking, such a family is not poor, although their income is under $130 a week, out of which all costs are supposed to come.

Suppose such a family lives in a small apartment or home. Even at a low temperature setting; the fuel bill could easily be $700 or more for the year. Rent (actual home ownership is unlikely) might be guessed at a conservative $150 a month, or $1,800 a year. The total of $2,500 for home and heat alone leaves $4,300 for all other costs. Food, clothing, medical care, transportation, and everything else are to be covered with scarcely $20 a week for each family member.

Of course, this family may receive food stamps or some other forms of assistance. Nevertheless, under the existing measure it is not officially poor. Yet families with three and four times the income of this hypothetical family of four are today wondering how to make ends meet.

F more rural people the

problem becomes even more difficult. The federal government continues to assume that rural living costs are substantially less than urban costs. The 1979 poverty threshold for an urban family of four is inadequate enough at $6,700; a non-urban family of four is supposed to be able to get by on $1,000 less than that before it is included among the official low-income population.

The assumption that rural means cheaper is based on the idea that rural housing is less expensive and that family gardens and farms can help reduce grocery bills. However, the actual cost of basic commodities in rural areas can often be higher than in urban areas. Take as one current example transportation costs. Public transit rarely exists in rural areas. People are forced to drive more and pay more for gas than their urban counterparts.

While many rural people are

Family

Size Nonfarm Farm 1 $3,400 $2,910

2 4,500 3,840 3 5,600 4,770

4 6,700 5,700 5 7,800 6,630 6 8,900 7,560
able to maintain gardens, they still must purchase basic needs. Rural stores, lacking the high volume markets which enable cheaper quantity purchasing, often charge more than larger, urban outlets. Additional transportation costs also increase the prices for items ranging from flour to hair brushes.

Extensive, research by the Bureau of Labor Statistics and others has shown that variations in the cost of maintaining fixed standards of living are very slight across the country. Nonetheless, the federal poverty line is roughly 15 percent less for rural areas. Is this supposed to mean that rural people should accept a 15 percent lower standard of living?

And while rural life does offer such non-urban virtues as openness, cleaner air, and a lack of rush hours, rural people also often have fewer recreational, social and cultural facilities. Medical care is generally harder to find, if indeed it is available at all. School districts are often underfunded, and jobs and other opportunities for youth are more limited. While some absolute costs may be lower in rural areas, they are more than offset by other factors preventing rural people from enjoying the same overall standard of living as city people.

The official poverty index fails to indicate accurately the extent of both absolute and relative poverty. Estimates are that 10 million more people - about a 40 percent increase - would be added to the poverty population if the measure were based on a diet incorporating more nutritional needs and current spending patterns.

In 1979, for example, the poverty index for a family of four stood at $6,700. The technique used to set that figure

 assumed that food would represent one-third of the budget or $186 a month. That translates into $1.55 per person per day for food. By any measure, a $1.55 a day per person for food is not adequate or rational.

Not only is the nutritional value of the plan questionable, but the current system for determining the food budget does not take geographic or cultural differences into account. Nor does it consider the changing dietary needs of persons at different stages of life. The elderly often have particular dietary needs that are expensive. Young mothers and growing teenagers certainly require diets that can easily exceed the food cost allowances.

Currently, the poverty level is raised by the increase in the consumer price index; however, the price of food and other basic necessities have increased at a far greater rate for most poor people.

Between 1977 and 1978, the cost of living for all items increased 7.6 percent, Nonetheless, the adjustment in the poverty index reflected the smaller, overall figure.

Since 1969 food has risen 94 percent while the total index has risen 78 percent. Costs for two other basic necessities - housing and energy - have also increased at a faster rate than the general price index. In 1978 as much as one-third of the income of the average poor household may have gone to pay for energy.

From both a numerical and human standpoint, then, poverty in America remains very real and significant. No amount of statistical manipulation can deny the poverty which is listed officially, let alone that which any more rational form or definition would reveal.

Perhaps government officials

and others who should be outraged at the extent and persistence of poverty believe the rhetoric that these are conservative times and that programs are more likely to face cut-backs instead of expansion. In and outside of government, many people have lost a sense of the impact of poverty and are unaware of what an official definition of poverty means for poor people. It is hard to believe that after more than 15 years of anti-poverty efforts, we continue to utilize a poverty measure which is so far removed from real costs faced daily by millions of families.

Major reform in the poverty definition is an essential first step in a revitalized effort against poverty. In view of the mood of the times, though, advocates of the poor and near-poor must portray their concerns in ways the general population can appreciate. Poverty, after all, is more than just a moral wrong. It is also a fiscal and physical waste of resources. All society pays for poverty.

By whatever reasonable and realistic measure we may want to use, it is clear that this country has an enormous and not so invisible poor population - one that probably exceeds 25 percent of the entire population. We cannot escape this fact, no matter how hard we try to pretend that such poverty is not there. Widespread poverty means continued misery for the poor themselves and a waste of general human potential for all of us. It stands as a continuing challenge to our democracy.

This article is adapted from a publication of the Center for Community Change, a Washingtonbased organization assisting local community development in low-income urban and rural areas. Pablo Einsenberg is the Center's president.

<div2 id="v2-7chaney.005" n="Political Changes in Terrible Terrell"
      type="Article">
<head>Political Changes in Terrible Terrell</head>
<docAuthor>By Betty Chaney</docAuthor>
<docDate>Vol. 2, No. 7, 1980, pp. 7-10</docDate>
<argument>
<p>Betty Chaney is senior editor of <hi rend="italic">Southern Changes</hi>.</p></argument>

<p>0n a winter's day in January 1980, Dawson, Georgia, internationally known for the racially inflamed "Dawson Five" murder trial of three years ago, quietly eased itself into the pages of history again. For this small, predominately Black, southwestern Georgia town, the county seat for "Terrible Terrell" County, making history is not something new. Back in 1960 it became the first jurisdiction to be sued by the Justice Department under the 1957 Civil Rights Act for discrimination in voter registration. This time, however, unlike much of its past history when Black men lined up against White to do battle, three Black men stood alongside three White men and were sworn in together as Dawson City Council members.</p>

<p>The victories for the Black men, Robert Albritten, Abraham Breedlove and Lucius Holloway, did not come easy. In fact they were the culmination of a long and fierce struggle. Terrell County was not nicknamed "terrible" because it rhymed; it had one of the worst records of race repression and violence in the South. Headlines about bombing and shooting of Black homes, the burning of Black churches, and even the murder of Blacks by Whites were not uncommon in Terrell County.</p>

<p>The September 13, 1962, issue of <hi rend="italic">The Dawson Times</hi> carried the following account:</p>

<p>- Two Negro churches, about a mile apart as the crow flies, were destroyed by fire at practically the same time early last Sunday morning.</p>

<p>- One of the churches - Mt. Olive at Sasser - had been employed recently for weekly Negro voter-registration meetings.</p>

<p>- The other - Mt. Mary at Chickasawhatchee - reportedly had been intermittently used for that purpose.</p>

<p>On December 12, 1963 the paper carried another report:</p>

<p>- Officers this week extended their investigation beyond the boundaries of Terrell County into the bombing and shooting into of two Negro homes in Dawson early Sunday morning.</p>

<p>The home of Carolyn Daniels, Negro woman who was spear-heading the Negro registration drive locally, was extensively damaged by a bomb and the nearby home of Willie Eston, Negro, was riddled with at least 50 gun shots."</p>

<p>Davey Gibson, whose family has been in Terrell for decades,
recalled that on more than one occasion Black men held for
<pb n="8"/> 
various offenses were beaten after being released from jail, One man,
he said, died after a number of days following such a beating. Gibson, one of the plaintiffs in the historic Justice Department suit against the Terrell County Board of Registrars, was himself the victim of another common form of repression. When he and four other college-educated Blacks were denied the right to register to vote because they allegedly could not read, they filed a suit against the county voter registrars and in reprisal the four teachers were not rehired.</p>

<p>The court in that case found evidence of discrimination against Black persons attempting to register and placed the Terrell County Board of Registrars under permanent injunction.</p>

<p>Then in 1968, the Terrell County Grand Jury Commissioners were placed under a permanent injunction by the Fifth Circuit Court of Appeals after it found that Blacks had been discriminated against in the selection of persons for grand and traverse jury service.</p>

<p>Still another permanent injunction was issued against Terrell. This time it was against the board of education whose dual school system was not dismantled until the 1970-71 school year.</p>

<p>Following these injunctions, three voting rights suits, involving the method of selecting the Terrell County Board of Education, the Board of Commissioners, and the Dawson City Council were all successfully challenged. The plaintiffs maintained that the county's pervasive history of racial discrimination continued to have a present day effect and that at-large elections were being used to perpetuate the exclusion of Blacks from the political process.</p>

<p>The Court directed that the method of selecting the board of education members be returned to appointment by the grand jury. This resulted in two Black persons being appointed, becoming the first Blacks to hold countywide office in Terrell County since the Reconstruction era.</p>

<p>The election of the three Black city council members marked the first
time ever that a  black person had been elected to the Council. Both Holloway and Albritten had run for the post, at-large, on three separate occasions. Their victories were the direct result of
The court-ordered reapportionment plan brought by the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) on behalf of Black voters in Dawson. At-large elections in Dawson denied Black voters equal access to the local political process, the suit claimed. The three Blacks who were elected ran from wards in which there is now a majority of Black registered voters.</p>

<p>The election raises once more the question of whether or not Dawson
has changed for good. Three years ago Attorney Millard Fanner paraded
the evils of Dawson before a captive international audience during the
"Dawson Five" murder trial. He portrayed the town and Terrell County
as a White supremacist society that tried to frame five young innocent
teens. When the murder charges were dropped for the five accused of gunning down a White farmer in a grocery store robbery, three of them left town. "Dawson is no place for a Black man," one said.</p>

<p>There hasn't been "any real social or economic change," a Black minister, the Rev. Ezekiel M. Holley, said when questioned after the trial. "This is a racist town. Hate breeds here like a germ." Ima Rude, the White executive secretary of the city council disagreed, however, saying "Dawson is the garden spot of the world. People don't think in terms of color."</p>

<p>Christopher Coates, the ACLU staff attorney who handled the voting rights suits, has been in and out of Dawson for the last five years. It is this very factor of race and the extent to which it colors all of Terrell county's life that begins to explain a hardcore racist town like Dawson, he suggests.</p>

<p>"People from Andy Young to Jimmy Carter have said that if discrimination is stopped, everyone wins. Hogwash!" Coates said. "Whites get definite benefits from discrimination."</p>

<p>He has found a pattern between racism and one's own
self-interest. It is sometimes more apparent in smaller towns like
Dawson than in larger cities. With only a few jobs to go around,
decisions about whether secretarial positions in the city clerk's
office go to Blacks or Whites loom vastly more
<pb n="9"/>
important.</p>

<p>Coates believes that the level of repression in an area is directly related to the percentage of Blacks in the population and to the lack of White leadership that would advocate racial equality. The inclination on the part of officials to participate in blatant racist acts, he says, increases with the percentage of Blacks in the population.</p>

<p>By this standard, racial conditions in Terrell are no different than in surrounding areas. Terrell is one of 23 counties in southwest Georgia with majority Black populations. In Terrell County there was a mass exodus of Whites from the public schools to private schools when integration took place. In a county that is 60 percent Black, now the public schools there are 90 percent Black. Similarly, in neighboring.. Mitchell County the same thing happened so that now Blacks make up 48 percent of Mitchell's population, but are 60 percent of the public school enrollment.</p>

<p>In other respects, though, "Terrible Terrell" is more staunch. Whereas some other counties might play it smart and allow a few token Blacks to register to vote, Coates said, so fearful was Terrell of Black power, they would allow almost no Blacks to register (12 Blacks in all) or serve on juries before lawsuits were won.</p>

<p>There are other exceptional factors too. One is Mayor James
G. Raines. (Another is Carl Rountree, editor of the conservative
newspaper, <hi rend="italic">The Dawson Times</hi>, who still argues the segregationist line.)</p>

<p>In the Justice Department voter registration suit, Raines was then the chairman of the 
Terrell Board of Registrars and a defendant in the case.  A wealthy landowner and Harvard law school graduate, Raines has been mayor of Dawson for a total of 16 years - 12 consecutively - and is probably the most powerful man in Terrell County.</p>

<p>"Raines," Coates contends, "is the key to why Terrell has had so many problems." His inability to provide enlightened leadership has been the county's biggest impediment, and because no economic pressure could be brought to bear on him, Raines was in an ideal position to provide that kind of leadership.</p>

<p>Raines responds to the charge in a humble, polite, good-ole-boy Southern fashion that he provided "the best leadership that I knew how."</p>

<p>When the mayor talks about the changes that have taken place in
Dawson during his
<pb n="10"/>
administration, he speaks of things like better paved streets, a sewage and water system, fire protection and pension plans for the police department. No mention is made of jobs or industry. There is still only one major industry in town and no construction is underway. But even the things the mayor points to with pride have come under attack. Councilman -elect Holloway says the town needs to continue sewage -extensions and to finish paving and maintaining streets in the Black sections of Dawson.</p>

<p>Holloway, long considered an "agitator" by the White community, says there have  been no vast improvements in Dawson.  Holloway should know since he's been battling in  Dawson for years: he was one of the plaintiffs in the ACLU suit against the board of  registration 1968 a plaintiff against the jury commissioners; and in 1976 a plaintiff against the board of education and board of commissioners.</p>

<p>Holloway said that the only change he had seen on the part of Whites since he and the other Black councilmen took office has been in a "show of attitude." He points to the fact that the Dawson Chamber of Commerce is actually soliciting Black membership. He and his wife, Emma Kate, were offered and accepted Chamber membership.</p>

<p>It is still too early to judge the changes in Dawson from its racially-mixed city council. In a three White/three Black split, the mayor is the tie-breaker. So far he has broken two ties when councilmen were deadlocked along racial lines. One time, Holloway reports, he voted with the Whites and the other time he voted with the Blacks. The mayor agreed to advertise the fact that Blacks are now permitted to use the formerly all-White cemetery. The cemetery figured prominently in defense strategy in the "Dawson Five" trial to show that a White supremacist attitude existed from birth to the grave in Dawson.</p>

<p>The impact of the Black city councilmen is not expected to be
immediate or monumental. The city budget, for one thing, was already
set when the trio took office. Still the councilmen have high
hopes. Holloway says he wanted to put more Blacks in clerical and
white collar jobs in city governments and to appoint Blacks to board
and commission positions. Breedlove looks forward to a new image of
Dawson that will draw back Blacks who left and attract new industry to
give them jobs. How close they come to having their hopes realized is
a page from Dawson's history yet to be written.</p>
</div2>

</div1>