<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader type="text">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Southern Changes.  Volume 20, Number 3, 1998</title>
            <author>Staff</author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Compiled and edited by</resp>
               <name>staff</name>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Lewis H. Beck Center</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Emory University</pubPlace>
            <address>
               <addrLine>Atlanta, Georgia</addrLine>
            </address>
            <availability>
               <p>1996 Emory University. Permission is granted to 
download, transmit, or otherwise reproduce, distribute or display the contributions to 
the work claimed by Emory University for non-profit educational purposes, provided  
this header is included in its entirety.  For inquiries about commercial uses, contact 
either: Southern Changes Web Project or Lewis H. Beck Center for Electronic 
collections and services, Emory University, Atlanta, Georgia 30322</p>
            </availability>
            <date>2003</date>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Southern Changes Web Project</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>Southern Changes.  Volume 20, Number 3. 1998</bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>This text is produced in conjunction with the  
Southern Changes Web Project at Emory University and the Southern Regional Council, 133 Carnegie Way, Suite 900, Atlanta, GA 30303-1024</p>
         </projectDesc>
      </encodingDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2003</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Beck Center</name>
               <resp>Staff</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <item>SGML tags inserted in compliance with TEI guidelines using TEILITE</item>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 id="v20-3.001" n="Southern Changes 20:3" type="Volume">
            <head>Southern Changes.  Volume 20, Number 3, 1998</head>
            <p> 
               <title>Southern Changes.</title>  Volume 20, Number 3, 1998</p>
            <div2 id="v20-3.002" n="Covering Race: A Deep White Sleep" type="Review">
               <head>The Culture of Whiteness</head>
               <docAuthor>Reviewed by TED OWNBY</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 20, No. 3, 1998</docDate>

<p>In the past few years, historians have begun to tell the story of whiteness. Moved by the scholarship of historian David Roediger and the ideas of Toni Morrison, scholars are investigating what it is about whiteness that binds people together, what privileges the concept gives those who claim it, and how it divides those who claim to be white from those who do not. This form of analysis is one of the most inspired examples of the de-essentializing trend in contemporary scholarship that views supposedly inherited categories of identity as works of construction.</p>
<p>Grace Hales <title>Making Whiteness</title> is the best book in this genre. It is also the first work to analyze how the concept of whiteness developed in southern history. Rather than asking familiar questions about the origins of segregation, disfranchisement, or anti-black violence, she asks how people in the Jim Crow era came to understand and articulate the meanings of being white.</p>
<p>Hale's explanations for the increasingly aggressive statements about whiteness around the turn of the century vary from the familiar to the new. Two -- emancipation and urbanization -- are well known. Hale begins the volume with a third explanation that the various forms of assertiveness of African Americans from emancipation through the early twentieth century stimulated new efforts to define the privileges of whiteness. A fourth explanation is the most novel. The development of a national consumer culture had the potential to undercut human differences by offering the privileges of spending money and enjoying goods to anyone who could afford them. Thus, in Hale's analysis, openly racist advertisements and "whites only" and "colored only" railroad compartments emerged as ways to create differences in situations that threatened to dissolve them.</p>
<p>Perhaps as important as its conclusions, the book offers a powerful example of history that investigates the stories Southerners told to help them understand their society. Segregation and white supremacy emerge as works in progress, full of tensions and insecurities that people tried to explain through different kinds of narratives. The stories she describes from an astonishing variety of sources -- novelists, journalists, advertisers, lynch mobs, United Daughters of the Confederacy speakers -- reveal the work of people trying to order their lives by using the notion that there was something special about being white. The story of the well-dressed black woman on the train was George Washington Cable's narrative that complicated easy notions that whiteness implied special privileges based on cleanliness and manners. The stories Joel Chandler Harris told in the voice of Uncle Remus displayed African-American personality but also gave whites reassuring notions of "the old plantation-bound ex-slave." Stories of Mammy figures involved a love of idealized women and slavery but also legitimated segregation as the story of adults who had consigned those images to misty memories. Racist advertisements that put African Americans in degrading positions reassured white consumers that blacks could not gain dignity through new access to goods. Lynchings told their own stories to use violence, and the denial "that any space was black space," all in a modem environment facilitated by railroads and advertising.</p>
<p>Far too much scholarly writing about identity construction is filled with excruciating jargon, as if to suggest that academics who are re-thinking basic assumptions have to write in their own language. Hale can play that game, but most of her work is powerful and direct.  In fact, on occasion her prose has the sound of a W.J. Cash for our generation. The South of legend, she writes, was "the place of not now." Nostalgia about the antebellum South was "the fun house mirror of New South progress." This is simply a wonderful book to read.</p>
<p>Hale's conclusion lies in the tradition of Winthrop Jordan's monumental <title>White Over Black</title> (1968). Jordan argued that change would come when individuals stop projecting the things they hate and fear about themselves onto other people they identify as an essentially different group (or race). Where Jordan stressed psychology and the need for individual conversion, Hale concentrates on societal ideals and regional identities. She calls on readers "to reimagine integration' by rejecting ideas of essential, in-born differences dividing people and by learning or remembering that southern and American history is the story of interdependence and shared experience. </p>

</div2>

            <div2 id="v20-3.003" n="The "New" Disfranchisement" type="Article">
               <head>The "New" Disfranchisement</head>
               <docAuthor>By Winnett Hagens and Ellen Spears</docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 20, No. 3, 1998</docDate>
<argument><p>Winnett Hagens is director of Fair Representation Programs and Ellen Spears is communications director at the Southern Regional Council.</p></argument>

<p>Because the core premise of a democratic society is that legitimate rule is based on the consent of the governed, the linchpin of our democratic order is fair representation. And fair representation begins with access to the ballot. In an intentionally democratic system like ours, rules about who is allowed to vote inevitably affect who gets what. </p>
<p>In American history, outright disfranchisement has been one of the
most common tactics employed by propertied interests seeking to
protect their advantages. Nowhere has disfranchisement worked better to preserve and entrench rule by a narrow segment of privilege and wealth in American society than its use in the South following Reconstruction. In the last quarter of the nineteenth century, white elites began building what V.O. Key in his 1949 book <hi rend="italic">Southern Politics</hi> called "the most impressive systems of obstacles between the voter and the ballot box known to the democratic world." Since readers of <hi rend="italic">Southern Changes</hi> are familiar with the inventory of ballot obstructions (literacy tests, poll taxes, all white primaries, etc.) instituted under segregation, the subject needs no elaboration here. </p>
<p>By today's standards, those methods of outright
disfranchisement-the "old" or traditional disfranchisement-are crude
and blunt mechanisms of control. The "old" disfranchisement simply
stole and denied the right to vote. The "new" disfranchisement gives
people the vote, and in doing so it breathes life into the illusion of
a society based on consent. This "new" disfranchisement steals from
the voters not their ballots but their choice of candidates and
representatives. It also steals the power of the vote through
dilution. Taylor Branch, in his book <hi rend="itlalic">Pillar of Fire</hi>, captured the essence of the "new" disfranchisement when he quoted civil rights worker Bob Moses in 1964: "The best way to keep someone a slave is to give him the vote and call him free." </p>
<p>Camouflage-concealing the potent and polarizing influence of race
and money in politics-is the distinctive feature of the "new"
disfranchisement, which we examine in this issue of <hi rend="italic">Southern Changes</hi>. The "new" disfranchisement is not enforced by police with billy clubs and tear gas. Voter intimidation persists, as witnessed in the multi-faceted assault on the use of absentee ballots and black political power in Greene County, Alabama. (See "Voting Rights on Trial Again in Alabama," by veteran activist Anne Braden, Summer 1998,  <hi rend="italic">Southern Changes</hi>.) Yet, even where such intimidation is absent, having a vote feels utterly pointless for voters if they have little or no hope of using it to protect their interests. The willful retreat from justice in voting rights is a classic case in point. </p>
<p>"The simple fact is that virtually all districts in which whites
are a majority elect white candidates.... For blacks to win," wrote
Lisa Handley and Bernard Grofman in the 1994 book <hi
rend="italic">Quiet Revolution in the South</hi>, "it is therefore
still necessary in the South to draw districts in which blacks are a
majority or a supermajority of the population." Even though it is
beyond dispute that African Americans and Latinos have almost no
chance of electing community-based candidates of their choice without
district geographies holding a preponderance of their voters, federal
courts have repeatedly rejected districts where race is a major factor
as unconstitutional. The courts' rulings in the 1993 <hi rend="italic">Shaw</hi> case and its progeny are "racially unfair and nearly unmanageable," explains Laughlin McDonald in his article, "Redistricting at the Millenium," quoting Supreme Court dissenters who point out that the recent rulings disadvantage the very group they were designed to help.</p>
<p>When the smoke screen of litigation lifts, we are left with a
legacy no carefully crafted electoral remedy can circumvent, the enduring fact of white racial bloc voting. "Until racial bloc voting diminishes, black-majority congressional districts are one appropriate and necessary means of ensuring that black candidates are afforded an equal opportunity to compete for-not win-office," argues Harvard public policy professor Keith Reeves in "When a Black Face Turns Away White Votes." Reeves shares his innovative research on media messages and white racial bloc voting in an excerpt from his 1997 book,<hi rend="italic">"Voting Hopes or Fears?: White Voters, Black Candidates and Racial Politics in America."</hi> </p>
<p>Sometimes circumstances-whether court rulings or geographical dispersion-preclude the use of districting as a leveling mechanism. In "Monopoly Politics: Southern Style," Center for Voting and Democracy Director Rob Richie explores an alternate route to fair representation for minorities, suggesting proportional representation as one way out of low turnout, uncontested elections and the limits of the winner-take-all system. Proportional systems are in effect in more than 200 localities in the U.S., including a number of communities in Alabama and Texas. They work to enfranchise any political minority-whether a racial or ethnic group, or a political party. </p>
<p>Of course, unless and until such systems enjoy more widespread use, incumbent politicians control the redistricting process. Allan Lichtman shares his predictions of expanded Republican power in the South after the November elections and the attendant consequences for the 2000 Census and the redistricting to follow.</p>
<p>In a special section, we explore what competes with race as a powerful disfranchising mechanism-Money in Politics-and the growing movement to curb its influence. Huge and growing sums of money are now required to capture public office. Any candidate reaching the ballot in today's world has already been pre-selected by an invisible "wealth primary," a "new-old" method of exclusion from decision-making. Advocates Randy Kehler, Sharon Basco, Gwen Patton, Stephanie Anthony and Pete McDowell outline what's at stake in this democratic fight for Clean Money and Clean Elections.</p>
<p>Criminal disfranchisement laws, the denial of the right to vote of people convicted of crimes have a disproportionate impact on African American males. Earl Shinhoster questions the unequal effect of these laws, with 1.4 million (one in seven) black men denied the right to vote due to present or prior felony convictions. </p>
<p>Jim Blacksher brings us back to the starting point: our society's legitimacy rests on the consent of the governed. Wholesale disfranchisement, delivered through unjust voting rights decisions, criminal disfranchisement laws, and the power of money, plainly contradicts the principle of consent. In departing from this principle, he says, the Shaw majority "would make interracial  legislative dialogue constitutionally illegitimate and black  political influence once again impotent." </p>

<p>Sadly, calls for genuine interracial dialogue have been all but buried in what passes for governance these days. The success of that interracial political dialogue requires fair representation of political interests-in a system that disfranchises no one.</p>

	    </div2>

            <div2 id="v20-3.004" n="The Midterm Elections in the South: Another Democratic Slide?" type="Article">
               <head>The Midterm Elections in the South: Another Democratic Slide?</head>
               <docAuthor>By Allan J. Lichtman </docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 20, No. 3, 1998</docDate>
<argument><p>Allan J. Lichtman chairs the Department of History at American University in Washington, D.C. He has participated as an expert witness in more than fifty federal voting rights and redistricting lawsuits and is the author of  The Keys to the White House, 1996: A Surefire Guide to Protecting the Next President, Madison Books (1996).
</p></argument>

<p>The notion that Bill Clinton saved the Democratic party by moving it from the left to the center of the political spectrum is another convenient theory exploded by inconvenient facts.  During the Clinton years  Democrats have suffered the worst drubbing at the polls since  World War I.</p>
<p>Democrats have lost control of both houses of Congress and of numerous state house and senate chambers. Since 1990, the number of Democratic governors has declined from twenty-nine to sixteen. Of the ten largest states, only Florida and North Carolina still have Democratic governors.</p>
<p>Nowhere has the decline of the Democratic party been more evident than in the once solidly Democratic South. Today, Democrats control a minority of U.S. House and Senate seats and governors' mansions in the South.</p>
<p>There is little chance that Democrats will reverse the Republican tide in the South in the midterm elections of 1998. Rather, these elections will likely bring additional Democratic losses in the South and elsewhere, with profound implications for the 2000 Census, the post-Census redistricting,  and policies that affect U.S. minority groups.</p>
<p>Given that Democrats in the South are as far or farther behind Republicans in U.S. Senate seats and governorships as in U.S. House seats, Democratic losses in the South cannot be attributed to the creation of majority-minority House districts following the Census of 1990. The Democrats' Southern problem is neither caused by nor subject to remedy by redistricting. Rather, it reflects a huge decline in votes cast for Democratic candidates.</p>
<p>In most Southern states there are no longer enough Democratic votes to create majorities for Democratic statewide candidates or Democratic congressional delegations. In Georgia, for example, the Democratic share of votes cast in congressional races fell from 61.3 percent in 1990 to 45.5 percent in 1994. In North Carolina, the Democratic share fell from 54.7 percent to 43.8 percent.</p>
<p>Thus far Democratic losses in the South have largely been confined to white voters. In most Southern states, Republicans can routinely count on 60 percent or more of the white vote. But, there are signs that Democrats may be losing their near-unanimous support from Southern black voters. In the 1997 elections for governor of  Virginia, victorious Republican candidate James Gilmore garnered a record 20 percent vote from African Americans. In Florida, with white and black Democrats squabbling, Republican gubernatorial candidate Jeb Bush seems poised to make significant inroads into the black vote. In other Southern states, similar though less serious rifts between black and white Democrats have emerged as well. Even a small loss in black support would have devastating consequences for Democrats in the South.</p>
<p>Although there should be no major shifts of party power in the South this year, chances are that the Democrats will slide further downhill. If the Clinton scandals explode further prior to November, that slide could be even steeper than is now expected. In governor's races, Democrats could lose two of the most important states the party still holds: Florida and Georgia, both of which have retiring Democratic governors. In Florida, Republican Jeb Bush is expected to defeat Democratic Lieutenant Governor Buddy MacKay. In Georgia, wealthy Republican businessman Guy Millner is perched to prevail over Democratic State Representative Roy Barnes. Another tight race is shaping up in Alabama, where Democratic Lieutenant Governor Don Siegelman faces  incumbent Republican Governor Fob James, who won easily after a brutal primary struggle.</p>
<p>House and Senate races in the South also present greater opportunities for Republicans than Democrats, especially in a midterm election with the White House in Democratic hands. Not since 1934 has the party of the President made gains in Congress during a midterm election. In the Senate, Republicans have a decent chance to pick up an open seat in Kentucky and the seat held by Ernest F. (Fritz) Hollings in South Carolina. The most vulnerable Republican is Lauch Faircloth in North Carolina. </p>
<p>In the House, about fifteen seats are in play, with Republicans having about two or three more opportunities than Democrats. In Alabama's Fifth Congressional District, Republicans may defeat Robert E. (Bud) Cramer, the last white Democratic Representative in that state. Already there are no white Democratic House members in Georgia and only one in Kentucky, Louisiana, South Carolina, Mississippi, and Alabama. If there is a broad ripple effect on Democrats from the scandals, even some of the South's black Democratic members of Congress could be in danger this November.</p>
<p>The likelihood of expanded Republican power in the South and nation virtually guarantees that the 2000 Census will be conducted without the sampling needed to reduce the undercount of minorities. Even if the Supreme Court authorizes sampling, Republicans will likely have enough power in Congress to block use of the procedure in the 2000 Census. It means that  far more so than in 1980 or 1990, redistricting will be controlled by Republicans whose power depends greatly on white votes. And it means less support for affirmative action and civil rights programs.</p>
<p>There is no quick fix for the declining electoral prospects of Democrats. The party may have to undergo a large-scale reconstruction like the Republicans pulled off in the 1970s. New issues are on the horizon of the twenty-first century. Among others, these include: the nation's potentially ruinous entitlement obligations; the increasing concentration of income and wealth among a small segment of the population; inequality in educational opportunity; genuine reform of the political system; the corrosive effects of the global economy; and, ongoing racial divisions.</p>
<p>If the Democratic party is to thrive in the new millennium, it cannot simply accommodate itself to Republicans. The party needs to seize control of the battle for new ideas, reinvigorate its grassroots base, and develop new mechanisms for communicating its ideas to the public.</p>
	    </div2>

            <div2 id="v20-3.005" n="When A Black Face Turns Away White Votes..." type="Article">
               <head>When A Black Face Turns Away White Votes...</head>
               <docAuthor>By Keith Reeves </docAuthor>
               <docDate>Vol. 20, No. 3, 1998</docDate>
<argument><p>Keith Reeves is an associate professor of public policy in the John F. Kennedy School of Government at Harvard University. He was an expert witness in Hays v. Louisiana, III, a federal court challenge to the creation of Louisiana's Fourth majority-black congressional district.</p></argument>

<p>In the wake of the Supreme Court's flawed but significant rulings on race-based districting, two central questions remain: What happens when a black face turns away white votes and can blacks be elected from settings where whites comprise a majority of the population? With the Court's developing jurisprudence of racial gerrymandering, racial pluralism in Congress has been dealt a signifcant blow.</p>
<p>In the entire checkered history of this country, only nine blacks have ever won election to the U.S. Congress from election districts where whites were overwhelmingly in the majority. Following the 1990 reapportionment, black congresspersons were elected from Florida for the first time ever, and from Alabama, North Carolina, South Carolina, and Virginia for the first time in more than a century. </p>
<p>One of those riding the crest of political change in 1992 was Louisiana's Cleo Fields, the twenty-nine year-old state senator from Baton Rouge. With prodding from the Department of Justice, the state legislature interpreted the 1982 proviso to the Voting Rights Act to mean that "where a majority-black district could be created, one must be created." Thus, to gain approval of its reapportionment plan, it carved out the district from which Fields was elected. Of seven congressional districts, Louisiana now had two that were predominantly black-the Second and the Fourth. William Jefferson's geographically compact Second District in the New Orleans region was relatively easy to configure(see  map). By stark contrast, Field's widely dispersed district, the "'Z' with drips" district stretched from the northwestern city of Shreveport to his home base of Baton Rouge.</p>

<p>But the Justice Department's policy of creating majority-black districts met with fierce criticism. Disputants charged that the districts convey the impression that voters were segregated on the basis of race, in violation of the Equal Protection Clause of the Fourteenth Amendment. Furthermore, intentional racially configured voting districts, they alleged, "raise the specter of racial quotas, deepening racial and ethnic cleavages, and minority political ghettos." "These districts are reserved for black candidates; no white candidates need apply," one detractor argued. Besides wrote another, "[r]ace relations suffer when 'electoral remedies' favor one racial group."</p>
<p>Such sentiments resonated with the U.S. Supreme Court when it ruled
in 1993 (in <hi rend="italci">Shaw v. Reno</hi>) that the shape of two majority-black congressional districts in North Carolina were suspiciously race-driven and subordinated traditional districting practices such as geographical compactness and contiguity, in particular. The five-member conservative plurality, speaking through Justice Sandra Day O'Connor, reasoned: "So bizarre on its face" were the districts that it "rationally cannot be understood as anything other than an effort to segregate citizens into separate voting districts on the basis of race." </p>
<p>Indeed, O'Connor maintained that North Carolina's majority-black First and Twelfth districts resembled "the most egregious racial gerrymanders of the past" and, accordingly, violated the constitutional rights of all voters to participate in a "color-blind" electoral process. That said, North Carolina would have to demonstrate that its reapportionment plan was not drawn for an expressly racial purpose or, if so, that the plan was "narrowly tailored to further a compelling governmental interest." Contorted majority-black electoral districts in Florida, Georgia, Louisiana, and Texas, all drawn after the 1990 census, were now open to legal challenge by disaffected whites. </p>
<p>Meanwhile, the Court plurality applied its reasoning in <hi rend="italic">Shaw v. Reno</hi> two years later, when it invalidated Georgia's majority-black Eleventh District, represented by Cynthia McKinney, the state's first black congresswoman. The Court concluded that the state legislature's emphasis on race when it drew the boundary lines was "predominant" and thus unconstitutional. </p>
<p>Like it or not, a great many of us are left to contemplate the profound and vast implications of the Court's evisceration of race-based legislative districting. Justice John Paul Stevens grasped the dire, if not muddled, ramifications of the Court's rulings. In poignant, pointed language, he epitomized the concerns of many:  "The decisions issued...serve merely to reinforce my conviction that the Court has...struck out into a jurisprudential wilderness that...threatens to create harms more significant than any suffered by the individual plaintiffs challenging these districts....I cannot profess to know how the Court's developing jurisprudence of racial gerrymandering will alter the political and racial landscape in this Nation-although it certainly will alter that landscape."</p>
<p>As Steven Holmes of <hi rend="italic">The New York Times</hi> put it, "[T]he country will soon have to face a practical question that all those legislative contortions were intended to avoid: Will whites vote for black candidates?"</p>
<p>For the last several years, white and black Americans across the country have been engaged in polemic and contentious discussions about the perils of affirmative action. And, in some critics' minds, majority-black districting amounts to "affirmative action in the voting booth." This is a simplistic and trivial characterization of both the nature and extent of the problem. Race remains this country's deepest and most enduring division. Racial discrimination was the problem in the 1965 campaign for voting rights, and even after the passage of the Voting Rights Act that year, it remains so today.</p>
<p>The presumption was that stringent enforcement of this law would
remedy the problem of black voters' disfranchisement. And to a great extent, the legislation has. But thirty years after the passage of the act, an intractable problem remains that neither Congress, state legislatures nor the courts can ignore <hi rend="italic">the prevalence of racial bloc voting on the part of whites</hi>.</p>
<p>To date, virtually all of the electoral data on the prevalence of racial bloc voting has been in the aggregate registration and turnout figures. This information does not enable us to understand why citizens vote as they do.</p>
<p>To ascertain whether whites' political choices are motivated by racial animus, for example, I conducted a biracial campaign study experiment. Approximately 110 white respondents in the study were asked to read one of two news stories that described a hotly contested and racially polarized election campaign between two mayoral candidates. One group of respondents was given a news story about two white candidates while the other group was given the same story, only in this case the race of the two candidates was changed, one candidate was black, the other white. </p>
<p>A research investigation of this kind is significant for the following reasons. First, the study provides direct information about the motivations and sentiments underlying white voting behavior toward a black office-seeker. For instance, respondents were queried about their: (1) racial attitudes; (2) evaluation of the candidates; and (3) vote choices "if the election were held today." Second, the fact that many voting-rights disputes cover small jurisdictions or past events means that individual-level survey instruments for these cases are usually not available and cannot be constructed. This experimental campaign study enables us to peer inside the privacy of the ballot box. Third and most important, if it can be shown that whites' limited receptivity toward a black office-seeker is due to racial animus independent of political orientation, qualifications, and experience, age, reputation, or some other personal attribute is an affirmative remedy not warranted?</p>
<p>Thus, several striking conclusions emerge from this biracial election campaign study. First, the study showed conclusively that those whites who read the news story of the contest between the black and white candidate were reluctant to vote for that black candidate despite the fact that he possessed identical credentials, political experience, and personal characteristics as his white counterpart depicted in the other news story. Furthermore, the study found that in a racially polarized political campaign, whites' aversion to voting for a black candidate is associated with their attitudes, opinions, and stereotypes of black Americans as a categorical group. A black candidate seeking the support of white voters is evaluated accordingly. Such racial bias unfairly burdens black candidates who ought to have an equal opportunity to compete for elected office on the basis of their qualifications, experience, issue stances and personal character.</p>
<p>Racial bloc voting on the part of whites perniciously stacks the electoral deck against any black candidate, particularly in circumstances in which that candidate competes against a white opponent. One must ponder what it says about our society that thirty years after the tumultuous campaigns of the 1960s, a black American who runs for office is not afforded an equal opportunity to compete for white votes.</p>
<p>Americans of all political and ideological stripes must acknowledge racial bloc voting for what it is a formidable barrier to aspiring black political candidates. Until racial bloc voting diminishes, black-majority congressional districts are one appropriate and necessary means of ensuring that black candidates are afforded an equal opportunity to compete for, not win, office. This is not a special privilege. Rather, it is a remedy to level the political playing field. And although five redistricted black members of Congress were returned to office in 1996, it is beyond dispute that race loomed large in those elections.</p>
<p>The merits of majority-minority districting ought to be evaluated from the vantage point of bringing real meaning to notions of equal opportunity and racial pluralism. As the Supreme Court continues its wade into the "jurisprudential wilderness of racial gerrymandering," it is imperative that the justices affirm these fundamental concepts. To do so, they must come to grips with the fact, however dispiriting, that racial bias still plays a role in the voting booth.	</p>
	    </div2>



</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
